<inferno>
<heading>
    <title>The Divine Comedy</title>
    <sub_title>Canticle I: Inferno</sub_title>
    <author>Dante Alighieri</author>
    <translator>Henry Wadsworth Longfellow</translator>
    <pubinfo>INSERT TEXT HERE</pubinfo>
    <!-- What is the publication info?-->
</heading>

<toc>
    <item>I. The Dark Forest.  The Hill of Difficulty.  The Panther,
        the Lion, and the Wolf.  Virgil.</item>
    <item>II. The Descent.  Dante's Protest and Virgil's Appeal.
        The Intercession of the Three Ladies Benedight.</item>
    <item>III. The Gate of Hell.  The Inefficient or Indifferent.
        Pope Celestine V.  The Shores of Acheron.  Charon.
        The Earthquake and the Swoon.</item>
    <item>IV. The First Circle, Limbo: Virtuous Pagans and the Unbaptized.
        The Four Poets, Homer, Horace, Ovid, and Lucan.  The Noble
        Castle of Philosophy.</item>
    <item>V. The Second Circle: The Wanton.  Minos.  The Infernal Hurricane.
        Francesca da Rimini.</item>
    <item>VI. The Third Circle: The Gluttonous.  Cerberus.  The Eternal Rain.
        Ciacco.  Florence.</item>
    <item>VII. The Fourth Circle: The Avaricious and the Prodigal.
        Plutus.  Fortune and her Wheel.  The Fifth Circle:
        The Irascible and the Sullen.  Styx.</item>
    <item>VIII. Phlegyas.  Philippo Argenti.  The Gate of the City of Dis.</item>
    <item>IX. The Furies and Medusa.  The Angel.  The City of Dis.
        The Sixth Circle: Heresiarchs.</item>
    <item>X. Farinata and Cavalcante de' Cavalcanti.  Discourse on the
        Knowledge of the Damned.</item>
    <item>XI. The Broken Rocks.  Pope Anastasius.  General Description of
        the Inferno and its Divisions.</item>
    <item>XII. The Minotaur.  The Seventh Circle: The Violent.
        The River Phlegethon.  The Violent against their Neighbours.
        The Centaurs.  Tyrants.</item>
    <item>XIII. The Wood of Thorns.  The Harpies.  The Violent
        against themselves.  Suicides.  Pier della Vigna.
        Lano and Jacopo da Sant' Andrea.</item>
    <item>XIV. The Sand Waste and the Rain of Fire.  The Violent against God.
        Capaneus.  The Statue of Time, and the Four Infernal Rivers.</item>
    <item>XV. The Violent against Nature.  Brunetto Latini.</item>
    <item>XVI. Guidoguerra, Aldobrandi, and Rusticucci.  Cataract of
        the River of Blood.</item>
    <item>XVII. Geryon.  The Violent against Art.  Usurers.  Descent into
        the Abyss of Malebolge.</item>
    <item>XVIII. The Eighth Circle, Malebolge: The Fraudulent and
        the Malicious.  The First Bolgia: Seducers and Panders.
        Venedico Caccianimico.  Jason.  The Second Bolgia:
        Flatterers.  Allessio Interminelli.  Thais.</item>
    <item>XIX. The Third Bolgia: Simoniacs.  Pope Nicholas III.
        Dante's Reproof of corrupt Prelates.</item>
    <item>XX. The Fourth Bolgia: Soothsayers.  Amphiaraus, Tiresias, Aruns,
        Manto, Eryphylus, Michael Scott, Guido Bonatti, and Asdente.
        Virgil reproaches Dante's Pity.  Mantua's Foundation.</item>
    <item>XXI. The Fifth Bolgia: Peculators.  The Elder of Santa Zita.
        Malacoda and other Devils.</item>
    <item>XXII. Ciampolo, Friar Gomita, and Michael Zanche.
        The Malabranche quarrel.</item>
    <item>XXIII. Escape from the Malabranche.  The Sixth Bolgia: Hypocrites.
        Catalano and Loderingo.  Caiaphas.</item>
    <item>XXIV. The Seventh Bolgia: Thieves.  Vanni Fucci.  Serpents.</item>
    <item>XXV. Vanni Fucci's Punishment.  Agnello Brunelleschi,
        Buoso degli Abati, Puccio Sciancato, Cianfa de' Donati,
        and Guercio Cavalcanti.</item>
    <item>XXVI. The Eighth Bolgia: Evil Counsellors.  Ulysses and Diomed.
        Ulysses' Last Voyage.</item>
    <item>XXVII. Guido da Montefeltro.  His deception by Pope Boniface VIII.</item>
    <item>XXVIII. The Ninth Bolgia: Schismatics.  Mahomet and Ali.
        Pier da Medicina, Curio, Mosca, and Bertrand de Born.</item>
    <item> XXIX. Geri del Bello.  The Tenth Bolgia: Alchemists.
        Griffolino d' Arezzo and Capocchino.</item>
    <item>XXX. Other Falsifiers or Forgers.  Gianni Schicchi, Myrrha,
        Adam of Brescia, Potiphar's Wife, and Sinon of Troy.</item>
    <item>XXXI. The Giants, Nimrod, Ephialtes, and Antaeus.
        Descent to Cocytus.</item>
    <item>XXXII. The Ninth Circle: Traitors.  The Frozen Lake of Cocytus.
        First Division, Caina: Traitors to their Kindred.
        Camicion de' Pazzi.  Second Division, Antenora:
        Traitors to their Country.  Dante questions
        Bocca degli Abati.  Buoso da Duera.</item>
    <item>XXXIII. Count Ugolino and the Archbishop Ruggieri.  The Death
        of Count Ugolino's Sons.  Third Division of the Ninth Circle,
        Ptolomaea: Traitors to their Friends.  Friar Alberigo,
        Branco d' Oria.</item>
    <item>XXXIV. Fourth Division of the Ninth Circle, the Judecca:
        Traitors to their Lords and Benefactors.  Lucifer,
        Judas Iscariot, Brutus, and Cassius. The Chasm of Lethe.
        The Ascent.</item>
</toc>
</inferno>
