<?xml-model href="inferno_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<inferno>
    <heading>
        <title>The Divine Comedy</title>
        <sub_title>Canticle I: Inferno</sub_title>
        <author>Dante Alighieri</author>
        <translator>Henry Wadsworth Longfellow</translator>
        <pubinfo>INSERT TEXT HERE</pubinfo>
        <!-- What is the publication info?-->
    </heading>
    
    <toc>
        <item>I. The Dark Forest.  The Hill of Difficulty.  The Panther,
            the Lion, and the Wolf.  Virgil.</item>
        <item>II. The Descent.  Dante's Protest and Virgil's Appeal.
            The Intercession of the Three Ladies Benedight.</item>
        <item>III. The Gate of Hell.  The Inefficient or Indifferent.
            Pope Celestine V.  The Shores of Acheron.  Charon.
            The Earthquake and the Swoon.</item>
        <item>IV. The First Circle, Limbo: Virtuous Pagans and the Unbaptized.
            The Four Poets, Homer, Horace, Ovid, and Lucan.  The Noble
            Castle of Philosophy.</item>
        <item>V. The Second Circle: The Wanton.  Minos.  The Infernal Hurricane.
            Francesca da Rimini.</item>
        <item>VI. The Third Circle: The Gluttonous.  Cerberus.  The Eternal Rain.
            Ciacco.  Florence.</item>
        <item>VII. The Fourth Circle: The Avaricious and the Prodigal.
            Plutus.  Fortune and her Wheel.  The Fifth Circle:
            The Irascible and the Sullen.  Styx.</item>
        <item>VIII. Phlegyas.  Philippo Argenti.  The Gate of the City of Dis.</item>
        <item>IX. The Furies and Medusa.  The Angel.  The City of Dis.
            The Sixth Circle: Heresiarchs.</item>
        <item>X. Farinata and Cavalcante de' Cavalcanti.  Discourse on the
            Knowledge of the Damned.</item>
        <item>XI. The Broken Rocks.  Pope Anastasius.  General Description of
            the Inferno and its Divisions.</item>
        <item>XII. The Minotaur.  The Seventh Circle: The Violent.
            The River Phlegethon.  The Violent against their Neighbours.
            The Centaurs.  Tyrants.</item>
        <item>XIII. The Wood of Thorns.  The Harpies.  The Violent
            against themselves.  Suicides.  Pier della Vigna.
            Lano and Jacopo da Sant' Andrea.</item>
        <item>XIV. The Sand Waste and the Rain of Fire.  The Violent against God.
            Capaneus.  The Statue of Time, and the Four Infernal Rivers.</item>
        <item>XV. The Violent against Nature.  Brunetto Latini.</item>
        <item>XVI. Guidoguerra, Aldobrandi, and Rusticucci.  Cataract of
            the River of Blood.</item>
        <item>XVII. Geryon.  The Violent against Art.  Usurers.  Descent into
            the Abyss of Malebolge.</item>
        <item>XVIII. The Eighth Circle, Malebolge: The Fraudulent and
            the Malicious.  The First Bolgia: Seducers and Panders.
            Venedico Caccianimico.  Jason.  The Second Bolgia:
            Flatterers.  Allessio Interminelli.  Thais.</item>
        <item>XIX. The Third Bolgia: Simoniacs.  Pope Nicholas III.
            Dante's Reproof of corrupt Prelates.</item>
        <item>XX. The Fourth Bolgia: Soothsayers.  Amphiaraus, Tiresias, Aruns,
            Manto, Eryphylus, Michael Scott, Guido Bonatti, and Asdente.
            Virgil reproaches Dante's Pity.  Mantua's Foundation.</item>
        <item>XXI. The Fifth Bolgia: Peculators.  The Elder of Santa Zita.
            Malacoda and other Devils.</item>
        <item>XXII. Ciampolo, Friar Gomita, and Michael Zanche.
            The Malabranche quarrel.</item>
        <item>XXIII. Escape from the Malabranche.  The Sixth Bolgia: Hypocrites.
            Catalano and Loderingo.  Caiaphas.</item>
        <item>XXIV. The Seventh Bolgia: Thieves.  Vanni Fucci.  Serpents.</item>
        <item>XXV. Vanni Fucci's Punishment.  Agnello Brunelleschi,
            Buoso degli Abati, Puccio Sciancato, Cianfa de' Donati,
            and Guercio Cavalcanti.</item>
        <item>XXVI. The Eighth Bolgia: Evil Counsellors.  Ulysses and Diomed.
            Ulysses' Last Voyage.</item>
        <item>XXVII. Guido da Montefeltro.  His deception by Pope Boniface VIII.</item>
        <item>XXVIII. The Ninth Bolgia: Schismatics.  Mahomet and Ali.
            Pier da Medicina, Curio, Mosca, and Bertrand de Born.</item>
        <item> XXIX. Geri del Bello.  The Tenth Bolgia: Alchemists.
            Griffolino d' Arezzo and Capocchino.</item>
        <item>XXX. Other Falsifiers or Forgers.  Gianni Schicchi, Myrrha,
            Adam of Brescia, Potiphar's Wife, and Sinon of Troy.</item>
        <item>XXXI. The Giants, Nimrod, Ephialtes, and Antaeus.
            Descent to Cocytus.</item>
        <item>XXXII. The Ninth Circle: Traitors.  The Frozen Lake of Cocytus.
            First Division, Caina: Traitors to their Kindred.
            Camicion de' Pazzi.  Second Division, Antenora:
            Traitors to their Country.  Dante questions
            Bocca degli Abati.  Buoso da Duera.</item>
        <item>XXXIII. Count Ugolino and the Archbishop Ruggieri.  The Death
            of Count Ugolino's Sons.  Third Division of the Ninth Circle,
            Ptolomaea: Traitors to their Friends.  Friar Alberigo,
            Branco d' Oria.</item>
        <item>XXXIV. Fourth Division of the Ninth Circle, the Judecca:
            Traitors to their Lords and Benefactors.  Lucifer,
            Judas Iscariot, Brutus, and Cassius. The Chasm of Lethe.
            The Ascent.</item>
    </toc>

<body>

<canto numeral="I"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>Midway upon the journey of our life
<lb/>I found myself within a forest dark,
<lb/>For the straightforward pathway had been lost.

<sb/>
<lb/>Ah me! how hard a thing it is to say
<lb/>What was this forest savage, rough, and stern,
<lb/>Which in the very thought renews the fear.

<sb/>
<lb/>So bitter is it, death is little more;
<lb/>But of the good to treat, which there I found,
<lb/>Speak will I of the other things I saw there.

<sb/>
<lb/>I cannot well repeat how there I entered,
<lb/>So full was I of slumber at the moment
<lb/>In which I had abandoned the true way.

<sb/>
<lb/>But after I had reached a mountain's foot,
<lb/>At that point where the valley terminated,
<lb/>Which had with consternation pierced my heart,

<sb/>
<lb/>Upward I looked, and I beheld its shoulders,
<lb/>Vested already with that planet's rays
<lb/>Which leadeth others right by every road.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then was the fear a little quieted
<lb/>That in my heart's lake had endured throughout
<lb/>The night, which I had passed so piteously.

<sb/>
<lb/>And even as he, who, with distressful breath,
<lb/>Forth issued from the sea upon the shore,
<lb/>Turns to the water perilous and gazes;

<sb/>
<lb/>So did my soul, that still was fleeing onward,
<lb/>Turn itself back to re-behold the pass
<lb/>Which never yet a living person left.

<sb/>
<lb/>After my weary body I had rested,
<lb/>The way resumed I on the desert slope,
<lb/>So that the firm foot ever was the lower.

<sb/>
<lb/>And lo! almost where the ascent began,
<lb/>A panther light and swift exceedingly,
<lb/>Which with a spotted skin was covered o'er!

<sb/>
<lb/>And never moved she from before my face,
<lb/>Nay, rather did impede so much my way,
<lb/>That many times I to return had turned.

<sb/>
<lb/>The time was the beginning of the morning,
<lb/>And up the sun was mounting with those stars
<lb/>That with him were, what time the Love Divine

<sb/>
<lb/>At first in motion set those beauteous things;
<lb/>So were to me occasion of good hope,
<lb/>The variegated skin of that wild beast,

<sb/>
<lb/>The hour of time, and the delicious season;
<lb/>But not so much, that did not give me fear
<lb/>A lion's aspect which appeared to me.

<sb/>
<lb/>He seemed as if against me he were coming
<lb/>With head uplifted, and with ravenous hunger,
<lb/>So that it seemed the air was afraid of him;

<sb/>
<lb/>And a she-wolf, that with all hungerings
<lb/>Seemed to be laden in her meagreness,
<lb/>And many folk has caused to live forlorn!

<sb/>
<lb/>She brought upon me so much heaviness,
<lb/>With the affright that from her aspect came,
<lb/>That I the hope relinquished of the height.

<sb/>
<lb/>And as he is who willingly acquires,
<lb/>And the time comes that causes him to lose,
<lb/>Who weeps in all his thoughts and is despondent,

<sb/>
<lb/>E'en such made me that beast withouten peace,
<lb/>Which, coming on against me by degrees
<lb/>Thrust me back thither where the sun is silent.

<sb/>
<lb/>While I was rushing downward to the lowland,
<lb/>Before mine eyes did one present himself,
<lb/>Who seemed from long-continued silence hoarse.

<sb/>
<lb/>When I beheld him in the desert vast,
<lb/>"Have pity on me," unto him I cried,
<lb/>"Whiche'er thou art, or shade or real man!"

<sb/>
<lb/>He answered me: "Not man; man once I was,
<lb/>And both my parents were of Lombardy,
<lb/>And Mantuans by country both of them.

<sb/>
<lb/>'Sub Julio' was I born, though it was late,
<lb/>And lived at Rome under the good Augustus,
<lb/>During the time of false and lying gods.

<sb/>
<lb/>A poet was I, and I sang that just
<lb/>Son of Anchises, who came forth from Troy,
<lb/>After that Ilion the superb was burned.

<sb/>
<lb/>But thou, why goest thou back to such annoyance?
<lb/>Why climb'st thou not the Mount Delectable,
<lb/>Which is the source and cause of every joy?"

<sb/>
<lb/>"Now, art thou that Virgilius and that fountain
<lb/>Which spreads abroad so wide a river of speech?"
<lb/>I made response to him with bashful forehead.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O, of the other poets honour and light,
<lb/>Avail me the long study and great love
<lb/>That have impelled me to explore thy volume!

<sb/>
<lb/>Thou art my master, and my author thou,
<lb/>Thou art alone the one from whom I took
<lb/>The beautiful style that has done honour to me.

<sb/>
<lb/>Behold the beast, for which I have turned back;
<lb/>Do thou protect me from her, famous Sage,
<lb/>For she doth make my veins and pulses tremble."

<sb/>
<lb/>"Thee it behoves to take another road,"
<lb/>Responded he, when he beheld me weeping,
<lb/>"If from this savage place thou wouldst escape;

<sb/>
<lb/>Because this beast, at which thou criest out,
<lb/>Suffers not any one to pass her way,
<lb/>But so doth harass him, that she destroys him;

<sb/>
<lb/>And has a nature so malign and ruthless,
<lb/>That never doth she glut her greedy will,
<lb/>And after food is hungrier than before.

<sb/>
<lb/>Many the animals with whom she weds,
<lb/>And more they shall be still, until the Greyhound
<lb/>Comes, who shall make her perish in her pain.

<sb/>
<lb/>He shall not feed on either earth or pelf,
<lb/>But upon wisdom, and on love and virtue;
<lb/>'Twixt Feltro and Feltro shall his nation be;

<sb/>
<lb/>Of that low Italy shall he be the saviour,
<lb/>On whose account the maid Camilla died,
<lb/>Euryalus, Turnus, Nisus, of their wounds;

<sb/>
<lb/>Through every city shall he hunt her down,
<lb/>Until he shall have driven her back to Hell,
<lb/>There from whence envy first did let her loose.

<sb/>
<lb/>Therefore I think and judge it for thy best
<lb/>Thou follow me, and I will be thy guide,
<lb/>And lead thee hence through the eternal place,

<sb/>
<lb/>Where thou shalt hear the desperate lamentations,
<lb/>Shalt see the ancient spirits disconsolate,
<lb/>Who cry out each one for the second death;

<sb/>
<lb/>And thou shalt see those who contented are
<lb/>Within the fire, because they hope to come,
<lb/>Whene'er it may be, to the blessed people;

<sb/>
<lb/>To whom, then, if thou wishest to ascend,
<lb/>A soul shall be for that than I more worthy;
<lb/>With her at my departure I will leave thee;

<sb/>
<lb/>Because that Emperor, who reigns above,
<lb/>In that I was rebellious to his law,
<lb/>Wills that through me none come into his city.

<sb/>
<lb/>He governs everywhere, and there he reigns;
<lb/>There is his city and his lofty throne;
<lb/>O happy he whom thereto he elects!"

<sb/>
<lb/>And I to him: "Poet, I thee entreat,
<lb/>By that same God whom thou didst never know,
<lb/>So that I may escape this woe and worse,

<sb/>
<lb/>Thou wouldst conduct me there where thou hast said,
<lb/>That I may see the portal of Saint Peter,
<lb/>And those thou makest so disconsolate."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then he moved on, and I behind him followed.

<canto numeral="II"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>Day was departing, and the embrowned air
<lb/>Released the animals that are on earth
<lb/>From their fatigues; and I the only one

<sb/>
<lb/>Made myself ready to sustain the war,
<lb/>Both of the way and likewise of the woe,
<lb/>Which memory that errs not shall retrace.

<sb/>
<lb/>O Muses, O high genius, now assist me!
<lb/>O memory, that didst write down what I saw,
<lb/>Here thy nobility shall be manifest!

<sb/>
<lb/>And I began: "Poet, who guidest me,
<lb/>Regard my manhood, if it be sufficient,
<lb/>Ere to the arduous pass thou dost confide me.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thou sayest, that of Silvius the parent,
<lb/>While yet corruptible, unto the world
<lb/>Immortal went, and was there bodily.

<sb/>
<lb/>But if the adversary of all evil
<lb/>Was courteous, thinking of the high effect
<lb/>That issue would from him, and who, and what,

<sb/>
<lb/>To men of intellect unmeet it seems not;
<lb/>For he was of great Rome, and of her empire
<lb/>In the empyreal heaven as father chosen;

<sb/>
<lb/>The which and what, wishing to speak the truth,
<lb/>Were stablished as the holy place, wherein
<lb/>Sits the successor of the greatest Peter.

<sb/>
<lb/>Upon this journey, whence thou givest him vaunt,
<lb/>Things did he hear, which the occasion were
<lb/>Both of his victory and the papal mantle.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thither went afterwards the Chosen Vessel,
<lb/>To bring back comfort thence unto that Faith,
<lb/>Which of salvation's way is the beginning.

<sb/>
<lb/>But I, why thither come, or who concedes it?
<lb/>I not Aeneas am, I am not Paul,
<lb/>Nor I, nor others, think me worthy of it.

<sb/>
<lb/>Therefore, if I resign myself to come,
<lb/>I fear the coming may be ill-advised;
<lb/>Thou'rt wise, and knowest better than I speak."

<sb/>
<lb/>And as he is, who unwills what he willed,
<lb/>And by new thoughts doth his intention change,
<lb/>So that from his design he quite withdraws,

<sb/>
<lb/>Such I became, upon that dark hillside,
<lb/>Because, in thinking, I consumed the emprise,
<lb/>Which was so very prompt in the beginning.

<sb/>
<lb/>"If I have well thy language understood,"
<lb/>Replied that shade of the Magnanimous,
<lb/>"Thy soul attainted is with cowardice,

<sb/>
<lb/>Which many times a man encumbers so,
<lb/>It turns him back from honoured enterprise,
<lb/>As false sight doth a beast, when he is shy.

<sb/>
<lb/>That thou mayst free thee from this apprehension,
<lb/>I'll tell thee why I came, and what I heard
<lb/>At the first moment when I grieved for thee.

<sb/>
<lb/>Among those was I who are in suspense,
<lb/>And a fair, saintly Lady called to me
<lb/>In such wise, I besought her to command me.

<sb/>
<lb/>Her eyes where shining brighter than the Star;
<lb/>And she began to say, gentle and low,
<lb/>With voice angelical, in her own language:

<sb/>
<lb/>'O spirit courteous of Mantua,
<lb/>Of whom the fame still in the world endures,
<lb/>And shall endure, long-lasting as the world;

<sb/>
<lb/>A friend of mine, and not the friend of fortune,
<lb/>Upon the desert slope is so impeded
<lb/>Upon his way, that he has turned through terror,

<sb/>
<lb/>And may, I fear, already be so lost,
<lb/>That I too late have risen to his succour,
<lb/>From that which I have heard of him in Heaven.

<sb/>
<lb/>Bestir thee now, and with thy speech ornate,
<lb/>And with what needful is for his release,
<lb/>Assist him so, that I may be consoled.

<sb/>
<lb/>Beatrice am I, who do bid thee go;
<lb/>I come from there, where I would fain return;
<lb/>Love moved me, which compelleth me to speak.

<sb/>
<lb/>When I shall be in presence of my Lord,
<lb/>Full often will I praise thee unto him.'
<lb/>Then paused she, and thereafter I began:

<sb/>
<lb/>'O Lady of virtue, thou alone through whom
<lb/>The human race exceedeth all contained
<lb/>Within the heaven that has the lesser circles,

<sb/>
<lb/>So grateful unto me is thy commandment,
<lb/>To obey, if 'twere already done, were late;
<lb/>No farther need'st thou ope to me thy wish.

<sb/>
<lb/>But the cause tell me why thou dost not shun
<lb/>The here descending down into this centre,
<lb/>From the vast place thou burnest to return to.'

<sb/>
<lb/>'Since thou wouldst fain so inwardly discern,
<lb/>Briefly will I relate,' she answered me,
<lb/>'Why I am not afraid to enter here.

<sb/>
<lb/>Of those things only should one be afraid
<lb/>Which have the power of doing others harm;
<lb/>Of the rest, no; because they are not fearful.

<sb/>
<lb/>God in his mercy such created me
<lb/>That misery of yours attains me not,
<lb/>Nor any flame assails me of this burning.

<sb/>
<lb/>A gentle Lady is in Heaven, who grieves
<lb/>At this impediment, to which I send thee,
<lb/>So that stern judgment there above is broken.

<sb/>
<lb/>In her entreaty she besought Lucia,
<lb/>And said, "Thy faithful one now stands in need
<lb/>Of thee, and unto thee I recommend him."

<sb/>
<lb/>Lucia, foe of all that cruel is,
<lb/>Hastened away, and came unto the place
<lb/>Where I was sitting with the ancient Rachel.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Beatrice" said she, "the true praise of God,
<lb/>Why succourest thou not him, who loved thee so,
<lb/>For thee he issued from the vulgar herd?

<sb/>
<lb/>Dost thou not hear the pity of his plaint?
<lb/>Dost thou not see the death that combats him
<lb/>Beside that flood, where ocean has no vaunt?"

<sb/>
<lb/>Never were persons in the world so swift
<lb/>To work their weal and to escape their woe,
<lb/>As I, after such words as these were uttered,

<sb/>
<lb/>Came hither downward from my blessed seat,
<lb/>Confiding in thy dignified discourse,
<lb/>Which honours thee, and those who've listened to it.'

<sb/>
<lb/>After she thus had spoken unto me,
<lb/>Weeping, her shining eyes she turned away;
<lb/>Whereby she made me swifter in my coming;

<sb/>
<lb/>And unto thee I came, as she desired;
<lb/>I have delivered thee from that wild beast,
<lb/>Which barred the beautiful mountain's short ascent.

<sb/>
<lb/>What is it, then?  Why, why dost thou delay?
<lb/>Why is such baseness bedded in thy heart?
<lb/>Daring and hardihood why hast thou not,

<sb/>
<lb/>Seeing that three such Ladies benedight
<lb/>Are caring for thee in the court of Heaven,
<lb/>And so much good my speech doth promise thee?"

<sb/>
<lb/>Even as the flowerets, by nocturnal chill,
<lb/>Bowed down and closed, when the sun whitens them,
<lb/>Uplift themselves all open on their stems;

<sb/>
<lb/>Such I became with my exhausted strength,
<lb/>And such good courage to my heart there coursed,
<lb/>That I began, like an intrepid person:

<sb/>
<lb/>"O she compassionate, who succoured me,
<lb/>And courteous thou, who hast obeyed so soon
<lb/>The words of truth which she addressed to thee!

<sb/>
<lb/>Thou hast my heart so with desire disposed
<lb/>To the adventure, with these words of thine,
<lb/>That to my first intent I have returned.

<sb/>
<lb/>Now go, for one sole will is in us both,
<lb/>Thou Leader, and thou Lord, and Master thou."
<lb/>Thus said I to him; and when he had moved,

<sb/>
<lb/>I entered on the deep and savage way.

<canto numeral="III"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>"Through me the way is to the city dolent;
<lb/>Through me the way is to eternal dole;
<lb/>Through me the way among the people lost.

<sb/>
<lb/>Justice incited my sublime Creator;
<lb/>Created me divine Omnipotence,
<lb/>The highest Wisdom and the primal Love.

<sb/>
<lb/>Before me there were no created things,
<lb/>Only eterne, and I eternal last.
<lb/>All hope abandon, ye who enter in!"

<sb/>
<lb/>These words in sombre colour I beheld
<lb/>Written upon the summit of a gate;
<lb/>Whence I: "Their sense is, Master, hard to me!"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me, as one experienced:
<lb/>"Here all suspicion needs must be abandoned,
<lb/>All cowardice must needs be here extinct.

<sb/>
<lb/>We to the place have come, where I have told thee
<lb/>Thou shalt behold the people dolorous
<lb/>Who have foregone the good of intellect."

<sb/>
<lb/>And after he had laid his hand on mine
<lb/>With joyful mien, whence I was comforted,
<lb/>He led me in among the secret things.

<sb/>
<lb/>There sighs, complaints, and ululations loud
<lb/>Resounded through the air without a star,
<lb/>Whence I, at the beginning, wept thereat.

<sb/>
<lb/>Languages diverse, horrible dialects,
<lb/>Accents of anger, words of agony,
<lb/>And voices high and hoarse, with sound of hands,

<sb/>
<lb/>Made up a tumult that goes whirling on
<lb/>For ever in that air for ever black,
<lb/>Even as the sand doth, when the whirlwind breathes.

<sb/>
<lb/>And I, who had my head with horror bound,
<lb/>Said: "Master, what is this which now I hear?
<lb/>What folk is this, which seems by pain so vanquished?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "This miserable mode
<lb/>Maintain the melancholy souls of those
<lb/>Who lived withouten infamy or praise.

<sb/>
<lb/>Commingled are they with that caitiff choir
<lb/>Of Angels, who have not rebellious been,
<lb/>Nor faithful were to God, but were for self.

<sb/>
<lb/>The heavens expelled them, not to be less fair;
<lb/>Nor them the nethermore abyss receives,
<lb/>For glory none the damned would have from them."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I: "O Master, what so grievous is
<lb/>To these, that maketh them lament so sore?"
<lb/>He answered: "I will tell thee very briefly.

<sb/>
<lb/>These have no longer any hope of death;
<lb/>And this blind life of theirs is so debased,
<lb/>They envious are of every other fate.

<sb/>
<lb/>No fame of them the world permits to be;
<lb/>Misericord and Justice both disdain them.
<lb/>Let us not speak of them, but look, and pass."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I, who looked again, beheld a banner,
<lb/>Which, whirling round, ran on so rapidly,
<lb/>That of all pause it seemed to me indignant;

<sb/>
<lb/>And after it there came so long a train
<lb/>Of people, that I ne'er would have believed
<lb/>That ever Death so many had undone.

<sb/>
<lb/>When some among them I had recognised,
<lb/>I looked, and I beheld the shade of him
<lb/>Who made through cowardice the great refusal.

<sb/>
<lb/>Forthwith I comprehended, and was certain,
<lb/>That this the sect was of the caitiff wretches
<lb/>Hateful to God and to his enemies.

<sb/>
<lb/>These miscreants, who never were alive,
<lb/>Were naked, and were stung exceedingly
<lb/>By gadflies and by hornets that were there.

<sb/>
<lb/>These did their faces irrigate with blood,
<lb/>Which, with their tears commingled, at their feet
<lb/>By the disgusting worms was gathered up.

<sb/>
<lb/>And when to gazing farther I betook me.
<lb/>People I saw on a great river's bank;
<lb/>Whence said I: "Master, now vouchsafe to me,

<sb/>
<lb/>That I may know who these are, and what law
<lb/>Makes them appear so ready to pass over,
<lb/>As I discern athwart the dusky light."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "These things shall all be known
<lb/>To thee, as soon as we our footsteps stay
<lb/>Upon the dismal shore of Acheron."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then with mine eyes ashamed and downward cast,
<lb/>Fearing my words might irksome be to him,
<lb/>From speech refrained I till we reached the river.

<sb/>
<lb/>And lo! towards us coming in a boat
<lb/>An old man, hoary with the hair of eld,
<lb/>Crying: "Woe unto you, ye souls depraved!

<sb/>
<lb/>Hope nevermore to look upon the heavens;
<lb/>I come to lead you to the other shore,
<lb/>To the eternal shades in heat and frost.

<sb/>
<lb/>And thou, that yonder standest, living soul,
<lb/>Withdraw thee from these people, who are dead!"
<lb/>But when he saw that I did not withdraw,

<sb/>
<lb/>He said: "By other ways, by other ports
<lb/>Thou to the shore shalt come, not here, for passage;
<lb/>A lighter vessel needs must carry thee."

<sb/>
<lb/>And unto him the Guide: "Vex thee not, Charon;
<lb/>It is so willed there where is power to do
<lb/>That which is willed; and farther question not."

<sb/>
<lb/>Thereat were quieted the fleecy cheeks
<lb/>Of him the ferryman of the livid fen,
<lb/>Who round about his eyes had wheels of flame.

<sb/>
<lb/>But all those souls who weary were and naked
<lb/>Their colour changed and gnashed their teeth together,
<lb/>As soon as they had heard those cruel words.

<sb/>
<lb/>God they blasphemed and their progenitors,
<lb/>The human race, the place, the time, the seed
<lb/>Of their engendering and of their birth!

<sb/>
<lb/>Thereafter all together they drew back,
<lb/>Bitterly weeping, to the accursed shore,
<lb/>Which waiteth every man who fears not God.

<sb/>
<lb/>Charon the demon, with the eyes of glede,
<lb/>Beckoning to them, collects them all together,
<lb/>Beats with his oar whoever lags behind.

<sb/>
<lb/>As in the autumn-time the leaves fall off,
<lb/>First one and then another, till the branch
<lb/>Unto the earth surrenders all its spoils;

<sb/>
<lb/>In similar wise the evil seed of Adam
<lb/>Throw themselves from that margin one by one,
<lb/>At signals, as a bird unto its lure.

<sb/>
<lb/>So they depart across the dusky wave,
<lb/>And ere upon the other side they land,
<lb/>Again on this side a new troop assembles.

<sb/>
<lb/>"My son," the courteous Master said to me,
<lb/>"All those who perish in the wrath of God
<lb/>Here meet together out of every land;

<sb/>
<lb/>And ready are they to pass o'er the river,
<lb/>Because celestial Justice spurs them on,
<lb/>So that their fear is turned into desire.

<sb/>
<lb/>This way there never passes a good soul;
<lb/>And hence if Charon doth complain of thee,
<lb/>Well mayst thou know now what his speech imports."

<sb/>
<lb/>This being finished, all the dusk champaign
<lb/>Trembled so violently, that of that terror
<lb/>The recollection bathes me still with sweat.

<sb/>
<lb/>The land of tears gave forth a blast of wind,
<lb/>And fulminated a vermilion light,
<lb/>Which overmastered in me every sense,

<sb/>
<lb/>And as a man whom sleep hath seized I fell.

<circle number="1" main_sin="not_christian">

<canto numeral="IV"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>Broke the deep lethargy within my head
<lb/>A heavy thunder, so that I upstarted,
<lb/>Like to a person who by force is wakened;

<sb/>
<lb/>And round about I moved my rested eyes,
<lb/>Uprisen erect, and steadfastly I gazed,
<lb/>To recognise the place wherein I was.

<sb/>
<lb/>True is it, that upon the verge I found me
<lb/>Of the abysmal valley dolorous,
<lb/>That gathers thunder of infinite ululations.

<sb/>
<lb/>Obscure, profound it was, and nebulous,
<lb/>So that by fixing on its depths my sight
<lb/>Nothing whatever I discerned therein.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Let us descend now into the blind world,"
<lb/>Began the Poet, pallid utterly;
<lb/>"I will be first, and thou shalt second be."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I, who of his colour was aware,
<lb/>Said: "How shall I come, if thou art afraid,
<lb/>Who'rt wont to be a comfort to my fears?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "The anguish of the people
<lb/>Who are below here in my face depicts
<lb/>That pity which for terror thou hast taken.

<sb/>
<lb/>Let us go on, for the long way impels us."
<lb/>Thus he went in, and thus he made me enter
<lb/>The foremost circle that surrounds the abyss.

<sb/>
<lb/>There, as it seemed to me from listening,
<lb/>Were lamentations none, but only sighs,
<lb/>That tremble made the everlasting air.

<sb/>
<lb/>And this arose from sorrow without torment,
<lb/>Which the crowds had, that many were and great,
<lb/>Of infants and of women and of men.

<sb/>
<lb/>To me the Master good: "Thou dost not ask
<lb/>What spirits these, which thou beholdest, are?
<lb/>Now will I have thee know, ere thou go farther,

<sb/>
<lb/>That they sinned not; and if they merit had,
<lb/>'Tis not enough, because they had not baptism
<lb/>Which is the portal of the Faith thou holdest;

<sb/>
<lb/>And if they were before Christianity,
<lb/>In the right manner they adored not God;
<lb/>And among such as these am I myself.

<sb/>
<lb/>For such defects, and not for other guilt,
<lb/>Lost are we and are only so far punished,
<lb/>That without hope we live on in desire."

<sb/>
<lb/>Great grief seized on my heart when this I heard,
<lb/>Because some people of much worthiness
<lb/>I knew, who in that Limbo were suspended.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Tell me, my Master, tell me, thou my Lord,"
<lb/>Began I, with desire of being certain
<lb/>Of that Faith which o'ercometh every error,

<sb/>
<lb/>"Came any one by his own merit hence,
<lb/>Or by another's, who was blessed thereafter?"
<lb/>And he, who understood my covert speech,

<sb/>
<lb/>Replied: "I was a novice in this state,
<lb/>When I saw hither come a Mighty One,
<lb/>With sign of victory incoronate.

<sb/>
<lb/>Hence he drew forth the shade of the First Parent,
<lb/>And that of his son Abel, and of Noah,
<lb/>Of Moses the lawgiver, and the obedient

<sb/>
<lb/>Abraham, patriarch, and David, king,
<lb/>Israel with his father and his children,
<lb/>And Rachel, for whose sake he did so much,

<sb/>
<lb/>And others many, and he made them blessed;
<lb/>And thou must know, that earlier than these
<lb/>Never were any human spirits saved."

<sb/>
<lb/>We ceased not to advance because he spake,
<lb/>But still were passing onward through the forest,
<lb/>The forest, say I, of thick-crowded ghosts.

<sb/>
<lb/>Not very far as yet our way had gone
<lb/>This side the summit, when I saw a fire
<lb/>That overcame a hemisphere of darkness.

<sb/>
<lb/>We were a little distant from it still,
<lb/>But not so far that I in part discerned not
<lb/>That honourable people held that place.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O thou who honourest every art and science,
<lb/>Who may these be, which such great honour have,
<lb/>That from the fashion of the rest it parts them?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "The honourable name,
<lb/>That sounds of them above there in thy life,
<lb/>Wins grace in Heaven, that so advances them."

<sb/>
<lb/>In the mean time a voice was heard by me:
<lb/>"All honour be to the pre-eminent Poet;
<lb/>His shade returns again, that was departed."

<sb/>
<lb/>After the voice had ceased and quiet was,
<lb/>Four mighty shades I saw approaching us;
<lb/>Semblance had they nor sorrowful nor glad.

<sb/>
<lb/>To say to me began my gracious Master:
<lb/>"Him with that falchion in his hand behold,
<lb/>Who comes before the three, even as their lord.

<sb/>
<lb/>That one is Homer, Poet sovereign;
<lb/>He who comes next is Horace, the satirist;
<lb/>The third is Ovid, and the last is Lucan.

<sb/>
<lb/>Because to each of these with me applies
<lb/>The name that solitary voice proclaimed,
<lb/>They do me honour, and in that do well."

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus I beheld assemble the fair school
<lb/>Of that lord of the song pre-eminent,
<lb/>Who o'er the others like an eagle soars.

<sb/>
<lb/>When they together had discoursed somewhat,
<lb/>They turned to me with signs of salutation,
<lb/>And on beholding this, my Master smiled;

<sb/>
<lb/>And more of honour still, much more, they did me,
<lb/>In that they made me one of their own band;
<lb/>So that the sixth was I, 'mid so much wit.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus we went on as far as to the light,
<lb/>Things saying 'tis becoming to keep silent,
<lb/>As was the saying of them where I was.

<sb/>
<lb/>We came unto a noble castle's foot,
<lb/>Seven times encompassed with lofty walls,
<lb/>Defended round by a fair rivulet;

<sb/>
<lb/>This we passed over even as firm ground;
<lb/>Through portals seven I entered with these Sages;
<lb/>We came into a meadow of fresh verdure.

<sb/>
<lb/>People were there with solemn eyes and slow,
<lb/>Of great authority in their countenance;
<lb/>They spake but seldom, and with gentle voices.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus we withdrew ourselves upon one side
<lb/>Into an opening luminous and lofty,
<lb/>So that they all of them were visible.

<sb/>
<lb/>There opposite, upon the green enamel,
<lb/>Were pointed out to me the mighty spirits,
<lb/>Whom to have seen I feel myself exalted.

<sb/>
<lb/>I saw Electra with companions many,
<lb/>'Mongst whom I knew both Hector and Aeneas,
<lb/>Caesar in armour with gerfalcon eyes;

<sb/>
<lb/>I saw Camilla and Penthesilea
<lb/>On the other side, and saw the King Latinus,
<lb/>Who with Lavinia his daughter sat;

<sb/>
<lb/>I saw that Brutus who drove Tarquin forth,
<lb/>Lucretia, Julia, Marcia, and Cornelia,
<lb/>And saw alone, apart, the Saladin.

<sb/>
<lb/>When I had lifted up my brows a little,
<lb/>The Master I beheld of those who know,
<lb/>Sit with his philosophic family.

<sb/>
<lb/>All gaze upon him, and all do him honour.
<lb/>There I beheld both Socrates and Plato,
<lb/>Who nearer him before the others stand;

<sb/>
<lb/>Democritus, who puts the world on chance,
<lb/>Diogenes, Anaxagoras, and Thales,
<lb/>Zeno, Empedocles, and Heraclitus;

<sb/>
<lb/>Of qualities I saw the good collector,
<lb/>Hight Dioscorides; and Orpheus saw I,
<lb/>Tully and Livy, and moral Seneca,

<sb/>
<lb/>Euclid, geometrician, and Ptolemy,
<lb/>Galen, Hippocrates, and Avicenna,
<lb/>Averroes, who the great Comment made.

<sb/>
<lb/>I cannot all of them pourtray in full,
<lb/>Because so drives me onward the long theme,
<lb/>That many times the word comes short of fact.

<sb/>
<lb/>The sixfold company in two divides;
<lb/>Another way my sapient Guide conducts me
<lb/>Forth from the quiet to the air that trembles;

<sb/>
<lb/>And to a place I come where nothing shines.
    
</circle>

<circle number="2" main_sin="lustful">

<canto numeral="V"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus I descended out of the first circle
<lb/>Down to the second, that less space begirds,
<lb/>And so much greater dole, that goads to wailing.

<sb/>
<lb/>There standeth Minos horribly, and snarls;
<lb/>Examines the transgressions at the entrance;
<lb/>Judges, and sends according as he girds him.

<sb/>
<lb/>I say, that when the spirit evil-born
<lb/>Cometh before him, wholly it confesses;
<lb/>And this discriminator of transgressions

<sb/>
<lb/>Seeth what place in Hell is meet for it;
<lb/>Girds himself with his tail as many times
<lb/>As grades he wishes it should be thrust down.

<sb/>
<lb/>Always before him many of them stand;
<lb/>They go by turns each one unto the judgment;
<lb/>They speak, and hear, and then are downward hurled.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O thou, that to this dolorous hostelry
<lb/>Comest," said Minos to me, when he saw me,
<lb/>Leaving the practice of so great an office,

<sb/>
<lb/>"Look how thou enterest, and in whom thou trustest;
<lb/>Let not the portal's amplitude deceive thee."
<lb/>And unto him my Guide: "Why criest thou too?

<sb/>
<lb/>Do not impede his journey fate-ordained;
<lb/>It is so willed there where is power to do
<lb/>That which is willed; and ask no further question."

<sb/>
<lb/>And now begin the dolesome notes to grow
<lb/>Audible unto me; now am I come
<lb/>There where much lamentation strikes upon me.

<sb/>
<lb/>I came into a place mute of all light,
<lb/>Which bellows as the sea does in a tempest,
<lb/>If by opposing winds 't is combated.

<sb/>
<lb/>The infernal hurricane that never rests
<lb/>Hurtles the spirits onward in its rapine;
<lb/>Whirling them round, and smiting, it molests them.

<sb/>
<lb/>When they arrive before the precipice,
<lb/>There are the shrieks, the plaints, and the laments,
<lb/>There they blaspheme the puissance divine.

<sb/>
<lb/>I understood that unto such a torment
<lb/>The carnal malefactors were condemned,
<lb/>Who reason subjugate to appetite.

<sb/>
<lb/>And as the wings of starlings bear them on
<lb/>In the cold season in large band and full,
<lb/>So doth that blast the spirits maledict;

<sb/>
<lb/>It hither, thither, downward, upward, drives them;
<lb/>No hope doth comfort them for evermore,
<lb/>Not of repose, but even of lesser pain.

<sb/>
<lb/>And as the cranes go chanting forth their lays,
<lb/>Making in air a long line of themselves,
<lb/>So saw I coming, uttering lamentations,

<sb/>
<lb/>Shadows borne onward by the aforesaid stress.
<lb/>Whereupon said I: "Master, who are those
<lb/>People, whom the black air so castigates?"

<sb/>
<lb/>"The first of those, of whom intelligence
<lb/>Thou fain wouldst have," then said he unto me,
<lb/>"The empress was of many languages.

<sb/>
<lb/>To sensual vices she was so abandoned,
<lb/>That lustful she made licit in her law,
<lb/>To remove the blame to which she had been led.

<sb/>
<lb/>She is Semiramis, of whom we read
<lb/>That she succeeded Ninus, and was his spouse;
<lb/>She held the land which now the Sultan rules.

<sb/>
<lb/>The next is she who killed herself for love,
<lb/>And broke faith with the ashes of Sichaeus;
<lb/>Then Cleopatra the voluptuous."

<sb/>
<lb/>Helen I saw, for whom so many ruthless
<lb/>Seasons revolved; and saw the great Achilles,
<lb/>Who at the last hour combated with Love.

<sb/>
<lb/>Paris I saw, Tristan; and more than a thousand
<lb/>Shades did he name and point out with his finger,
<lb/>Whom Love had separated from our life.

<sb/>
<lb/>After that I had listened to my Teacher,
<lb/>Naming the dames of eld and cavaliers,
<lb/>Pity prevailed, and I was nigh bewildered.

<sb/>
<lb/>And I began: "O Poet, willingly
<lb/>Speak would I to those two, who go together,
<lb/>And seem upon the wind to be so light."

<sb/>
<lb/>And, he to me: "Thou'lt mark, when they shall be
<lb/>Nearer to us; and then do thou implore them
<lb/>By love which leadeth them, and they will come."

<sb/>
<lb/>Soon as the wind in our direction sways them,
<lb/>My voice uplift I: "O ye weary souls!
<lb/>Come speak to us, if no one interdicts it."

<sb/>
<lb/>As turtle-doves, called onward by desire,
<lb/>With open and steady wings to the sweet nest
<lb/>Fly through the air by their volition borne,

<sb/>
<lb/>So came they from the band where Dido is,
<lb/>Approaching us athwart the air malign,
<lb/>So strong was the affectionate appeal.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O living creature gracious and benignant,
<lb/>Who visiting goest through the purple air
<lb/>Us, who have stained the world incarnadine,

<sb/>
<lb/>If were the King of the Universe our friend,
<lb/>We would pray unto him to give thee peace,
<lb/>Since thou hast pity on our woe perverse.

<sb/>
<lb/>Of what it pleases thee to hear and speak,
<lb/>That will we hear, and we will speak to you,
<lb/>While silent is the wind, as it is now.

<sb/>
<lb/>Sitteth the city, wherein I was born,
<lb/>Upon the sea-shore where the Po descends
<lb/>To rest in peace with all his retinue.

<sb/>
<lb/>Love, that on gentle heart doth swiftly seize,
<lb/>Seized this man for the person beautiful
<lb/>That was ta'en from me, and still the mode offends me.

<sb/>
<lb/>Love, that exempts no one beloved from loving,
<lb/>Seized me with pleasure of this man so strongly,
<lb/>That, as thou seest, it doth not yet desert me;

<sb/>
<lb/>Love has conducted us unto one death;
<lb/>Caina waiteth him who quenched our life!"
<lb/>These words were borne along from them to us.

<sb/>
<lb/>As soon as I had heard those souls tormented,
<lb/>I bowed my face, and so long held it down
<lb/>Until the Poet said to me: "What thinkest?"

<sb/>
<lb/>When I made answer, I began: "Alas!
<lb/>How many pleasant thoughts, how much desire,
<lb/>Conducted these unto the dolorous pass!"

<sb/>
<lb/>Then unto them I turned me, and I spake,
<lb/>And I began: "Thine agonies, Francesca,
<lb/>Sad and compassionate to weeping make me.

<sb/>
<lb/>But tell me, at the time of those sweet sighs,
<lb/>By what and in what manner Love conceded,
<lb/>That you should know your dubious desires?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And she to me: "There is no greater sorrow
<lb/>Than to be mindful of the happy time
<lb/>In misery, and that thy Teacher knows.

<sb/>
<lb/>But, if to recognise the earliest root
<lb/>Of love in us thou hast so great desire,
<lb/>I will do even as he who weeps and speaks.

<sb/>
<lb/>One day we reading were for our delight
<lb/>Of Launcelot, how Love did him enthral.
<lb/>Alone we were and without any fear.

<sb/>
<lb/>Full many a time our eyes together drew
<lb/>That reading, and drove the colour from our faces;
<lb/>But one point only was it that o'ercame us.

<sb/>
<lb/>When as we read of the much-longed-for smile
<lb/>Being by such a noble lover kissed,
<lb/>This one, who ne'er from me shall be divided,

<sb/>
<lb/>Kissed me upon the mouth all palpitating.
<lb/>Galeotto was the book and he who wrote it.
<lb/>That day no farther did we read therein."

<sb/>
<lb/>And all the while one spirit uttered this,
<lb/>The other one did weep so, that, for pity,
<lb/>I swooned away as if I had been dying,

<sb/>
<lb/>And fell, even as a dead body falls.

</circle>

<circle number="3" main_sin="gluttonous">
    
<canto numeral="VI"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>At the return of consciousness, that closed
<lb/>Before the pity of those two relations,
<lb/>Which utterly with sadness had confused me,

<sb/>
<lb/>New torments I behold, and new tormented
<lb/>Around me, whichsoever way I move,
<lb/>And whichsoever way I turn, and gaze.

<sb/>
<lb/>In the third circle am I of the rain
<lb/>Eternal, maledict, and cold, and heavy;
<lb/>Its law and quality are never new.

<sb/>
<lb/>Huge hail, and water sombre-hued, and snow,
<lb/>Athwart the tenebrous air pour down amain;
<lb/>Noisome the earth is, that receiveth this.

<sb/>
<lb/>Cerberus, monster cruel and uncouth,
<lb/>With his three gullets like a dog is barking
<lb/>Over the people that are there submerged.

<sb/>
<lb/>Red eyes he has, and unctuous beard and black,
<lb/>And belly large, and armed with claws his hands;
<lb/>He rends the spirits, flays, and quarters them.

<sb/>
<lb/>Howl the rain maketh them like unto dogs;
<lb/>One side they make a shelter for the other;
<lb/>Oft turn themselves the wretched reprobates.

<sb/>
<lb/>When Cerberus perceived us, the great worm!
<lb/>His mouths he opened, and displayed his tusks;
<lb/>Not a limb had he that was motionless.

<sb/>
<lb/>And my Conductor, with his spans extended,
<lb/>Took of the earth, and with his fists well filled,
<lb/>He threw it into those rapacious gullets.

<sb/>
<lb/>Such as that dog is, who by barking craves,
<lb/>And quiet grows soon as his food he gnaws,
<lb/>For to devour it he but thinks and struggles,

<sb/>
<lb/>The like became those muzzles filth-begrimed
<lb/>Of Cerberus the demon, who so thunders
<lb/>Over the souls that they would fain be deaf.

<sb/>
<lb/>We passed across the shadows, which subdues
<lb/>The heavy rain-storm, and we placed our feet
<lb/>Upon their vanity that person seems.

<sb/>
<lb/>They all were lying prone upon the earth,
<lb/>Excepting one, who sat upright as soon
<lb/>As he beheld us passing on before him.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O thou that art conducted through this Hell,"
<lb/>He said to me, "recall me, if thou canst;
<lb/>Thyself wast made before I was unmade."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I to him: "The anguish which thou hast
<lb/>Perhaps doth draw thee out of my remembrance,
<lb/>So that it seems not I have ever seen thee.

<sb/>
<lb/>But tell me who thou art, that in so doleful
<lb/>A place art put, and in such punishment,
<lb/>If some are greater, none is so displeasing."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "Thy city, which is full
<lb/>Of envy so that now the sack runs over,
<lb/>Held me within it in the life serene.

<sb/>
<lb/>You citizens were wont to call me Ciacco;
<lb/>For the pernicious sin of gluttony
<lb/>I, as thou seest, am battered by this rain.

<sb/>
<lb/>And I, sad soul, am not the only one,
<lb/>For all these suffer the like penalty
<lb/>For the like sin;" and word no more spake he.

<sb/>
<lb/>I answered him: "Ciacco, thy wretchedness
<lb/>Weighs on me so that it to weep invites me;
<lb/>But tell me, if thou knowest, to what shall come

<sb/>
<lb/>The citizens of the divided city;
<lb/>If any there be just; and the occasion
<lb/>Tell me why so much discord has assailed it."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "They, after long contention,
<lb/>Will come to bloodshed; and the rustic party
<lb/>Will drive the other out with much offence.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then afterwards behoves it this one fall
<lb/>Within three suns, and rise again the other
<lb/>By force of him who now is on the coast.

<sb/>
<lb/>High will it hold its forehead a long while,
<lb/>Keeping the other under heavy burdens,
<lb/>Howe'er it weeps thereat and is indignant.

<sb/>
<lb/>The just are two, and are not understood there;
<lb/>Envy and Arrogance and Avarice
<lb/>Are the three sparks that have all hearts enkindled."

<sb/>
<lb/>Here ended he his tearful utterance;
<lb/>And I to him: "I wish thee still to teach me,
<lb/>And make a gift to me of further speech.

<sb/>
<lb/>Farinata and Tegghiaio, once so worthy,
<lb/>Jacopo Rusticucci, Arrigo, and Mosca,
<lb/>And others who on good deeds set their thoughts,

<sb/>
<lb/>Say where they are, and cause that I may know them;
<lb/>For great desire constraineth me to learn
<lb/>If Heaven doth sweeten them, or Hell envenom."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he: "They are among the blacker souls;
<lb/>A different sin downweighs them to the bottom;
<lb/>If thou so far descendest, thou canst see them.

<sb/>
<lb/>But when thou art again in the sweet world,
<lb/>I pray thee to the mind of others bring me;
<lb/>No more I tell thee and no more I answer."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then his straightforward eyes he turned askance,
<lb/>Eyed me a little, and then bowed his head;
<lb/>He fell therewith prone like the other blind.

<sb/>
<lb/>And the Guide said to me: "He wakes no more
<lb/>This side the sound of the angelic trumpet;
<lb/>When shall approach the hostile Potentate,

<sb/>
<lb/>Each one shall find again his dismal tomb,
<lb/>Shall reassume his flesh and his own figure,
<lb/>Shall hear what through eternity re-echoes."

<sb/>
<lb/>So we passed onward o'er the filthy mixture
<lb/>Of shadows and of rain with footsteps slow,
<lb/>Touching a little on the future life.

<sb/>
<lb/>Wherefore I said: "Master, these torments here,
<lb/>Will they increase after the mighty sentence,
<lb/>Or lesser be, or will they be as burning?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "Return unto thy science,
<lb/>Which wills, that as the thing more perfect is,
<lb/>The more it feels of pleasure and of pain.

<sb/>
<lb/>Albeit that this people maledict
<lb/>To true perfection never can attain,
<lb/>Hereafter more than now they look to be."

<sb/>
<lb/>Round in a circle by that road we went,
<lb/>Speaking much more, which I do not repeat;
<lb/>We came unto the point where the descent is;

<sb/>
<lb/>There we found Plutus the great enemy.
    
</circle>
        
<circle number="4" main_sin="avaricious_prodigal">    

<canto numeral="VII"/>
    
<sb/>
<lb/>"Pape Satan, Pape Satan, Aleppe!"
<lb/>Thus Plutus with his clucking voice began;
<lb/>And that benignant Sage, who all things knew,

<sb/>
<lb/>Said, to encourage me: "Let not thy fear
<lb/>Harm thee; for any power that he may have
<lb/>Shall not prevent thy going down this crag."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then he turned round unto that bloated lip,
<lb/>And said: "Be silent, thou accursed wolf;
<lb/>Consume within thyself with thine own rage.

<sb/>
<lb/>Not causeless is this journey to the abyss;
<lb/>Thus is it willed on high, where Michael wrought
<lb/>Vengeance upon the proud adultery."

<sb/>
<lb/>Even as the sails inflated by the wind
<lb/>Involved together fall when snaps the mast,
<lb/>So fell the cruel monster to the earth.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus we descended into the fourth chasm,
<lb/>Gaining still farther on the dolesome shore
<lb/>Which all the woe of the universe insacks.

<sb/>
<lb/>Justice of God, ah! who heaps up so many
<lb/>New toils and sufferings as I beheld?
<lb/>And why doth our transgression waste us so?

<sb/>
<lb/>As doth the billow there upon Charybdis,
<lb/>That breaks itself on that which it encounters,
<lb/>So here the folk must dance their roundelay.

<sb/>
<lb/>Here saw I people, more than elsewhere, many,
<lb/>On one side and the other, with great howls,
<lb/>Rolling weights forward by main force of chest.

<sb/>
<lb/>They clashed together, and then at that point
<lb/>Each one turned backward, rolling retrograde,
<lb/>Crying, "Why keepest?" and, "Why squanderest thou?"

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus they returned along the lurid circle
<lb/>On either hand unto the opposite point,
<lb/>Shouting their shameful metre evermore.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then each, when he arrived there, wheeled about
<lb/>Through his half-circle to another joust;
<lb/>And I, who had my heart pierced as it were,

<sb/>
<lb/>Exclaimed: "My Master, now declare to me
<lb/>What people these are, and if all were clerks,
<lb/>These shaven crowns upon the left of us."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "All of them were asquint
<lb/>In intellect in the first life, so much
<lb/>That there with measure they no spending made.

<sb/>
<lb/>Clearly enough their voices bark it forth,
<lb/>Whene'er they reach the two points of the circle,
<lb/>Where sunders them the opposite defect.

<sb/>
<lb/>Clerks those were who no hairy covering
<lb/>Have on the head, and Popes and Cardinals,
<lb/>In whom doth Avarice practise its excess."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I: "My Master, among such as these
<lb/>I ought forsooth to recognise some few,
<lb/>Who were infected with these maladies."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "Vain thought thou entertainest;
<lb/>The undiscerning life which made them sordid
<lb/>Now makes them unto all discernment dim.

<sb/>
<lb/>Forever shall they come to these two buttings;
<lb/>These from the sepulchre shall rise again
<lb/>With the fist closed, and these with tresses shorn.

<sb/>
<lb/>Ill giving and ill keeping the fair world
<lb/>Have ta'en from them, and placed them in this scuffle;
<lb/>Whate'er it be, no words adorn I for it.

<sb/>
<lb/>Now canst thou, Son, behold the transient farce
<lb/>Of goods that are committed unto Fortune,
<lb/>For which the human race each other buffet;

<sb/>
<lb/>For all the gold that is beneath the moon,
<lb/>Or ever has been, of these weary souls
<lb/>Could never make a single one repose."

<sb/>
<lb/>"Master," I said to him, "now tell me also
<lb/>What is this Fortune which thou speakest of,
<lb/>That has the world's goods so within its clutches?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "O creatures imbecile,
<lb/>What ignorance is this which doth beset you?
<lb/>Now will I have thee learn my judgment of her.

<sb/>
<lb/>He whose omniscience everything transcends
<lb/>The heavens created, and gave who should guide them,
<lb/>That every part to every part may shine,

<sb/>
<lb/>Distributing the light in equal measure;
<lb/>He in like manner to the mundane splendours
<lb/>Ordained a general ministress and guide,

<sb/>
<lb/>That she might change at times the empty treasures
<lb/>From race to race, from one blood to another,
<lb/>Beyond resistance of all human wisdom.

<sb/>
<lb/>Therefore one people triumphs, and another
<lb/>Languishes, in pursuance of her judgment,
<lb/>Which hidden is, as in the grass a serpent.

<sb/>
<lb/>Your knowledge has no counterstand against her;
<lb/>She makes provision, judges, and pursues
<lb/>Her governance, as theirs the other gods.

<sb/>
<lb/>Her permutations have not any truce;
<lb/>Necessity makes her precipitate,
<lb/>So often cometh who his turn obtains.

<sb/>
<lb/>And this is she who is so crucified
<lb/>Even by those who ought to give her praise,
<lb/>Giving her blame amiss, and bad repute.

<sb/>
<lb/>But she is blissful, and she hears it not;
<lb/>Among the other primal creatures gladsome
<lb/>She turns her sphere, and blissful she rejoices.

<sb/>
<lb/>Let us descend now unto greater woe;
<lb/>Already sinks each star that was ascending
<lb/>When I set out, and loitering is forbidden."
    
</circle>
    
<circle number="5" main_sin="wrathful_sullen">

<sb/>
<lb/>We crossed the circle to the other bank,
<lb/>Near to a fount that boils, and pours itself
<lb/>Along a gully that runs out of it.

<sb/>
<lb/>The water was more sombre far than perse;
<lb/>And we, in company with the dusky waves,
<lb/>Made entrance downward by a path uncouth.

<sb/>
<lb/>A marsh it makes, which has the name of Styx,
<lb/>This tristful brooklet, when it has descended
<lb/>Down to the foot of the malign gray shores.

<sb/>
<lb/>And I, who stood intent upon beholding,
<lb/>Saw people mud-besprent in that lagoon,
<lb/>All of them naked and with angry look.

<sb/>
<lb/>They smote each other not alone with hands,
<lb/>But with the head and with the breast and feet,
<lb/>Tearing each other piecemeal with their teeth.

<sb/>
<lb/>Said the good Master: "Son, thou now beholdest
<lb/>The souls of those whom anger overcame;
<lb/>And likewise I would have thee know for certain

<sb/>
<lb/>Beneath the water people are who sigh
<lb/>And make this water bubble at the surface,
<lb/>As the eye tells thee wheresoe'er it turns.

<sb/>
<lb/>Fixed in the mire they say, 'We sullen were
<lb/>In the sweet air, which by the sun is gladdened,
<lb/>Bearing within ourselves the sluggish reek;

<sb/>
<lb/>Now we are sullen in this sable mire.'
<lb/>This hymn do they keep gurgling in their throats,
<lb/>For with unbroken words they cannot say it."

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus we went circling round the filthy fen
<lb/>A great arc 'twixt the dry bank and the swamp,
<lb/>With eyes turned unto those who gorge the mire;

<sb/>
<lb/>Unto the foot of a tower we came at last.

</circle>

<canto numeral="VIII"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>I say, continuing, that long before
<lb/>We to the foot of that high tower had come,
<lb/>Our eyes went upward to the summit of it,

<sb/>
<lb/>By reason of two flamelets we saw placed there,
<lb/>And from afar another answer them,
<lb/>So far, that hardly could the eye attain it.

<sb/>
<lb/>And, to the sea of all discernment turned,
<lb/>I said: "What sayeth this, and what respondeth
<lb/>That other fire? and who are they that made it?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "Across the turbid waves
<lb/>What is expected thou canst now discern,
<lb/>If reek of the morass conceal it not."

<sb/>
<lb/>Cord never shot an arrow from itself
<lb/>That sped away athwart the air so swift,
<lb/>As I beheld a very little boat

<sb/>
<lb/>Come o'er the water tow'rds us at that moment,
<lb/>Under the guidance of a single pilot,
<lb/>Who shouted, "Now art thou arrived, fell soul?"

<sb/>
<lb/>"Phlegyas, Phlegyas, thou criest out in vain
<lb/>For this once," said my Lord; "thou shalt not have us
<lb/>Longer than in the passing of the slough."

<sb/>
<lb/>As he who listens to some great deceit
<lb/>That has been done to him, and then resents it,
<lb/>Such became Phlegyas, in his gathered wrath.

<sb/>
<lb/>My Guide descended down into the boat,
<lb/>And then he made me enter after him,
<lb/>And only when I entered seemed it laden.

<sb/>
<lb/>Soon as the Guide and I were in the boat,
<lb/>The antique prow goes on its way, dividing
<lb/>More of the water than 'tis wont with others.

<sb/>
<lb/>While we were running through the dead canal,
<lb/>Uprose in front of me one full of mire,
<lb/>And said, "Who 'rt thou that comest ere the hour?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And I to him: "Although I come, I stay not;
<lb/>But who art thou that hast become so squalid?"
<lb/>"Thou seest that I am one who weeps," he answered.

<sb/>
<lb/>And I to him: "With weeping and with wailing,
<lb/>Thou spirit maledict, do thou remain;
<lb/>For thee I know, though thou art all defiled."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then stretched he both his hands unto the boat;
<lb/>Whereat my wary Master thrust him back,
<lb/>Saying, "Away there with the other dogs!"

<sb/>
<lb/>Thereafter with his arms he clasped my neck;
<lb/>He kissed my face, and said: "Disdainful soul,
<lb/>Blessed be she who bore thee in her bosom.

<sb/>
<lb/>That was an arrogant person in the world;
<lb/>Goodness is none, that decks his memory;
<lb/>So likewise here his shade is furious.

<sb/>
<lb/>How many are esteemed great kings up there,
<lb/>Who here shall be like unto swine in mire,
<lb/>Leaving behind them horrible dispraises!"

<sb/>
<lb/>And I: "My Master, much should I be pleased,
<lb/>If I could see him soused into this broth,
<lb/>Before we issue forth out of the lake."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "Ere unto thee the shore
<lb/>Reveal itself, thou shalt be satisfied;
<lb/>Such a desire 'tis meet thou shouldst enjoy."

<sb/>
<lb/>A little after that, I saw such havoc
<lb/>Made of him by the people of the mire,
<lb/>That still I praise and thank my God for it.

<sb/>
<lb/>They all were shouting, "At Philippo Argenti!"
<lb/>And that exasperate spirit Florentine
<lb/>Turned round upon himself with his own teeth.

<sb/>
<lb/>We left him there, and more of him I tell not;
<lb/>But on mine ears there smote a lamentation,
<lb/>Whence forward I intent unbar mine eyes.

<sb/>
<lb/>And the good Master said: "Even now, my Son,
<lb/>The city draweth near whose name is Dis,
<lb/>With the grave citizens, with the great throng."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I: "Its mosques already, Master, clearly
<lb/>Within there in the valley I discern
<lb/>Vermilion, as if issuing from the fire

<sb/>
<lb/>They were."  And he to me: "The fire eternal
<lb/>That kindles them within makes them look red,
<lb/>As thou beholdest in this nether Hell."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then we arrived within the moats profound,
<lb/>That circumvallate that disconsolate city;
<lb/>The walls appeared to me to be of iron.

<sb/>
<lb/>Not without making first a circuit wide,
<lb/>We came unto a place where loud the pilot
<lb/>Cried out to us, "Debark, here is the entrance."

<sb/>
<lb/>More than a thousand at the gates I saw
<lb/>Out of the Heavens rained down, who angrily
<lb/>Were saying, "Who is this that without death

<sb/>
<lb/>Goes through the kingdom of the people dead?"
<lb/>And my sagacious Master made a sign
<lb/>Of wishing secretly to speak with them.

<sb/>
<lb/>A little then they quelled their great disdain,
<lb/>And said: "Come thou alone, and he begone
<lb/>Who has so boldly entered these dominions.

<sb/>
<lb/>Let him return alone by his mad road;
<lb/>Try, if he can; for thou shalt here remain,
<lb/>Who hast escorted him through such dark regions."

<sb/>
<lb/>Think, Reader, if I was discomforted
<lb/>At utterance of the accursed words;
<lb/>For never to return here I believed.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O my dear Guide, who more than seven times
<lb/>Hast rendered me security, and drawn me
<lb/>From imminent peril that before me stood,

<sb/>
<lb/>Do not desert me," said I, "thus undone;
<lb/>And if the going farther be denied us,
<lb/>Let us retrace our steps together swiftly."

<sb/>
<lb/>And that Lord, who had led me thitherward,
<lb/>Said unto me: "Fear not; because our passage
<lb/>None can take from us, it by Such is given.

<sb/>
<lb/>But here await me, and thy weary spirit
<lb/>Comfort and nourish with a better hope;
<lb/>For in this nether world I will not leave thee."

<sb/>
<lb/>So onward goes and there abandons me
<lb/>My Father sweet, and I remain in doubt,
<lb/>For No and Yes within my head contend.

<sb/>
<lb/>I could not hear what he proposed to them;
<lb/>But with them there he did not linger long,
<lb/>Ere each within in rivalry ran back.

<sb/>
<lb/>They closed the portals, those our adversaries,
<lb/>On my Lord's breast, who had remained without
<lb/>And turned to me with footsteps far between.

<sb/>
<lb/>His eyes cast down, his forehead shorn had he
<lb/>Of all its boldness, and he said, with sighs,
<lb/>"Who has denied to me the dolesome houses?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And unto me: "Thou, because I am angry,
<lb/>Fear not, for I will conquer in the trial,
<lb/>Whatever for defence within be planned.

<sb/>
<lb/>This arrogance of theirs is nothing new;
<lb/>For once they used it at less secret gate,
<lb/>Which finds itself without a fastening still.

<sb/>
<lb/>O'er it didst thou behold the dead inscription;
<lb/>And now this side of it descends the steep,
<lb/>Passing across the circles without escort,

<sb/>
<lb/>One by whose means the city shall be opened."


<canto numeral="IX"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>That hue which cowardice brought out on me,
<lb/>Beholding my Conductor backward turn,
<lb/>Sooner repressed within him his new colour.

<sb/>
<lb/>He stopped attentive, like a man who listens,
<lb/>Because the eye could not conduct him far
<lb/>Through the black air, and through the heavy fog.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Still it behoveth us to win the fight,"
<lb/>Began he; "Else. . .Such offered us herself. . .
<lb/>O how I long that some one here arrive!"

<sb/>
<lb/>Well I perceived, as soon as the beginning
<lb/>He covered up with what came afterward,
<lb/>That they were words quite different from the first;

<sb/>
<lb/>But none the less his saying gave me fear,
<lb/>Because I carried out the broken phrase,
<lb/>Perhaps to a worse meaning than he had.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Into this bottom of the doleful conch
<lb/>Doth any e'er descend from the first grade,
<lb/>Which for its pain has only hope cut off?"

<sb/>
<lb/>This question put I; and he answered me:
<lb/>"Seldom it comes to pass that one of us
<lb/>Maketh the journey upon which I go.

<sb/>
<lb/>True is it, once before I here below
<lb/>Was conjured by that pitiless Erictho,
<lb/>Who summoned back the shades unto their bodies.

<sb/>
<lb/>Naked of me short while the flesh had been,
<lb/>Before within that wall she made me enter,
<lb/>To bring a spirit from the circle of Judas;

<sb/>
<lb/>That is the lowest region and the darkest,
<lb/>And farthest from the heaven which circles all.
<lb/>Well know I the way; therefore be reassured.

<sb/>
<lb/>This fen, which a prodigious stench exhales,
<lb/>Encompasses about the city dolent,
<lb/>Where now we cannot enter without anger."

<sb/>
<lb/>And more he said, but not in mind I have it;
<lb/>Because mine eye had altogether drawn me
<lb/>Tow'rds the high tower with the red-flaming summit,

<sb/>
<lb/>Where in a moment saw I swift uprisen
<lb/>The three infernal Furies stained with blood,
<lb/>Who had the limbs of women and their mien,

<sb/>
<lb/>And with the greenest hydras were begirt;
<lb/>Small serpents and cerastes were their tresses,
<lb/>Wherewith their horrid temples were entwined.

<sb/>
<lb/>And he who well the handmaids of the Queen
<lb/>Of everlasting lamentation knew,
<lb/>Said unto me: "Behold the fierce Erinnys.

<sb/>
<lb/>This is Megaera, on the left-hand side;
<lb/>She who is weeping on the right, Alecto;
<lb/>Tisiphone is between;" and then was silent.

<sb/>
<lb/>Each one her breast was rending with her nails;
<lb/>They beat them with their palms, and cried so loud,
<lb/>That I for dread pressed close unto the Poet.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Medusa come, so we to stone will change him!"
<lb/>All shouted looking down; "in evil hour
<lb/>Avenged we not on Theseus his assault!"

<sb/>
<lb/>"Turn thyself round, and keep thine eyes close shut,
<lb/>For if the Gorgon appear, and thou shouldst see it,
<lb/>No more returning upward would there be."

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus said the Master; and he turned me round
<lb/>Himself, and trusted not unto my hands
<lb/>So far as not to blind me with his own.

<sb/>
<lb/>O ye who have undistempered intellects,
<lb/>Observe the doctrine that conceals itself
<lb/>Beneath the veil of the mysterious verses!

<sb/>
<lb/>And now there came across the turbid waves
<lb/>The clangour of a sound with terror fraught,
<lb/>Because of which both of the margins trembled;

<sb/>
<lb/>Not otherwise it was than of a wind
<lb/>Impetuous on account of adverse heats,
<lb/>That smites the forest, and, without restraint,

<sb/>
<lb/>The branches rends, beats down, and bears away;
<lb/>Right onward, laden with dust, it goes superb,
<lb/>And puts to flight the wild beasts and the shepherds.

<sb/>
<lb/>Mine eyes he loosed, and said: "Direct the nerve
<lb/>Of vision now along that ancient foam,
<lb/>There yonder where that smoke is most intense."

<sb/>
<lb/>Even as the frogs before the hostile serpent
<lb/>Across the water scatter all abroad,
<lb/>Until each one is huddled in the earth.

<sb/>
<lb/>More than a thousand ruined souls I saw,
<lb/>Thus fleeing from before one who on foot
<lb/>Was passing o'er the Styx with soles unwet.

<sb/>
<lb/>From off his face he fanned that unctuous air,
<lb/>Waving his left hand oft in front of him,
<lb/>And only with that anguish seemed he weary.

<sb/>
<lb/>Well I perceived one sent from Heaven was he,
<lb/>And to the Master turned; and he made sign
<lb/>That I should quiet stand, and bow before him.

<sb/>
<lb/>Ah! how disdainful he appeared to me!
<lb/>He reached the gate, and with a little rod
<lb/>He opened it, for there was no resistance.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O banished out of Heaven, people despised!"
<lb/>Thus he began upon the horrid threshold;
<lb/>"Whence is this arrogance within you couched?

<sb/>
<lb/>Wherefore recalcitrate against that will,
<lb/>From which the end can never be cut off,
<lb/>And which has many times increased your pain?

<sb/>
<lb/>What helpeth it to butt against the fates?
<lb/>Your Cerberus, if you remember well,
<lb/>For that still bears his chin and gullet peeled."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then he returned along the miry road,
<lb/>And spake no word to us, but had the look
<lb/>Of one whom other care constrains and goads

<sb/>
<lb/>Than that of him who in his presence is;
<lb/>And we our feet directed tow'rds the city,
<lb/>After those holy words all confident.

<sb/>
<lb/>Within we entered without any contest;
<lb/>And I, who inclination had to see
<lb/>What the condition such a fortress holds,

<sb/>
<lb/>Soon as I was within, cast round mine eye,
<lb/>And see on every hand an ample plain,
<lb/>Full of distress and torment terrible.

<sb/>
<lb/>Even as at Arles, where stagnant grows the Rhone,
<lb/>Even as at Pola near to the Quarnaro,
<lb/>That shuts in Italy and bathes its borders,

<sb/>
<lb/>The sepulchres make all the place uneven;
<lb/>So likewise did they there on every side,
<lb/>Saving that there the manner was more bitter;

<sb/>
<lb/>For flames between the sepulchres were scattered,
<lb/>By which they so intensely heated were,
<lb/>That iron more so asks not any art.

<sb/>
<lb/>All of their coverings uplifted were,
<lb/>And from them issued forth such dire laments,
<lb/>Sooth seemed they of the wretched and tormented.

<sb/>
<lb/>And I: "My Master, what are all those people
<lb/>Who, having sepulture within those tombs,
<lb/>Make themselves audible by doleful sighs?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "Here are the Heresiarchs,
<lb/>With their disciples of all sects, and much
<lb/>More than thou thinkest laden are the tombs.

<sb/>
<lb/>Here like together with its like is buried;
<lb/>And more and less the monuments are heated."
<lb/>And when he to the right had turned, we passed

<sb/>
<lb/>Between the torments and high parapets.

<circle number="6" main_sin="heretic">

<canto numeral="X"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>Now onward goes, along a narrow path
<lb/>Between the torments and the city wall,
<lb/>My Master, and I follow at his back.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O power supreme, that through these impious circles
<lb/>Turnest me," I began, "as pleases thee,
<lb/>Speak to me, and my longings satisfy;

<sb/>
<lb/>The people who are lying in these tombs,
<lb/>Might they be seen? already are uplifted
<lb/>The covers all, and no one keepeth guard."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "They all will be closed up
<lb/>When from Jehoshaphat they shall return
<lb/>Here with the bodies they have left above.

<sb/>
<lb/>Their cemetery have upon this side
<lb/>With Epicurus all his followers,
<lb/>Who with the body mortal make the soul;

<sb/>
<lb/>But in the question thou dost put to me,
<lb/>Within here shalt thou soon be satisfied,
<lb/>And likewise in the wish thou keepest silent."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I: "Good Leader, I but keep concealed
<lb/>From thee my heart, that I may speak the less,
<lb/>Nor only now hast thou thereto disposed me."

<sb/>
<lb/>"O Tuscan, thou who through the city of fire
<lb/>Goest alive, thus speaking modestly,
<lb/>Be pleased to stay thy footsteps in this place.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thy mode of speaking makes thee manifest
<lb/>A native of that noble fatherland,
<lb/>To which perhaps I too molestful was."

<sb/>
<lb/>Upon a sudden issued forth this sound
<lb/>From out one of the tombs; wherefore I pressed,
<lb/>Fearing, a little nearer to my Leader.

<sb/>
<lb/>And unto me he said: "Turn thee; what dost thou?
<lb/>Behold there Farinata who has risen;
<lb/>From the waist upwards wholly shalt thou see him."

<sb/>
<lb/>I had already fixed mine eyes on his,
<lb/>And he uprose erect with breast and front
<lb/>E'en as if Hell he had in great despite.

<sb/>
<lb/>And with courageous hands and prompt my Leader
<lb/>Thrust me between the sepulchres towards him,
<lb/>Exclaiming, "Let thy words explicit be."

<sb/>
<lb/>As soon as I was at the foot of his tomb
<lb/>Somewhat he eyed me, and, as if disdainful,
<lb/>Then asked of me, "Who were thine ancestors?"

<sb/>
<lb/>I, who desirous of obeying was,
<lb/>Concealed it not, but all revealed to him;
<lb/>Whereat he raised his brows a little upward.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then said he: "Fiercely adverse have they been
<lb/>To me, and to my fathers, and my party;
<lb/>So that two several times I scattered them."

<sb/>
<lb/>"If they were banished, they returned on all sides,"
<lb/>I answered him, "the first time and the second;
<lb/>But yours have not acquired that art aright."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then there uprose upon the sight, uncovered
<lb/>Down to the chin, a shadow at his side;
<lb/>I think that he had risen on his knees.

<sb/>
<lb/>Round me he gazed, as if solicitude
<lb/>He had to see if some one else were with me,
<lb/>But after his suspicion was all spent,

<sb/>
<lb/>Weeping, he said to me: "If through this blind
<lb/>Prison thou goest by loftiness of genius,
<lb/>Where is my son? and why is he not with thee?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And I to him: "I come not of myself;
<lb/>He who is waiting yonder leads me here,
<lb/>Whom in disdain perhaps your Guido had."

<sb/>
<lb/>His language and the mode of punishment
<lb/>Already unto me had read his name;
<lb/>On that account my answer was so full.

<sb/>
<lb/>Up starting suddenly, he cried out: "How
<lb/>Saidst thou,--he had?  Is he not still alive?
<lb/>Does not the sweet light strike upon his eyes?"

<sb/>
<lb/>When he became aware of some delay,
<lb/>Which I before my answer made, supine
<lb/>He fell again, and forth appeared no more.

<sb/>
<lb/>But the other, magnanimous, at whose desire
<lb/>I had remained, did not his aspect change,
<lb/>Neither his neck he moved, nor bent his side.

<sb/>
<lb/>"And if," continuing his first discourse,
<lb/>"They have that art," he said, "not learned aright,
<lb/>That more tormenteth me, than doth this bed.

<sb/>
<lb/>But fifty times shall not rekindled be
<lb/>The countenance of the Lady who reigns here,
<lb/>Ere thou shalt know how heavy is that art;

<sb/>
<lb/>And as thou wouldst to the sweet world return,
<lb/>Say why that people is so pitiless
<lb/>Against my race in each one of its laws?"

<sb/>
<lb/>Whence I to him: "The slaughter and great carnage
<lb/>Which have with crimson stained the Arbia, cause
<lb/>Such orisons in our temple to be made."

<sb/>
<lb/>After his head he with a sigh had shaken,
<lb/>"There I was not alone," he said, "nor surely
<lb/>Without a cause had with the others moved.

<sb/>
<lb/>But there I was alone, where every one
<lb/>Consented to the laying waste of Florence,
<lb/>He who defended her with open face."

<sb/>
<lb/>"Ah! so hereafter may your seed repose,"
<lb/>I him entreated, "solve for me that knot,
<lb/>Which has entangled my conceptions here.

<sb/>
<lb/>It seems that you can see, if I hear rightly,
<lb/>Beforehand whatsoe'er time brings with it,
<lb/>And in the present have another mode."

<sb/>
<lb/>"We see, like those who have imperfect sight,
<lb/>The things," he said, "that distant are from us;
<lb/>So much still shines on us the Sovereign Ruler.

<sb/>
<lb/>When they draw near, or are, is wholly vain
<lb/>Our intellect, and if none brings it to us,
<lb/>Not anything know we of your human state.

<sb/>
<lb/>Hence thou canst understand, that wholly dead
<lb/>Will be our knowledge from the moment when
<lb/>The portal of the future shall be closed."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then I, as if compunctious for my fault,
<lb/>Said: "Now, then, you will tell that fallen one,
<lb/>That still his son is with the living joined.

<sb/>
<lb/>And if just now, in answering, I was dumb,
<lb/>Tell him I did it because I was thinking
<lb/>Already of the error you have solved me."

<sb/>
<lb/>And now my Master was recalling me,
<lb/>Wherefore more eagerly I prayed the spirit
<lb/>That he would tell me who was with him there.

<sb/>
<lb/>He said: "With more than a thousand here I lie;
<lb/>Within here is the second Frederick,
<lb/>And the Cardinal, and of the rest I speak not."

<sb/>
<lb/>Thereon he hid himself; and I towards
<lb/>The ancient poet turned my steps, reflecting
<lb/>Upon that saying, which seemed hostile to me.

<sb/>
<lb/>He moved along; and afterward thus going,
<lb/>He said to me, "Why art thou so bewildered?"
<lb/>And I in his inquiry satisfied him.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Let memory preserve what thou hast heard
<lb/>Against thyself," that Sage commanded me,
<lb/>"And now attend here;" and he raised his finger.

<sb/>
<lb/>"When thou shalt be before the radiance sweet
<lb/>Of her whose beauteous eyes all things behold,
<lb/>From her thou'lt know the journey of thy life."

<sb/>
<lb/>Unto the left hand then he turned his feet;
<lb/>We left the wall, and went towards the middle,
<lb/>Along a path that strikes into a valley,

<sb/>
<lb/>Which even up there unpleasant made its stench.

<canto numeral="XI"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>Upon the margin of a lofty bank
<lb/>Which great rocks broken in a circle made,
<lb/>We came upon a still more cruel throng;

<sb/>
<lb/>And there, by reason of the horrible
<lb/>Excess of stench the deep abyss throws out,
<lb/>We drew ourselves aside behind the cover

<sb/>
<lb/>Of a great tomb, whereon I saw a writing,
<lb/>Which said: "Pope Anastasius I hold,
<lb/>Whom out of the right way Photinus drew."

<sb/>
<lb/>"Slow it behoveth our descent to be,
<lb/>So that the sense be first a little used
<lb/>To the sad blast, and then we shall not heed it."

<sb/>
<lb/>The Master thus; and unto him I said,
<lb/>"Some compensation find, that the time pass not
<lb/>Idly;" and he: "Thou seest I think of that.

<sb/>
<lb/>My son, upon the inside of these rocks,"
<lb/>Began he then to say, "are three small circles,
<lb/>From grade to grade, like those which thou art leaving.

<sb/>
<lb/>They all are full of spirits maledict;
<lb/>But that hereafter sight alone suffice thee,
<lb/>Hear how and wherefore they are in constraint.

<sb/>
<lb/>Of every malice that wins hate in Heaven,
<lb/>Injury is the end; and all such end
<lb/>Either by force or fraud afflicteth others.

<sb/>
<lb/>But because fraud is man's peculiar vice,
<lb/>More it displeases God; and so stand lowest
<lb/>The fraudulent, and greater dole assails them.

<sb/>
<lb/>All the first circle of the Violent is;
<lb/>But since force may be used against three persons,
<lb/>In three rounds 'tis divided and constructed.

<sb/>
<lb/>To God, to ourselves, and to our neighbour can we
<lb/>Use force; I say on them and on their things,
<lb/>As thou shalt hear with reason manifest.

<sb/>
<lb/>A death by violence, and painful wounds,
<lb/>Are to our neighbour given; and in his substance
<lb/>Ruin, and arson, and injurious levies;

<sb/>
<lb/>Whence homicides, and he who smites unjustly,
<lb/>Marauders, and freebooters, the first round
<lb/>Tormenteth all in companies diverse.

<sb/>
<lb/>Man may lay violent hands upon himself
<lb/>And his own goods; and therefore in the second
<lb/>Round must perforce without avail repent

<sb/>
<lb/>Whoever of your world deprives himself,
<lb/>Who games, and dissipates his property,
<lb/>And weepeth there, where he should jocund be.

<sb/>
<lb/>Violence can be done the Deity,
<lb/>In heart denying and blaspheming Him,
<lb/>And by disdaining Nature and her bounty.

<sb/>
<lb/>And for this reason doth the smallest round
<lb/>Seal with its signet Sodom and Cahors,
<lb/>And who, disdaining God, speaks from the heart.

<sb/>
<lb/>Fraud, wherewithal is every conscience stung,
<lb/>A man may practise upon him who trusts,
<lb/>And him who doth no confidence imburse.

<sb/>
<lb/>This latter mode, it would appear, dissevers
<lb/>Only the bond of love which Nature makes;
<lb/>Wherefore within the second circle nestle

<sb/>
<lb/>Hypocrisy, flattery, and who deals in magic,
<lb/>Falsification, theft, and simony,
<lb/>Panders, and barrators, and the like filth.

<sb/>
<lb/>By the other mode, forgotten is that love
<lb/>Which Nature makes, and what is after added,
<lb/>From which there is a special faith engendered.

<sb/>
<lb/>Hence in the smallest circle, where the point is
<lb/>Of the Universe, upon which Dis is seated,
<lb/>Whoe'er betrays for ever is consumed."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I: "My Master, clear enough proceeds
<lb/>Thy reasoning, and full well distinguishes
<lb/>This cavern and the people who possess it.

<sb/>
<lb/>But tell me, those within the fat lagoon,
<lb/>Whom the wind drives, and whom the rain doth beat,
<lb/>And who encounter with such bitter tongues,

<sb/>
<lb/>Wherefore are they inside of the red city
<lb/>Not punished, if God has them in his wrath,
<lb/>And if he has not, wherefore in such fashion?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And unto me he said: "Why wanders so
<lb/>Thine intellect from that which it is wont?
<lb/>Or, sooth, thy mind where is it elsewhere looking?

<sb/>
<lb/>Hast thou no recollection of those words
<lb/>With which thine Ethics thoroughly discusses
<lb/>The dispositions three, that Heaven abides not,--

<sb/>
<lb/>Incontinence, and Malice, and insane
<lb/>Bestiality? and how Incontinence
<lb/>Less God offendeth, and less blame attracts?

<sb/>
<lb/>If thou regardest this conclusion well,
<lb/>And to thy mind recallest who they are
<lb/>That up outside are undergoing penance,

<sb/>
<lb/>Clearly wilt thou perceive why from these felons
<lb/>They separated are, and why less wroth
<lb/>Justice divine doth smite them with its hammer."

<sb/>
<lb/>"O Sun, that healest all distempered vision,
<lb/>Thou dost content me so, when thou resolvest,
<lb/>That doubting pleases me no less than knowing!

<sb/>
<lb/>Once more a little backward turn thee," said I,
<lb/>"There where thou sayest that usury offends
<lb/>Goodness divine, and disengage the knot."

<sb/>
<lb/>"Philosophy," he said, "to him who heeds it,
<lb/>Noteth, not only in one place alone,
<lb/>After what manner Nature takes her course

<sb/>
<lb/>From Intellect Divine, and from its art;
<lb/>And if thy Physics carefully thou notest,
<lb/>After not many pages shalt thou find,

<sb/>
<lb/>That this your art as far as possible
<lb/>Follows, as the disciple doth the master;
<lb/>So that your art is, as it were, God's grandchild.

<sb/>
<lb/>From these two, if thou bringest to thy mind
<lb/>Genesis at the beginning, it behoves
<lb/>Mankind to gain their life and to advance;

<sb/>
<lb/>And since the usurer takes another way,
<lb/>Nature herself and in her follower
<lb/>Disdains he, for elsewhere he puts his hope.

<sb/>
<lb/>But follow, now, as I would fain go on,
<lb/>For quivering are the Fishes on the horizon,
<lb/>And the Wain wholly over Caurus lies,

<sb/>
<lb/>And far beyond there we descend the crag."

</circle>
    
<circle number="7" main_sin="violence">
    
<canto numeral="XII"/>

<pouch_ring number="1" sub_sin="violent_to_neighbor">
    
<sb/>
<lb/>The place where to descend the bank we came
<lb/>Was alpine, and from what was there, moreover,
<lb/>Of such a kind that every eye would shun it.

<sb/>
<lb/>Such as that ruin is which in the flank
<lb/>Smote, on this side of Trent, the Adige,
<lb/>Either by earthquake or by failing stay,

<sb/>
<lb/>For from the mountain's top, from which it moved,
<lb/>Unto the plain the cliff is shattered so,
<lb/>Some path 'twould give to him who was above;

<sb/>
<lb/>Even such was the descent of that ravine,
<lb/>And on the border of the broken chasm
<lb/>The infamy of Crete was stretched along,

<sb/>
<lb/>Who was conceived in the fictitious cow;
<lb/>And when he us beheld, he bit himself,
<lb/>Even as one whom anger racks within.

<sb/>
<lb/>My Sage towards him shouted: "Peradventure
<lb/>Thou think'st that here may be the Duke of Athens,
<lb/>Who in the world above brought death to thee?

<sb/>
<lb/>Get thee gone, beast, for this one cometh not
<lb/>Instructed by thy sister, but he comes
<lb/>In order to behold your punishments."

<sb/>
<lb/>As is that bull who breaks loose at the moment
<lb/>In which he has received the mortal blow,
<lb/>Who cannot walk, but staggers here and there,

<sb/>
<lb/>The Minotaur beheld I do the like;
<lb/>And he, the wary, cried: "Run to the passage;
<lb/>While he wroth, 'tis well thou shouldst descend."

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus down we took our way o'er that discharge
<lb/>Of stones, which oftentimes did move themselves
<lb/>Beneath my feet, from the unwonted burden.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thoughtful I went; and he said: "Thou art thinking
<lb/>Perhaps upon this ruin, which is guarded
<lb/>By that brute anger which just now I quenched.

<sb/>
<lb/>Now will I have thee know, the other time
<lb/>I here descended to the nether Hell,
<lb/>This precipice had not yet fallen down.

<sb/>
<lb/>But truly, if I well discern, a little
<lb/>Before His coming who the mighty spoil
<lb/>Bore off from Dis, in the supernal circle,

<sb/>
<lb/>Upon all sides the deep and loathsome valley
<lb/>Trembled so, that I thought the Universe
<lb/>Was thrilled with love, by which there are who think

<sb/>
<lb/>The world ofttimes converted into chaos;
<lb/>And at that moment this primeval crag
<lb/>Both here and elsewhere made such overthrow.

<sb/>
<lb/>But fix thine eyes below; for draweth near
<lb/>The river of blood, within which boiling is
<lb/>Whoe'er by violence doth injure others."

<sb/>
<lb/>O blind cupidity, O wrath insane,
<lb/>That spurs us onward so in our short life,
<lb/>And in the eternal then so badly steeps us!

<sb/>
<lb/>I saw an ample moat bent like a bow,
<lb/>As one which all the plain encompasses,
<lb/>Conformable to what my Guide had said.

<sb/>
<lb/>And between this and the embankment's foot
<lb/>Centaurs in file were running, armed with arrows,
<lb/>As in the world they used the chase to follow.

<sb/>
<lb/>Beholding us descend, each one stood still,
<lb/>And from the squadron three detached themselves,
<lb/>With bows and arrows in advance selected;

<sb/>
<lb/>And from afar one cried: "Unto what torment
<lb/>Come ye, who down the hillside are descending?
<lb/>Tell us from there; if not, I draw the bow."

<sb/>
<lb/>My Master said: "Our answer will we make
<lb/>To Chiron, near you there; in evil hour,
<lb/>That will of thine was evermore so hasty."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then touched he me, and said: "This one is Nessus,
<lb/>Who perished for the lovely Dejanira,
<lb/>And for himself, himself did vengeance take.

<sb/>
<lb/>And he in the midst, who at his breast is gazing,
<lb/>Is the great Chiron, who brought up Achilles;
<lb/>That other Pholus is, who was so wrathful.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thousands and thousands go about the moat
<lb/>Shooting with shafts whatever soul emerges
<lb/>Out of the blood, more than his crime allots."

<sb/>
<lb/>Near we approached unto those monsters fleet;
<lb/>Chiron an arrow took, and with the notch
<lb/>Backward upon his jaws he put his beard.

<sb/>
<lb/>After he had uncovered his great mouth,
<lb/>He said to his companions: "Are you ware
<lb/>That he behind moveth whate'er he touches?

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus are not wont to do the feet of dead men."
<lb/>And my good Guide, who now was at his breast,
<lb/>Where the two natures are together joined,

<sb/>
<lb/>Replied: "Indeed he lives, and thus alone
<lb/>Me it behoves to show him the dark valley;
<lb/>Necessity, and not delight, impels us.

<sb/>
<lb/>Some one withdrew from singing Halleluja,
<lb/>Who unto me committed this new office;
<lb/>No thief is he, nor I a thievish spirit.

<sb/>
<lb/>But by that virtue through which I am moving
<lb/>My steps along this savage thoroughfare,
<lb/>Give us some one of thine, to be with us,

<sb/>
<lb/>And who may show us where to pass the ford,
<lb/>And who may carry this one on his back;
<lb/>For 'tis no spirit that can walk the air."

<sb/>
<lb/>Upon his right breast Chiron wheeled about,
<lb/>And said to Nessus: "Turn and do thou guide them,
<lb/>And warn aside, if other band may meet you."

<sb/>
<lb/>We with our faithful escort onward moved
<lb/>Along the brink of the vermilion boiling,
<lb/>Wherein the boiled were uttering loud laments.

<sb/>
<lb/>People I saw within up to the eyebrows,
<lb/>And the great Centaur said: "Tyrants are these,
<lb/>Who dealt in bloodshed and in pillaging.

<sb/>
<lb/>Here they lament their pitiless mischiefs; here
<lb/>Is Alexander, and fierce Dionysius
<lb/>Who upon Sicily brought dolorous years.

<sb/>
<lb/>That forehead there which has the hair so black
<lb/>Is Azzolin; and the other who is blond,
<lb/>Obizzo is of Esti, who, in truth,

<sb/>
<lb/>Up in the world was by his stepson slain."
<lb/>Then turned I to the Poet; and he said,
<lb/>"Now he be first to thee, and second I."

<sb/>
<lb/>A little farther on the Centaur stopped
<lb/>Above a folk, who far down as the throat
<lb/>Seemed from that boiling stream to issue forth.

<sb/>
<lb/>A shade he showed us on one side alone,
<lb/>Saying: "He cleft asunder in God's bosom
<lb/>The heart that still upon the Thames is honoured."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then people saw I, who from out the river
<lb/>Lifted their heads and also all the chest;
<lb/>And many among these I recognised.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus ever more and more grew shallower
<lb/>That blood, so that the feet alone it covered;
<lb/>And there across the moat our passage was.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Even as thou here upon this side beholdest
<lb/>The boiling stream, that aye diminishes,"
<lb/>The Centaur said, "I wish thee to believe

<sb/>
<lb/>That on this other more and more declines
<lb/>Its bed, until it reunites itself
<lb/>Where it behoveth tyranny to groan.

<sb/>
<lb/>Justice divine, upon this side, is goading
<lb/>That Attila, who was a scourge on earth,
<lb/>And Pyrrhus, and Sextus; and for ever milks

<sb/>
<lb/>The tears which with the boiling it unseals
<lb/>In Rinier da Corneto and Rinier Pazzo,
<lb/>Who made upon the highways so much war."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then back he turned, and passed again the ford.
    
</pouch_ring>
        
<canto numeral="XIII"/>
    
<pouch_ring number="2" sub_sin="violent_to_self">
    
<sb/>
<lb/>Not yet had Nessus reached the other side,
<lb/>When we had put ourselves within a wood,
<lb/>That was not marked by any path whatever.

<sb/>
<lb/>Not foliage green, but of a dusky colour,
<lb/>Not branches smooth, but gnarled and intertangled,
<lb/>Not apple-trees were there, but thorns with poison.

<sb/>
<lb/>Such tangled thickets have not, nor so dense,
<lb/>Those savage wild beasts, that in hatred hold
<lb/>'Twixt Cecina and Corneto the tilled places.

<sb/>
<lb/>There do the hideous Harpies make their nests,
<lb/>Who chased the Trojans from the Strophades,
<lb/>With sad announcement of impending doom;

<sb/>
<lb/>Broad wings have they, and necks and faces human,
<lb/>And feet with claws, and their great bellies fledged;
<lb/>They make laments upon the wondrous trees.

<sb/>
<lb/>And the good Master: "Ere thou enter farther,
<lb/>Know that thou art within the second round,"
<lb/>Thus he began to say, "and shalt be, till

<sb/>
<lb/>Thou comest out upon the horrible sand;
<lb/>Therefore look well around, and thou shalt see
<lb/>Things that will credence give unto my speech."

<sb/>
<lb/>I heard on all sides lamentations uttered,
<lb/>And person none beheld I who might make them,
<lb/>Whence, utterly bewildered, I stood still.

<sb/>
<lb/>I think he thought that I perhaps might think
<lb/>So many voices issued through those trunks
<lb/>From people who concealed themselves from us;

<sb/>
<lb/>Therefore the Master said: "If thou break off
<lb/>Some little spray from any of these trees,
<lb/>The thoughts thou hast will wholly be made vain."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then stretched I forth my hand a little forward,
<lb/>And plucked a branchlet off from a great thorn;
<lb/>And the trunk cried, "Why dost thou mangle me?"

<sb/>
<lb/>After it had become embrowned with blood,
<lb/>It recommenced its cry: "Why dost thou rend me?
<lb/>Hast thou no spirit of pity whatsoever?

<sb/>
<lb/>Men once we were, and now are changed to trees;
<lb/>Indeed, thy hand should be more pitiful,
<lb/>Even if the souls of serpents we had been."

<sb/>
<lb/>As out of a green brand, that is on fire
<lb/>At one of the ends, and from the other drips
<lb/>And hisses with the wind that is escaping;

<sb/>
<lb/>So from that splinter issued forth together
<lb/>Both words and blood; whereat I let the tip
<lb/>Fall, and stood like a man who is afraid.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Had he been able sooner to believe,"
<lb/>My Sage made answer, "O thou wounded soul,
<lb/>What only in my verses he has seen,

<sb/>
<lb/>Not upon thee had he stretched forth his hand;
<lb/>Whereas the thing incredible has caused me
<lb/>To put him to an act which grieveth me.

<sb/>
<lb/>But tell him who thou wast, so that by way
<lb/>Of some amends thy fame he may refresh
<lb/>Up in the world, to which he can return."

<sb/>
<lb/>And the trunk said: "So thy sweet words allure me,
<lb/>I cannot silent be; and you be vexed not,
<lb/>That I a little to discourse am tempted.

<sb/>
<lb/>I am the one who both keys had in keeping
<lb/>Of Frederick's heart, and turned them to and fro
<lb/>So softly in unlocking and in locking,

<sb/>
<lb/>That from his secrets most men I withheld;
<lb/>Fidelity I bore the glorious office
<lb/>So great, I lost thereby my sleep and pulses.

<sb/>
<lb/>The courtesan who never from the dwelling
<lb/>Of Caesar turned aside her strumpet eyes,
<lb/>Death universal and the vice of courts,

<sb/>
<lb/>Inflamed against me all the other minds,
<lb/>And they, inflamed, did so inflame Augustus,
<lb/>That my glad honours turned to dismal mournings.

<sb/>
<lb/>My spirit, in disdainful exultation,
<lb/>Thinking by dying to escape disdain,
<lb/>Made me unjust against myself, the just.

<sb/>
<lb/>I, by the roots unwonted of this wood,
<lb/>Do swear to you that never broke I faith
<lb/>Unto my lord, who was so worthy of honour;

<sb/>
<lb/>And to the world if one of you return,
<lb/>Let him my memory comfort, which is lying
<lb/>Still prostrate from the blow that envy dealt it."

<sb/>
<lb/>Waited awhile, and then: "Since he is silent,"
<lb/>The Poet said to me, "lose not the time,
<lb/>But speak, and question him, if more may please thee."

<sb/>
<lb/>Whence I to him: "Do thou again inquire
<lb/>Concerning what thou thinks't will satisfy me;
<lb/>For I cannot, such pity is in my heart."

<sb/>
<lb/>Therefore he recommenced: "So may the man
<lb/>Do for thee freely what thy speech implores,
<lb/>Spirit incarcerate, again be pleased

<sb/>
<lb/>To tell us in what way the soul is bound
<lb/>Within these knots; and tell us, if thou canst,
<lb/>If any from such members e'er is freed."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then blew the trunk amain, and afterward
<lb/>The wind was into such a voice converted:
<lb/>"With brevity shall be replied to you.

<sb/>
<lb/>When the exasperated soul abandons
<lb/>The body whence it rent itself away,
<lb/>Minos consigns it to the seventh abyss.

<sb/>
<lb/>It falls into the forest, and no part
<lb/>Is chosen for it; but where Fortune hurls it,
<lb/>There like a grain of spelt it germinates.

<sb/>
<lb/>It springs a sapling, and a forest tree;
<lb/>The Harpies, feeding then upon its leaves,
<lb/>Do pain create, and for the pain an outlet.

<sb/>
<lb/>Like others for our spoils shall we return;
<lb/>But not that any one may them revest,
<lb/>For 'tis not just to have what one casts off.

<sb/>
<lb/>Here we shall drag them, and along the dismal
<lb/>Forest our bodies shall suspended be,
<lb/>Each to the thorn of his molested shade."

<sb/>
<lb/>We were attentive still unto the trunk,
<lb/>Thinking that more it yet might wish to tell us,
<lb/>When by a tumult we were overtaken,

<sb/>
<lb/>In the same way as he is who perceives
<lb/>The boar and chase approaching to his stand,
<lb/>Who hears the crashing of the beasts and branches;

<sb/>
<lb/>And two behold! upon our left-hand side,
<lb/>Naked and scratched, fleeing so furiously,
<lb/>That of the forest, every fan they broke.

<sb/>
<lb/>He who was in advance: "Now help, Death, help!"
<lb/>And the other one, who seemed to lag too much,
<lb/>Was shouting: "Lano, were not so alert

<sb/>
<lb/>Those legs of thine at joustings of the Toppo!"
<lb/>And then, perchance because his breath was failing,
<lb/>He grouped himself together with a bush.

<sb/>
<lb/>Behind them was the forest full of black
<lb/>She-mastiffs, ravenous, and swift of foot
<lb/>As greyhounds, who are issuing from the chain.

<sb/>
<lb/>On him who had crouched down they set their teeth,
<lb/>And him they lacerated piece by piece,
<lb/>Thereafter bore away those aching members.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thereat my Escort took me by the hand,
<lb/>And led me to the bush, that all in vain
<lb/>Was weeping from its bloody lacerations.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O Jacopo," it said, "of Sant' Andrea,
<lb/>What helped it thee of me to make a screen?
<lb/>What blame have I in thy nefarious life?"

<sb/>
<lb/>When near him had the Master stayed his steps,
<lb/>He said: "Who wast thou, that through wounds so many
<lb/>Art blowing out with blood thy dolorous speech?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to us: "O souls, that hither come
<lb/>To look upon the shameful massacre
<lb/>That has so rent away from me my leaves,

<sb/>
<lb/>Gather them up beneath the dismal bush;
<lb/>I of that city was which to the Baptist
<lb/>Changed its first patron, wherefore he for this

<sb/>
<lb/>Forever with his art will make it sad.
<lb/>And were it not that on the pass of Arno
<lb/>Some glimpses of him are remaining still,

<sb/>
<lb/>Those citizens, who afterwards rebuilt it
<lb/>Upon the ashes left by Attila,
<lb/>In vain had caused their labour to be done.

<sb/>
<lb/>Of my own house I made myself a gibbet."
    
</pouch_ring>

<canto numeral="XIV"/>
    
<pouch_ring number="3" sub_sin="violent_to_god">

<sb/>
<lb/>Because the charity of my native place
<lb/>Constrained me, gathered I the scattered leaves,
<lb/>And gave them back to him, who now was hoarse.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then came we to the confine, where disparted
<lb/>The second round is from the third, and where
<lb/>A horrible form of Justice is beheld.

<sb/>
<lb/>Clearly to manifest these novel things,
<lb/>I say that we arrived upon a plain,
<lb/>Which from its bed rejecteth every plant;

<sb/>
<lb/>The dolorous forest is a garland to it
<lb/>All round about, as the sad moat to that;
<lb/>There close upon the edge we stayed our feet.

<sb/>
<lb/>The soil was of an arid and thick sand,
<lb/>Not of another fashion made than that
<lb/>Which by the feet of Cato once was pressed.

<sb/>
<lb/>Vengeance of God, O how much oughtest thou
<lb/>By each one to be dreaded, who doth read
<lb/>That which was manifest unto mine eyes!

<sb/>
<lb/>Of naked souls beheld I many herds,
<lb/>Who all were weeping very miserably,
<lb/>And over them seemed set a law diverse.

<sb/>
<lb/>Supine upon the ground some folk were lying;
<lb/>And some were sitting all drawn up together,
<lb/>And others went about continually.

<sb/>
<lb/>Those who were going round were far the more,
<lb/>And those were less who lay down to their torment,
<lb/>But had their tongues more loosed to lamentation.

<sb/>
<lb/>O'er all the sand-waste, with a gradual fall,
<lb/>Were raining down dilated flakes of fire,
<lb/>As of the snow on Alp without a wind.

<sb/>
<lb/>As Alexander, in those torrid parts
<lb/>Of India, beheld upon his host
<lb/>Flames fall unbroken till they reached the ground.

<sb/>
<lb/>Whence he provided with his phalanxes
<lb/>To trample down the soil, because the vapour
<lb/>Better extinguished was while it was single;

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus was descending the eternal heat,
<lb/>Whereby the sand was set on fire, like tinder
<lb/>Beneath the steel, for doubling of the dole.

<sb/>
<lb/>Without repose forever was the dance
<lb/>Of miserable hands, now there, now here,
<lb/>Shaking away from off them the fresh gleeds.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Master," began I, "thou who overcomest
<lb/>All things except the demons dire, that issued
<lb/>Against us at the entrance of the gate,

<sb/>
<lb/>Who is that mighty one who seems to heed not
<lb/>The fire, and lieth lowering and disdainful,
<lb/>So that the rain seems not to ripen him?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he himself, who had become aware
<lb/>That I was questioning my Guide about him,
<lb/>Cried: "Such as I was living, am I, dead.

<sb/>
<lb/>If Jove should weary out his smith, from whom
<lb/>He seized in anger the sharp thunderbolt,
<lb/>Wherewith upon the last day I was smitten,

<sb/>
<lb/>And if he wearied out by turns the others
<lb/>In Mongibello at the swarthy forge,
<lb/>Vociferating, 'Help, good Vulcan, help!'

<sb/>
<lb/>Even as he did there at the fight of Phlegra,
<lb/>And shot his bolts at me with all his might,
<lb/>He would not have thereby a joyous vengeance."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then did my Leader speak with such great force,
<lb/>That I had never heard him speak so loud:
<lb/>"O Capaneus, in that is not extinguished

<sb/>
<lb/>Thine arrogance, thou punished art the more;
<lb/>Not any torment, saving thine own rage,
<lb/>Would be unto thy fury pain complete."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then he turned round to me with better lip,
<lb/>Saying: "One of the Seven Kings was he
<lb/>Who Thebes besieged, and held, and seems to hold

<sb/>
<lb/>God in disdain, and little seems to prize him;
<lb/>But, as I said to him, his own despites
<lb/>Are for his breast the fittest ornaments.

<sb/>
<lb/>Now follow me, and mind thou do not place
<lb/>As yet thy feet upon the burning sand,
<lb/>But always keep them close unto the wood."

<sb/>
<lb/>Speaking no word, we came to where there gushes
<lb/>Forth from the wood a little rivulet,
<lb/>Whose redness makes my hair still stand on end.

<sb/>
<lb/>As from the Bulicame springs the brooklet,
<lb/>The sinful women later share among them,
<lb/>So downward through the sand it went its way.

<sb/>
<lb/>The bottom of it, and both sloping banks,
<lb/>Were made of stone, and the margins at the side;
<lb/>Whence I perceived that there the passage was.

<sb/>
<lb/>"In all the rest which I have shown to thee
<lb/>Since we have entered in within the gate
<lb/>Whose threshold unto no one is denied,

<sb/>
<lb/>Nothing has been discovered by thine eyes
<lb/>So notable as is the present river,
<lb/>Which all the little flames above it quenches."

<sb/>
<lb/>These words were of my Leader; whence I prayed him
<lb/>That he would give me largess of the food,
<lb/>For which he had given me largess of desire.

<sb/>
<lb/>"In the mid-sea there sits a wasted land,"
<lb/>Said he thereafterward, "whose name is Crete,
<lb/>Under whose king the world of old was chaste.

<sb/>
<lb/>There is a mountain there, that once was glad
<lb/>With waters and with leaves, which was called Ida;
<lb/>Now 'tis deserted, as a thing worn out.

<sb/>
<lb/>Rhea once chose it for the faithful cradle
<lb/>Of her own son; and to conceal him better,
<lb/>Whene'er he cried, she there had clamours made.

<sb/>
<lb/>A grand old man stands in the mount erect,
<lb/>Who holds his shoulders turned tow'rds Damietta,
<lb/>And looks at Rome as if it were his mirror.

<sb/>
<lb/>His head is fashioned of refined gold,
<lb/>And of pure silver are the arms and breast;
<lb/>Then he is brass as far down as the fork.

<sb/>
<lb/>From that point downward all is chosen iron,
<lb/>Save that the right foot is of kiln-baked clay,
<lb/>And more he stands on that than on the other.

<sb/>
<lb/>Each part, except the gold, is by a fissure
<lb/>Asunder cleft, that dripping is with tears,
<lb/>Which gathered together perforate that cavern.

<sb/>
<lb/>From rock to rock they fall into this valley;
<lb/>Acheron, Styx, and Phlegethon they form;
<lb/>Then downward go along this narrow sluice

<sb/>
<lb/>Unto that point where is no more descending.
<lb/>They form Cocytus; what that pool may be
<lb/>Thou shalt behold, so here 'tis not narrated."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I to him: "If so the present runnel
<lb/>Doth take its rise in this way from our world,
<lb/>Why only on this verge appears it to us?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "Thou knowest the place is round,
<lb/>And notwithstanding thou hast journeyed far,
<lb/>Still to the left descending to the bottom,

<sb/>
<lb/>Thou hast not yet through all the circle turned.
<lb/>Therefore if something new appear to us,
<lb/>It should not bring amazement to thy face."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I again: "Master, where shall be found
<lb/>Lethe and Phlegethon, for of one thou'rt silent,
<lb/>And sayest the other of this rain is made?"

<sb/>
<lb/>"In all thy questions truly thou dost please me,"
<lb/>Replied he; "but the boiling of the red
<lb/>Water might well solve one of them thou makest.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thou shalt see Lethe, but outside this moat,
<lb/>There where the souls repair to lave themselves,
<lb/>When sin repented of has been removed."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then said he: "It is time now to abandon
<lb/>The wood; take heed that thou come after me;
<lb/>A way the margins make that are not burning,

<sb/>
<lb/>And over them all vapours are extinguished."

<canto numeral="XV"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>Now bears us onward one of the hard margins,
<lb/>And so the brooklet's mist o'ershadows it,
<lb/>From fire it saves the water and the dikes.

<sb/>
<lb/>Even as the Flemings, 'twixt Cadsand and Bruges,
<lb/>Fearing the flood that tow'rds them hurls itself,
<lb/>Their bulwarks build to put the sea to flight;

<sb/>
<lb/>And as the Paduans along the Brenta,
<lb/>To guard their villas and their villages,
<lb/>Or ever Chiarentana feel the heat;

<sb/>
<lb/>In such similitude had those been made,
<lb/>Albeit not so lofty nor so thick,
<lb/>Whoever he might be, the master made them.

<sb/>
<lb/>Now were we from the forest so remote,
<lb/>I could not have discovered where it was,
<lb/>Even if backward I had turned myself,

<sb/>
<lb/>When we a company of souls encountered,
<lb/>Who came beside the dike, and every one
<lb/>Gazed at us, as at evening we are wont

<sb/>
<lb/>To eye each other under a new moon,
<lb/>And so towards us sharpened they their brows
<lb/>As an old tailor at the needle's eye.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus scrutinised by such a family,
<lb/>By some one I was recognised, who seized
<lb/>My garment's hem, and cried out, "What a marvel!"

<sb/>
<lb/>And I, when he stretched forth his arm to me,
<lb/>On his baked aspect fastened so mine eyes,
<lb/>That the scorched countenance prevented not

<sb/>
<lb/>His recognition by my intellect;
<lb/>And bowing down my face unto his own,
<lb/>I made reply, "Are you here, Ser Brunetto?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he: "May't not displease thee, O my son,
<lb/>If a brief space with thee Brunetto Latini
<lb/>Backward return and let the trail go on."

<sb/>
<lb/>I said to him: "With all my power I ask it;
<lb/>And if you wish me to sit down with you,
<lb/>I will, if he please, for I go with him."

<sb/>
<lb/>"O son," he said, "whoever of this herd
<lb/>A moment stops, lies then a hundred years,
<lb/>Nor fans himself when smiteth him the fire.

<sb/>
<lb/>Therefore go on; I at thy skirts will come,
<lb/>And afterward will I rejoin my band,
<lb/>Which goes lamenting its eternal doom."

<sb/>
<lb/>I did not dare to go down from the road
<lb/>Level to walk with him; but my head bowed
<lb/>I held as one who goeth reverently.

<sb/>
<lb/>And he began: "What fortune or what fate
<lb/>Before the last day leadeth thee down here?
<lb/>And who is this that showeth thee the way?"

<sb/>
<lb/>"Up there above us in the life serene,"
<lb/>I answered him, "I lost me in a valley,
<lb/>Or ever yet my age had been completed.

<sb/>
<lb/>But yestermorn I turned my back upon it;
<lb/>This one appeared to me, returning thither,
<lb/>And homeward leadeth me along this road."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "If thou thy star do follow,
<lb/>Thou canst not fail thee of a glorious port,
<lb/>If well I judged in the life beautiful.

<sb/>
<lb/>And if I had not died so prematurely,
<lb/>Seeing Heaven thus benignant unto thee,
<lb/>I would have given thee comfort in the work.

<sb/>
<lb/>But that ungrateful and malignant people,
<lb/>Which of old time from Fesole descended,
<lb/>And smacks still of the mountain and the granite,

<sb/>
<lb/>Will make itself, for thy good deeds, thy foe;
<lb/>And it is right; for among crabbed sorbs
<lb/>It ill befits the sweet fig to bear fruit.

<sb/>
<lb/>Old rumour in the world proclaims them blind;
<lb/>A people avaricious, envious, proud;
<lb/>Take heed that of their customs thou do cleanse thee.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thy fortune so much honour doth reserve thee,
<lb/>One party and the other shall be hungry
<lb/>For thee; but far from goat shall be the grass.

<sb/>
<lb/>Their litter let the beasts of Fesole
<lb/>Make of themselves, nor let them touch the plant,
<lb/>If any still upon their dunghill rise,

<sb/>
<lb/>In which may yet revive the consecrated
<lb/>Seed of those Romans, who remained there when
<lb/>The nest of such great malice it became."

<sb/>
<lb/>"If my entreaty wholly were fulfilled,"
<lb/>Replied I to him, "not yet would you be
<lb/>In banishment from human nature placed;

<sb/>
<lb/>For in my mind is fixed, and touches now
<lb/>My heart the dear and good paternal image
<lb/>Of you, when in the world from hour to hour

<sb/>
<lb/>You taught me how a man becomes eternal;
<lb/>And how much I am grateful, while I live
<lb/>Behoves that in my language be discerned.

<sb/>
<lb/>What you narrate of my career I write,
<lb/>And keep it to be glossed with other text
<lb/>By a Lady who can do it, if I reach her.

<sb/>
<lb/>This much will I have manifest to you;
<lb/>Provided that my conscience do not chide me,
<lb/>For whatsoever Fortune I am ready.

<sb/>
<lb/>Such handsel is not new unto mine ears;
<lb/>Therefore let Fortune turn her wheel around
<lb/>As it may please her, and the churl his mattock."

<sb/>
<lb/>My Master thereupon on his right cheek
<lb/>Did backward turn himself, and looked at me;
<lb/>Then said: "He listeneth well who noteth it."

<sb/>
<lb/>Nor speaking less on that account, I go
<lb/>With Ser Brunetto, and I ask who are
<lb/>His most known and most eminent companions.

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "To know of some is well;
<lb/>Of others it were laudable to be silent,
<lb/>For short would be the time for so much speech.

<sb/>
<lb/>Know them in sum, that all of them were clerks,
<lb/>And men of letters great and of great fame,
<lb/>In the world tainted with the selfsame sin.

<sb/>
<lb/>Priscian goes yonder with that wretched crowd,
<lb/>And Francis of Accorso; and thou hadst seen there
<lb/>If thou hadst had a hankering for such scurf,

<sb/>
<lb/>That one, who by the Servant of the Servants
<lb/>From Arno was transferred to Bacchiglione,
<lb/>Where he has left his sin-excited nerves.

<sb/>
<lb/>More would I say, but coming and discoursing
<lb/>Can be no longer; for that I behold
<lb/>New smoke uprising yonder from the sand.

<sb/>
<lb/>A people comes with whom I may not be;
<lb/>Commended unto thee be my Tesoro,
<lb/>In which I still live, and no more I ask."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then he turned round, and seemed to be of those
<lb/>Who at Verona run for the Green Mantle
<lb/>Across the plain; and seemed to be among them

<sb/>
<lb/>The one who wins, and not the one who loses.
    
<canto numeral="XVI"/>
        
<sb/>
<lb/>Now was I where was heard the reverberation
<lb/>Of water falling into the next round,
<lb/>Like to that humming which the beehives make,

<sb/>
<lb/>When shadows three together started forth,
<lb/>Running, from out a company that passed
<lb/>Beneath the rain of the sharp martyrdom.

<sb/>
<lb/>Towards us came they, and each one cried out:
<lb/>"Stop, thou; for by thy garb to us thou seemest
<lb/>To be some one of our depraved city."

<sb/>
<lb/>Ah me! what wounds I saw upon their limbs,
<lb/>Recent and ancient by the flames burnt in!
<lb/>It pains me still but to remember it.

<sb/>
<lb/>Unto their cries my Teacher paused attentive;
<lb/>He turned his face towards me, and "Now wait,"
<lb/>He said; "to these we should be courteous.

<sb/>
<lb/>And if it were not for the fire that darts
<lb/>The nature of this region, I should say
<lb/>That haste were more becoming thee than them."

<sb/>
<lb/>As soon as we stood still, they recommenced
<lb/>The old refrain, and when they overtook us,
<lb/>Formed of themselves a wheel, all three of them.

<sb/>
<lb/>As champions stripped and oiled are wont to do,
<lb/>Watching for their advantage and their hold,
<lb/>Before they come to blows and thrusts between them,

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus, wheeling round, did every one his visage
<lb/>Direct to me, so that in opposite wise
<lb/>His neck and feet continual journey made.

<sb/>
<lb/>And, "If the misery of this soft place
<lb/>Bring in disdain ourselves and our entreaties,"
<lb/>Began one, "and our aspect black and blistered,

<sb/>
<lb/>Let the renown of us thy mind incline
<lb/>To tell us who thou art, who thus securely
<lb/>Thy living feet dost move along through Hell.

<sb/>
<lb/>He in whose footprints thou dost see me treading,
<lb/>Naked and skinless though he now may go,
<lb/>Was of a greater rank than thou dost think;

<sb/>
<lb/>He was the grandson of the good Gualdrada;
<lb/>His name was Guidoguerra, and in life
<lb/>Much did he with his wisdom and his sword.

<sb/>
<lb/>The other, who close by me treads the sand,
<lb/>Tegghiaio Aldobrandi is, whose fame
<lb/>Above there in the world should welcome be.

<sb/>
<lb/>And I, who with them on the cross am placed,
<lb/>Jacopo Rusticucci was; and truly
<lb/>My savage wife, more than aught else, doth harm me."

<sb/>
<lb/>Could I have been protected from the fire,
<lb/>Below I should have thrown myself among them,
<lb/>And think the Teacher would have suffered it;

<sb/>
<lb/>But as I should have burned and baked myself,
<lb/>My terror overmastered my good will,
<lb/>Which made me greedy of embracing them.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then I began: "Sorrow and not disdain
<lb/>Did your condition fix within me so,
<lb/>That tardily it wholly is stripped off,

<sb/>
<lb/>As soon as this my Lord said unto me
<lb/>Words, on account of which I thought within me
<lb/>That people such as you are were approaching.

<sb/>
<lb/>I of your city am; and evermore
<lb/>Your labours and your honourable names
<lb/>I with affection have retraced and heard.

<sb/>
<lb/>I leave the gall, and go for the sweet fruits
<lb/>Promised to me by the veracious Leader;
<lb/>But to the centre first I needs must plunge."

<sb/>
<lb/>"So may the soul for a long while conduct
<lb/>Those limbs of thine," did he make answer then,
<lb/>"And so may thy renown shine after thee,

<sb/>
<lb/>Valour and courtesy, say if they dwell
<lb/>Within our city, as they used to do,
<lb/>Or if they wholly have gone out of it;

<sb/>
<lb/>For Guglielmo Borsier, who is in torment
<lb/>With us of late, and goes there with his comrades,
<lb/>Doth greatly mortify us with his words."

<sb/>
<lb/>"The new inhabitants and the sudden gains,
<lb/>Pride and extravagance have in thee engendered,
<lb/>Florence, so that thou weep'st thereat already!"

<sb/>
<lb/>In this wise I exclaimed with face uplifted;
<lb/>And the three, taking that for my reply,
<lb/>Looked at each other, as one looks at truth.

<sb/>
<lb/>"If other times so little it doth cost thee,"
<lb/>Replied they all, "to satisfy another,
<lb/>Happy art thou, thus speaking at thy will!

<sb/>
<lb/>Therefore, if thou escape from these dark places,
<lb/>And come to rebehold the beauteous stars,
<lb/>When it shall pleasure thee to say, 'I was,'

<sb/>
<lb/>See that thou speak of us unto the people."
<lb/>Then they broke up the wheel, and in their flight
<lb/>It seemed as if their agile legs were wings.

<sb/>
<lb/>Not an Amen could possibly be said
<lb/>So rapidly as they had disappeared;
<lb/>Wherefore the Master deemed best to depart.

<sb/>
<lb/>I followed him, and little had we gone,
<lb/>Before the sound of water was so near us,
<lb/>That speaking we should hardly have been heard.

<sb/>
<lb/>Even as that stream which holdeth its own course
<lb/>The first from Monte Veso tow'rds the East,
<lb/>Upon the left-hand slope of Apennine,

<sb/>
<lb/>Which is above called Acquacheta, ere
<lb/>It down descendeth into its low bed,
<lb/>And at Forli is vacant of that name,

<sb/>
<lb/>Reverberates there above San Benedetto
<lb/>From Alps, by falling at a single leap,
<lb/>Where for a thousand there were room enough;

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus downward from a bank precipitate,
<lb/>We found resounding that dark-tinted water,
<lb/>So that it soon the ear would have offended.

<sb/>
<lb/>I had a cord around about me girt,
<lb/>And therewithal I whilom had designed
<lb/>To take the panther with the painted skin.

<sb/>
<lb/>After I this had all from me unloosed,
<lb/>As my Conductor had commanded me,
<lb/>I reached it to him, gathered up and coiled,

<sb/>
<lb/>Whereat he turned himself to the right side,
<lb/>And at a little distance from the verge,
<lb/>He cast it down into that deep abyss.

<sb/>
<lb/>"It must needs be some novelty respond,"
<lb/>I said within myself, "to the new signal
<lb/>The Master with his eye is following so."

<sb/>
<lb/>Ah me! how very cautious men should be
<lb/>With those who not alone behold the act,
<lb/>But with their wisdom look into the thoughts!

<sb/>
<lb/>He said to me: "Soon there will upward come
<lb/>What I await; and what thy thought is dreaming
<lb/>Must soon reveal itself unto thy sight."

<sb/>
<lb/>Aye to that truth which has the face of falsehood,
<lb/>A man should close his lips as far as may be,
<lb/>Because without his fault it causes shame;

<sb/>
<lb/>But here I cannot; and, Reader, by the notes
<lb/>Of this my Comedy to thee I swear,
<lb/>So may they not be void of lasting favour,

<sb/>
<lb/>Athwart that dense and darksome atmosphere
<lb/>I saw a figure swimming upward come,
<lb/>Marvellous unto every steadfast heart,

<sb/>
<lb/>Even as he returns who goeth down
<lb/>Sometimes to clear an anchor, which has grappled
<lb/>Reef, or aught else that in the sea is hidden,

<sb/>
<lb/>Who upward stretches, and draws in his feet.
    
<canto numeral="XVII"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>"Behold the monster with the pointed tail,
<lb/>Who cleaves the hills, and breaketh walls and weapons,
<lb/>Behold him who infecteth all the world."

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus unto me my Guide began to say,
<lb/>And beckoned him that he should come to shore,
<lb/>Near to the confine of the trodden marble;

<sb/>
<lb/>And that uncleanly image of deceit
<lb/>Came up and thrust ashore its head and bust,
<lb/>But on the border did not drag its tail.

<sb/>
<lb/>The face was as the face of a just man,
<lb/>Its semblance outwardly was so benign,
<lb/>And of a serpent all the trunk beside.

<sb/>
<lb/>Two paws it had, hairy unto the armpits;
<lb/>The back, and breast, and both the sides it had
<lb/>Depicted o'er with nooses and with shields.

<sb/>
<lb/>With colours more, groundwork or broidery
<lb/>Never in cloth did Tartars make nor Turks,
<lb/>Nor were such tissues by Arachne laid.

<sb/>
<lb/>As sometimes wherries lie upon the shore,
<lb/>That part are in the water, part on land;
<lb/>And as among the guzzling Germans there,

<sb/>
<lb/>The beaver plants himself to wage his war;
<lb/>So that vile monster lay upon the border,
<lb/>Which is of stone, and shutteth in the sand.

<sb/>
<lb/>His tail was wholly quivering in the void,
<lb/>Contorting upwards the envenomed fork,
<lb/>That in the guise of scorpion armed its point.

<sb/>
<lb/>The Guide said: "Now perforce must turn aside
<lb/>Our way a little, even to that beast
<lb/>Malevolent, that yonder coucheth him."

<sb/>
<lb/>We therefore on the right side descended,
<lb/>And made ten steps upon the outer verge,
<lb/>Completely to avoid the sand and flame;

<sb/>
<lb/>And after we are come to him, I see
<lb/>A little farther off upon the sand
<lb/>A people sitting near the hollow place.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then said to me the Master: "So that full
<lb/>Experience of this round thou bear away,
<lb/>Now go and see what their condition is.

<sb/>
<lb/>There let thy conversation be concise;
<lb/>Till thou returnest I will speak with him,
<lb/>That he concede to us his stalwart shoulders."

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus farther still upon the outermost
<lb/>Head of that seventh circle all alone
<lb/>I went, where sat the melancholy folk.

<sb/>
<lb/>Out of their eyes was gushing forth their woe;
<lb/>This way, that way, they helped them with their hands
<lb/>Now from the flames and now from the hot soil.

<sb/>
<lb/>Not otherwise in summer do the dogs,
<lb/>Now with the foot, now with the muzzle, when
<lb/>By fleas, or flies, or gadflies, they are bitten.

<sb/>
<lb/>When I had turned mine eyes upon the faces
<lb/>Of some, on whom the dolorous fire is falling,
<lb/>Not one of them I knew; but I perceived

<sb/>
<lb/>That from the neck of each there hung a pouch,
<lb/>Which certain colour had, and certain blazon;
<lb/>And thereupon it seems their eyes are feeding.

<sb/>
<lb/>And as I gazing round me come among them,
<lb/>Upon a yellow pouch I azure saw
<lb/>That had the face and posture of a lion.

<sb/>
<lb/>Proceeding then the current of my sight,
<lb/>Another of them saw I, red as blood,
<lb/>Display a goose more white than butter is.

<sb/>
<lb/>And one, who with an azure sow and gravid
<lb/>Emblazoned had his little pouch of white,
<lb/>Said unto me: "What dost thou in this moat?

<sb/>
<lb/>Now get thee gone; and since thou'rt still alive,
<lb/>Know that a neighbour of mine, Vitaliano,
<lb/>Will have his seat here on my left-hand side.

<sb/>
<lb/>A Paduan am I with these Florentines;
<lb/>Full many a time they thunder in mine ears,
<lb/>Exclaiming, 'Come the sovereign cavalier,

<sb/>
<lb/>He who shall bring the satchel with three goats;'"
<lb/>Then twisted he his mouth, and forth he thrust
<lb/>His tongue, like to an ox that licks its nose.

<sb/>
<lb/>And fearing lest my longer stay might vex
<lb/>Him who had warned me not to tarry long,
<lb/>Backward I turned me from those weary souls.

<sb/>
<lb/>I found my Guide, who had already mounted
<lb/>Upon the back of that wild animal,
<lb/>And said to me: "Now be both strong and bold.

<sb/>
<lb/>Now we descend by stairways such as these;
<lb/>Mount thou in front, for I will be midway,
<lb/>So that the tail may have no power to harm thee."

<sb/>
<lb/>Such as he is who has so near the ague
<lb/>Of quartan that his nails are blue already,
<lb/>And trembles all, but looking at the shade;

<sb/>
<lb/>Even such became I at those proffered words;
<lb/>But shame in me his menaces produced,
<lb/>Which maketh servant strong before good master.

<sb/>
<lb/>I seated me upon those monstrous shoulders;
<lb/>I wished to say, and yet the voice came not
<lb/>As I believed, "Take heed that thou embrace me."

<sb/>
<lb/>But he, who other times had rescued me
<lb/>In other peril, soon as I had mounted,
<lb/>Within his arms encircled and sustained me,

<sb/>
<lb/>And said: "Now, Geryon, bestir thyself;
<lb/>The circles large, and the descent be little;
<lb/>Think of the novel burden which thou hast."

<sb/>
<lb/>Even as the little vessel shoves from shore,
<lb/>Backward, still backward, so he thence withdrew;
<lb/>And when he wholly felt himself afloat,

<sb/>
<lb/>There where his breast had been he turned his tail,
<lb/>And that extended like an eel he moved,
<lb/>And with his paws drew to himself the air.

<sb/>
<lb/>A greater fear I do not think there was
<lb/>What time abandoned Phaeton the reins,
<lb/>Whereby the heavens, as still appears, were scorched;

<sb/>
<lb/>Nor when the wretched Icarus his flanks
<lb/>Felt stripped of feathers by the melting wax,
<lb/>His father crying, "An ill way thou takest!"

<sb/>
<lb/>Than was my own, when I perceived myself
<lb/>On all sides in the air, and saw extinguished
<lb/>The sight of everything but of the monster.

<sb/>
<lb/>Onward he goeth, swimming slowly, slowly;
<lb/>Wheels and descends, but I perceive it only
<lb/>By wind upon my face and from below.

<sb/>
<lb/>I heard already on the right the whirlpool
<lb/>Making a horrible crashing under us;
<lb/>Whence I thrust out my head with eyes cast downward.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then was I still more fearful of the abyss;
<lb/>Because I fires beheld, and heard laments,
<lb/>Whereat I, trembling, all the closer cling.

<sb/>
<lb/>I saw then, for before I had not seen it,
<lb/>The turning and descending, by great horrors
<lb/>That were approaching upon divers sides.

<sb/>
<lb/>As falcon who has long been on the wing,
<lb/>Who, without seeing either lure or bird,
<lb/>Maketh the falconer say, "Ah me, thou stoopest,"

<sb/>
<lb/>Descendeth weary, whence he started swiftly,
<lb/>Thorough a hundred circles, and alights
<lb/>Far from his master, sullen and disdainful;

<sb/>
<lb/>Even thus did Geryon place us on the bottom,
<lb/>Close to the bases of the rough-hewn rock,
<lb/>And being disencumbered of our persons,

<sb/>
<lb/>He sped away as arrow from the string.

</pouch_ring>
    
</circle>    

<circle number="8" main_sin="fraud">
        
<canto numeral="XVIII"/>
    
<pouch_ring number="1" sub_sin="panderer_seducer">

<sb/>
<lb/>There is a place in Hell called Malebolge,
<lb/>Wholly of stone and of an iron colour,
<lb/>As is the circle that around it turns.

<sb/>
<lb/>Right in the middle of the field malign
<lb/>There yawns a well exceeding wide and deep,
<lb/>Of which its place the structure will recount.

<sb/>
<lb/>Round, then, is that enclosure which remains
<lb/>Between the well and foot of the high, hard bank,
<lb/>And has distinct in valleys ten its bottom.

<sb/>
<lb/>As where for the protection of the walls
<lb/>Many and many moats surround the castles,
<lb/>The part in which they are a figure forms,

<sb/>
<lb/>Just such an image those presented there;
<lb/>And as about such strongholds from their gates
<lb/>Unto the outer bank are little bridges,

<sb/>
<lb/>So from the precipice's base did crags
<lb/>Project, which intersected dikes and moats,
<lb/>Unto the well that truncates and collects them.

<sb/>
<lb/>Within this place, down shaken from the back
<lb/>Of Geryon, we found us; and the Poet
<lb/>Held to the left, and I moved on behind.

<sb/>
<lb/>Upon my right hand I beheld new anguish,
<lb/>New torments, and new wielders of the lash,
<lb/>Wherewith the foremost Bolgia was replete.

<sb/>
<lb/>Down at the bottom were the sinners naked;
<lb/>This side the middle came they facing us,
<lb/>Beyond it, with us, but with greater steps;

<sb/>
<lb/>Even as the Romans, for the mighty host,
<lb/>The year of Jubilee, upon the bridge,
<lb/>Have chosen a mode to pass the people over;

<sb/>
<lb/>For all upon one side towards the Castle
<lb/>Their faces have, and go unto St. Peter's;
<lb/>On the other side they go towards the Mountain.

<sb/>
<lb/>This side and that, along the livid stone
<lb/>Beheld I horned demons with great scourges,
<lb/>Who cruelly were beating them behind.

<sb/>
<lb/>Ah me! how they did make them lift their legs
<lb/>At the first blows! and sooth not any one
<lb/>The second waited for, nor for the third.

<sb/>
<lb/>While I was going on, mine eyes by one
<lb/>Encountered were; and straight I said: "Already
<lb/>With sight of this one I am not unfed."

<sb/>
<lb/>Therefore I stayed my feet to make him out,
<lb/>And with me the sweet Guide came to a stand,
<lb/>And to my going somewhat back assented;

<sb/>
<lb/>And he, the scourged one, thought to hide himself,
<lb/>Lowering his face, but little it availed him;
<lb/>For said I: "Thou that castest down thine eyes,

<sb/>
<lb/>If false are not the features which thou bearest,
<lb/>Thou art Venedico Caccianimico;
<lb/>But what doth bring thee to such pungent sauces?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "Unwillingly I tell it;
<lb/>But forces me thine utterance distinct,
<lb/>Which makes me recollect the ancient world.

<sb/>
<lb/>I was the one who the fair Ghisola
<lb/>Induced to grant the wishes of the Marquis,
<lb/>Howe'er the shameless story may be told.

<sb/>
<lb/>Not the sole Bolognese am I who weeps here;
<lb/>Nay, rather is this place so full of them,
<lb/>That not so many tongues to-day are taught

<sb/>
<lb/>'Twixt Reno and Savena to say 'sipa;'
<lb/>And if thereof thou wishest pledge or proof,
<lb/>Bring to thy mind our avaricious heart."

<sb/>
<lb/>While speaking in this manner, with his scourge
<lb/>A demon smote him, and said: "Get thee gone
<lb/>Pander, there are no women here for coin."

<sb/>
<lb/>I joined myself again unto mine Escort;
<lb/>Thereafterward with footsteps few we came
<lb/>To where a crag projected from the bank.

<sb/>
<lb/>This very easily did we ascend,
<lb/>And turning to the right along its ridge,
<lb/>From those eternal circles we departed.

<sb/>
<lb/>When we were there, where it is hollowed out
<lb/>Beneath, to give a passage to the scourged,
<lb/>The Guide said: "Wait, and see that on thee strike

<sb/>
<lb/>The vision of those others evil-born,
<lb/>Of whom thou hast not yet beheld the faces,
<lb/>Because together with us they have gone."

<sb/>
<lb/>From the old bridge we looked upon the train
<lb/>Which tow'rds us came upon the other border,
<lb/>And which the scourges in like manner smite.

<sb/>
<lb/>And the good Master, without my inquiring,
<lb/>Said to me: "See that tall one who is coming,
<lb/>And for his pain seems not to shed a tear;

<sb/>
<lb/>Still what a royal aspect he retains!
<lb/>That Jason is, who by his heart and cunning
<lb/>The Colchians of the Ram made destitute.

<sb/>
<lb/>He by the isle of Lemnos passed along
<lb/>After the daring women pitiless
<lb/>Had unto death devoted all their males.

<sb/>
<lb/>There with his tokens and with ornate words
<lb/>Did he deceive Hypsipyle, the maiden
<lb/>Who first, herself, had all the rest deceived.

<sb/>
<lb/>There did he leave her pregnant and forlorn;
<lb/>Such sin unto such punishment condemns him,
<lb/>And also for Medea is vengeance done.

<sb/>
<lb/>With him go those who in such wise deceive;
<lb/>And this sufficient be of the first valley
<lb/>To know, and those that in its jaws it holds."

<sb/>
<lb/>We were already where the narrow path
<lb/>Crosses athwart the second dike, and forms
<lb/>Of that a buttress for another arch.
    
</pouch_ring>
    
<pouch_ring number="2" sub_sin="flatterer">

<sb/>
<lb/>Thence we heard people, who are making moan
<lb/>In the next Bolgia, snorting with their muzzles,
<lb/>And with their palms beating upon themselves

<sb/>
<lb/>The margins were incrusted with a mould
<lb/>By exhalation from below, that sticks there,
<lb/>And with the eyes and nostrils wages war.

<sb/>
<lb/>The bottom is so deep, no place suffices
<lb/>To give us sight of it, without ascending
<lb/>The arch's back, where most the crag impends.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thither we came, and thence down in the moat
<lb/>I saw a people smothered in a filth
<lb/>That out of human privies seemed to flow;

<sb/>
<lb/>And whilst below there with mine eye I search,
<lb/>I saw one with his head so foul with ordure,
<lb/>It was not clear if he were clerk or layman.

<sb/>
<lb/>He screamed to me: "Wherefore art thou so eager
<lb/>To look at me more than the other foul ones?"
<lb/>And I to him: "Because, if I remember,

<sb/>
<lb/>I have already seen thee with dry hair,
<lb/>And thou'rt Alessio Interminei of Lucca;
<lb/>Therefore I eye thee more than all the others."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he thereon, belabouring his pumpkin:
<lb/>"The flatteries have submerged me here below,
<lb/>Wherewith my tongue was never surfeited."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then said to me the Guide: "See that thou thrust
<lb/>Thy visage somewhat farther in advance,
<lb/>That with thine eyes thou well the face attain

<sb/>
<lb/>Of that uncleanly and dishevelled drab,
<lb/>Who there doth scratch herself with filthy nails,
<lb/>And crouches now, and now on foot is standing.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thais the harlot is it, who replied
<lb/>Unto her paramour, when he said, 'Have I
<lb/>Great gratitude from thee?'--'Nay, marvellous;'

<sb/>
<lb/>And herewith let our sight be satisfied."

</pouch_ring>

<canto numeral="XIX"/>

<pouch_ring number="3" sub_sin="simonist">

<sb/>
<lb/>O Simon Magus, O forlorn disciples,
<lb/>Ye who the things of God, which ought to be
<lb/>The brides of holiness, rapaciously

<sb/>
<lb/>For silver and for gold do prostitute,
<lb/>Now it behoves for you the trumpet sound,
<lb/>Because in this third Bolgia ye abide.

<sb/>
<lb/>We had already on the following tomb
<lb/>Ascended to that portion of the crag
<lb/>Which o'er the middle of the moat hangs plumb.

<sb/>
<lb/>Wisdom supreme, O how great art thou showest
<lb/>In heaven, in earth, and in the evil world,
<lb/>And with what justice doth thy power distribute!

<sb/>
<lb/>I saw upon the sides and on the bottom
<lb/>The livid stone with perforations filled,
<lb/>All of one size, and every one was round.

<sb/>
<lb/>To me less ample seemed they not, nor greater
<lb/>Than those that in my beautiful Saint John
<lb/>Are fashioned for the place of the baptisers,

<sb/>
<lb/>And one of which, not many years ago,
<lb/>I broke for some one, who was drowning in it;
<lb/>Be this a seal all men to undeceive.

<sb/>
<lb/>Out of the mouth of each one there protruded
<lb/>The feet of a transgressor, and the legs
<lb/>Up to the calf, the rest within remained.

<sb/>
<lb/>In all of them the soles were both on fire;
<lb/>Wherefore the joints so violently quivered,
<lb/>They would have snapped asunder withes and bands.

<sb/>
<lb/>Even as the flame of unctuous things is wont
<lb/>To move upon the outer surface only,
<lb/>So likewise was it there from heel to point.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Master, who is that one who writhes himself,
<lb/>More than his other comrades quivering,"
<lb/>I said, "and whom a redder flame is sucking?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "If thou wilt have me bear thee
<lb/>Down there along that bank which lowest lies,
<lb/>From him thou'lt know his errors and himself."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I: "What pleases thee, to me is pleasing;
<lb/>Thou art my Lord, and knowest that I depart not
<lb/>From thy desire, and knowest what is not spoken."

<sb/>
<lb/>Straightway upon the fourth dike we arrived;
<lb/>We turned, and on the left-hand side descended
<lb/>Down to the bottom full of holes and narrow.

<sb/>
<lb/>And the good Master yet from off his haunch
<lb/>Deposed me not, till to the hole he brought me
<lb/>Of him who so lamented with his shanks.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Whoe'er thou art, that standest upside down,
<lb/>O doleful soul, implanted like a stake,"
<lb/>To say began I, "if thou canst, speak out."

<sb/>
<lb/>I stood even as the friar who is confessing
<lb/>The false assassin, who, when he is fixed,
<lb/>Recalls him, so that death may be delayed.

<sb/>
<lb/>And he cried out: "Dost thou stand there already,
<lb/>Dost thou stand there already, Boniface?
<lb/>By many years the record lied to me.

<sb/>
<lb/>Art thou so early satiate with that wealth,
<lb/>For which thou didst not fear to take by fraud
<lb/>The beautiful Lady, and then work her woe?"

<sb/>
<lb/>Such I became, as people are who stand,
<lb/>Not comprehending what is answered them,
<lb/>As if bemocked, and know not how to answer.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then said Virgilius: "Say to him straightway,
<lb/>'I am not he, I am not he thou thinkest.'"
<lb/>And I replied as was imposed on me.

<sb/>
<lb/>Whereat the spirit writhed with both his feet,
<lb/>Then, sighing, with a voice of lamentation
<lb/>Said to me: "Then what wantest thou of me?

<sb/>
<lb/>If who I am thou carest so much to know,
<lb/>That thou on that account hast crossed the bank,
<lb/>Know that I vested was with the great mantle;

<sb/>
<lb/>And truly was I son of the She-bear,
<lb/>So eager to advance the cubs, that wealth
<lb/>Above, and here myself, I pocketed.

<sb/>
<lb/>Beneath my head the others are dragged down
<lb/>Who have preceded me in simony,
<lb/>Flattened along the fissure of the rock.

<sb/>
<lb/>Below there I shall likewise fall, whenever
<lb/>That one shall come who I believed thou wast,
<lb/>What time the sudden question I proposed.

<sb/>
<lb/>But longer I my feet already toast,
<lb/>And here have been in this way upside down,
<lb/>Than he will planted stay with reddened feet;

<sb/>
<lb/>For after him shall come of fouler deed
<lb/>From tow'rds the west a Pastor without law,
<lb/>Such as befits to cover him and me.

<sb/>
<lb/>New Jason will he be, of whom we read
<lb/>In Maccabees; and as his king was pliant,
<lb/>So he who governs France shall be to this one."

<sb/>
<lb/>I do not know if I were here too bold,
<lb/>That him I answered only in this metre:
<lb/>"I pray thee tell me now how great a treasure

<sb/>
<lb/>Our Lord demanded of Saint Peter first,
<lb/>Before he put the keys into his keeping?
<lb/>Truly he nothing asked but 'Follow me.'

<sb/>
<lb/>Nor Peter nor the rest asked of Matthias
<lb/>Silver or gold, when he by lot was chosen
<lb/>Unto the place the guilty soul had lost.

<sb/>
<lb/>Therefore stay here, for thou art justly punished,
<lb/>And keep safe guard o'er the ill-gotten money,
<lb/>Which caused thee to be valiant against Charles.

<sb/>
<lb/>And were it not that still forbids it me
<lb/>The reverence for the keys superlative
<lb/>Thou hadst in keeping in the gladsome life,

<sb/>
<lb/>I would make use of words more grievous still;
<lb/>Because your avarice afflicts the world,
<lb/>Trampling the good and lifting the depraved.

<sb/>
<lb/>The Evangelist you Pastors had in mind,
<lb/>When she who sitteth upon many waters
<lb/>To fornicate with kings by him was seen;

<sb/>
<lb/>The same who with the seven heads was born,
<lb/>And power and strength from the ten horns received,
<lb/>So long as virtue to her spouse was pleasing.

<sb/>
<lb/>Ye have made yourselves a god of gold and silver;
<lb/>And from the idolater how differ ye,
<lb/>Save that he one, and ye a hundred worship?

<sb/>
<lb/>Ah, Constantine! of how much ill was mother,
<lb/>Not thy conversion, but that marriage dower
<lb/>Which the first wealthy Father took from thee!"

<sb/>
<lb/>And while I sang to him such notes as these,
<lb/>Either that anger or that conscience stung him,
<lb/>He struggled violently with both his feet.

<sb/>
<lb/>I think in sooth that it my Leader pleased,
<lb/>With such contented lip he listened ever
<lb/>Unto the sound of the true words expressed.

<sb/>
<lb/>Therefore with both his arms he took me up,
<lb/>And when he had me all upon his breast,
<lb/>Remounted by the way where he descended.

<sb/>
<lb/>Nor did he tire to have me clasped to him;
<lb/>But bore me to the summit of the arch
<lb/>Which from the fourth dike to the fifth is passage.

<sb/>
<lb/>There tenderly he laid his burden down,
<lb/>Tenderly on the crag uneven and steep,
<lb/>That would have been hard passage for the goats:

<sb/>
<lb/>Thence was unveiled to me another valley.
    
</pouch_ring>

<canto numeral="XX"/>

<pouch_ring number="4" sub_sin="sorcerer">

<sb/>
<lb/>Of a new pain behoves me to make verses
<lb/>And give material to the twentieth canto
<lb/>Of the first song, which is of the submerged.

<sb/>
<lb/>I was already thoroughly disposed
<lb/>To peer down into the uncovered depth,
<lb/>Which bathed itself with tears of agony;

<sb/>
<lb/>And people saw I through the circular valley,
<lb/>Silent and weeping, coming at the pace
<lb/>Which in this world the Litanies assume.

<sb/>
<lb/>As lower down my sight descended on them,
<lb/>Wondrously each one seemed to be distorted
<lb/>From chin to the beginning of the chest;

<sb/>
<lb/>For tow'rds the reins the countenance was turned,
<lb/>And backward it behoved them to advance,
<lb/>As to look forward had been taken from them.

<sb/>
<lb/>Perchance indeed by violence of palsy
<lb/>Some one has been thus wholly turned awry;
<lb/>But I ne'er saw it, nor believe it can be.

<sb/>
<lb/>As God may let thee, Reader, gather fruit
<lb/>From this thy reading, think now for thyself
<lb/>How I could ever keep my face unmoistened,

<sb/>
<lb/>When our own image near me I beheld
<lb/>Distorted so, the weeping of the eyes
<lb/>Along the fissure bathed the hinder parts.

<sb/>
<lb/>Truly I wept, leaning upon a peak
<lb/>Of the hard crag, so that my Escort said
<lb/>To me: "Art thou, too, of the other fools?

<sb/>
<lb/>Here pity lives when it is wholly dead;
<lb/>Who is a greater reprobate than he
<lb/>Who feels compassion at the doom divine?

<sb/>
<lb/>Lift up, lift up thy head, and see for whom
<lb/>Opened the earth before the Thebans' eyes;
<lb/>Wherefore they all cried: 'Whither rushest thou,

<sb/>
<lb/>Amphiaraus?  Why dost leave the war?'
<lb/>And downward ceased he not to fall amain
<lb/>As far as Minos, who lays hold on all.

<sb/>
<lb/>See, he has made a bosom of his shoulders!
<lb/>Because he wished to see too far before him
<lb/>Behind he looks, and backward goes his way:

<sb/>
<lb/>Behold Tiresias, who his semblance changed,
<lb/>When from a male a female he became,
<lb/>His members being all of them transformed;

<sb/>
<lb/>And afterwards was forced to strike once more
<lb/>The two entangled serpents with his rod,
<lb/>Ere he could have again his manly plumes.

<sb/>
<lb/>That Aruns is, who backs the other's belly,
<lb/>Who in the hills of Luni, there where grubs
<lb/>The Carrarese who houses underneath,

<sb/>
<lb/>Among the marbles white a cavern had
<lb/>For his abode; whence to behold the stars
<lb/>And sea, the view was not cut off from him.

<sb/>
<lb/>And she there, who is covering up her breasts,
<lb/>Which thou beholdest not, with loosened tresses,
<lb/>And on that side has all the hairy skin,

<sb/>
<lb/>Was Manto, who made quest through many lands,
<lb/>Afterwards tarried there where I was born;
<lb/>Whereof I would thou list to me a little.

<sb/>
<lb/>After her father had from life departed,
<lb/>And the city of Bacchus had become enslaved,
<lb/>She a long season wandered through the world.

<sb/>
<lb/>Above in beauteous Italy lies a lake
<lb/>At the Alp's foot that shuts in Germany
<lb/>Over Tyrol, and has the name Benaco.

<sb/>
<lb/>By a thousand springs, I think, and more, is bathed,
<lb/>'Twixt Garda and Val Camonica, Pennino,
<lb/>With water that grows stagnant in that lake.

<sb/>
<lb/>Midway a place is where the Trentine Pastor,
<lb/>And he of Brescia, and the Veronese
<lb/>Might give his blessing, if he passed that way.

<sb/>
<lb/>Sitteth Peschiera, fortress fair and strong,
<lb/>To front the Brescians and the Bergamasks,
<lb/>Where round about the bank descendeth lowest.

<sb/>
<lb/>There of necessity must fall whatever
<lb/>In bosom of Benaco cannot stay,
<lb/>And grows a river down through verdant pastures.

<sb/>
<lb/>Soon as the water doth begin to run,
<lb/>No more Benaco is it called, but Mincio,
<lb/>Far as Governo, where it falls in Po.

<sb/>
<lb/>Not far it runs before it finds a plain
<lb/>In which it spreads itself, and makes it marshy,
<lb/>And oft 'tis wont in summer to be sickly.

<sb/>
<lb/>Passing that way the virgin pitiless
<lb/>Land in the middle of the fen descried,
<lb/>Untilled and naked of inhabitants;

<sb/>
<lb/>There to escape all human intercourse,
<lb/>She with her servants stayed, her arts to practise
<lb/>And lived, and left her empty body there.

<sb/>
<lb/>The men, thereafter, who were scattered round,
<lb/>Collected in that place, which was made strong
<lb/>By the lagoon it had on every side;

<sb/>
<lb/>They built their city over those dead bones,
<lb/>And, after her who first the place selected,
<lb/>Mantua named it, without other omen.

<sb/>
<lb/>Its people once within more crowded were,
<lb/>Ere the stupidity of Casalodi
<lb/>From Pinamonte had received deceit.

<sb/>
<lb/>Therefore I caution thee, if e'er thou hearest
<lb/>Originate my city otherwise,
<lb/>No falsehood may the verity defraud."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I: "My Master, thy discourses are
<lb/>To me so certain, and so take my faith,
<lb/>That unto me the rest would be spent coals.

<sb/>
<lb/>But tell me of the people who are passing,
<lb/>If any one note-worthy thou beholdest,
<lb/>For only unto that my mind reverts."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then said he to me: "He who from the cheek
<lb/>Thrusts out his beard upon his swarthy shoulders
<lb/>Was, at the time when Greece was void of males,

<sb/>
<lb/>So that there scarce remained one in the cradle,
<lb/>An augur, and with Calchas gave the moment,
<lb/>In Aulis, when to sever the first cable.

<sb/>
<lb/>Eryphylus his name was, and so sings
<lb/>My lofty Tragedy in some part or other;
<lb/>That knowest thou well, who knowest the whole of it.

<sb/>
<lb/>The next, who is so slender in the flanks,
<lb/>Was Michael Scott, who of a verity
<lb/>Of magical illusions knew the game.

<sb/>
<lb/>Behold Guido Bonatti, behold Asdente,
<lb/>Who now unto his leather and his thread
<lb/>Would fain have stuck, but he too late repents.

<sb/>
<lb/>Behold the wretched ones, who left the needle,
<lb/>The spool and rock, and made them fortune-tellers;
<lb/>They wrought their magic spells with herb and image.

<sb/>
<lb/>But come now, for already holds the confines
<lb/>Of both the hemispheres, and under Seville
<lb/>Touches the ocean-wave, Cain and the thorns,

<sb/>
<lb/>And yesternight the moon was round already;
<lb/>Thou shouldst remember well it did not harm thee
<lb/>From time to time within the forest deep."

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus spake he to me, and we walked the while.
    
</pouch_ring>
    
<canto numeral="XXI"/>

<pouch_ring number="5" sub_sin="barrator">

<sb/>
<lb/>From bridge to bridge thus, speaking other things
<lb/>Of which my Comedy cares not to sing,
<lb/>We came along, and held the summit, when

<sb/>
<lb/>We halted to behold another fissure
<lb/>Of Malebolge and other vain laments;
<lb/>And I beheld it marvellously dark.

<sb/>
<lb/>As in the Arsenal of the Venetians
<lb/>Boils in the winter the tenacious pitch
<lb/>To smear their unsound vessels o'er again,

<sb/>
<lb/>For sail they cannot; and instead thereof
<lb/>One makes his vessel new, and one recaulks
<lb/>The ribs of that which many a voyage has made;

<sb/>
<lb/>One hammers at the prow, one at the stern,
<lb/>This one makes oars, and that one cordage twists,
<lb/>Another mends the mainsail and the mizzen;

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus, not by fire, but by the art divine,
<lb/>Was boiling down below there a dense pitch
<lb/>Which upon every side the bank belimed.

<sb/>
<lb/>I saw it, but I did not see within it
<lb/>Aught but the bubbles that the boiling raised,
<lb/>And all swell up and resubside compressed.

<sb/>
<lb/>The while below there fixedly I gazed,
<lb/>My Leader, crying out: "Beware, beware!"
<lb/>Drew me unto himself from where I stood.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then I turned round, as one who is impatient
<lb/>To see what it behoves him to escape,
<lb/>And whom a sudden terror doth unman,

<sb/>
<lb/>Who, while he looks, delays not his departure;
<lb/>And I beheld behind us a black devil,
<lb/>Running along upon the crag, approach.

<sb/>
<lb/>Ah, how ferocious was he in his aspect!
<lb/>And how he seemed to me in action ruthless,
<lb/>With open wings and light upon his feet!

<sb/>
<lb/>His shoulders, which sharp-pointed were and high,
<lb/>A sinner did encumber with both haunches,
<lb/>And he held clutched the sinews of the feet.

<sb/>
<lb/>From off our bridge, he said: "O Malebranche,
<lb/>Behold one of the elders of Saint Zita;
<lb/>Plunge him beneath, for I return for others

<sb/>
<lb/>Unto that town, which is well furnished with them.
<lb/>All there are barrators, except Bonturo;
<lb/>No into Yes for money there is changed."

<sb/>
<lb/>He hurled him down, and over the hard crag
<lb/>Turned round, and never was a mastiff loosened
<lb/>In so much hurry to pursue a thief.

<sb/>
<lb/>The other sank, and rose again face downward;
<lb/>But the demons, under cover of the bridge,
<lb/>Cried: "Here the Santo Volto has no place!

<sb/>
<lb/>Here swims one otherwise than in the Serchio;
<lb/>Therefore, if for our gaffs thou wishest not,
<lb/>Do not uplift thyself above the pitch."

<sb/>
<lb/>They seized him then with more than a hundred rakes;
<lb/>They said: "It here behoves thee to dance covered,
<lb/>That, if thou canst, thou secretly mayest pilfer."

<sb/>
<lb/>Not otherwise the cooks their scullions make
<lb/>Immerse into the middle of the caldron
<lb/>The meat with hooks, so that it may not float.

<sb/>
<lb/>Said the good Master to me: "That it be not
<lb/>Apparent thou art here, crouch thyself down
<lb/>Behind a jag, that thou mayest have some screen;

<sb/>
<lb/>And for no outrage that is done to me
<lb/>Be thou afraid, because these things I know,
<lb/>For once before was I in such a scuffle."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then he passed on beyond the bridge's head,
<lb/>And as upon the sixth bank he arrived,
<lb/>Need was for him to have a steadfast front.

<sb/>
<lb/>With the same fury, and the same uproar,
<lb/>As dogs leap out upon a mendicant,
<lb/>Who on a sudden begs, where'er he stops,

<sb/>
<lb/>They issued from beneath the little bridge,
<lb/>And turned against him all their grappling-irons;
<lb/>But he cried out: "Be none of you malignant!

<sb/>
<lb/>Before those hooks of yours lay hold of me,
<lb/>Let one of you step forward, who may hear me,
<lb/>And then take counsel as to grappling me."

<sb/>
<lb/>They all cried out: "Let Malacoda go;"
<lb/>Whereat one started, and the rest stood still,
<lb/>And he came to him, saying: "What avails it?"

<sb/>
<lb/>"Thinkest thou, Malacoda, to behold me
<lb/>Advanced into this place," my Master said,
<lb/>"Safe hitherto from all your skill of fence,

<sb/>
<lb/>Without the will divine, and fate auspicious?
<lb/>Let me go on, for it in Heaven is willed
<lb/>That I another show this savage road."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then was his arrogance so humbled in him,
<lb/>That he let fall his grapnel at his feet,
<lb/>And to the others said: "Now strike him not."

<sb/>
<lb/>And unto me my Guide: "O thou, who sittest
<lb/>Among the splinters of the bridge crouched down,
<lb/>Securely now return to me again."

<sb/>
<lb/>Wherefore I started and came swiftly to him;
<lb/>And all the devils forward thrust themselves,
<lb/>So that I feared they would not keep their compact.

<sb/>
<lb/>And thus beheld I once afraid the soldiers
<lb/>Who issued under safeguard from Caprona,
<lb/>Seeing themselves among so many foes.

<sb/>
<lb/>Close did I press myself with all my person
<lb/>Beside my Leader, and turned not mine eyes
<lb/>From off their countenance, which was not good.

<sb/>
<lb/>They lowered their rakes, and "Wilt thou have me hit him,"
<lb/>They said to one another, "on the rump?"
<lb/>And answered: "Yes; see that thou nick him with it."

<sb/>
<lb/>But the same demon who was holding parley
<lb/>With my Conductor turned him very quickly,
<lb/>And said: "Be quiet, be quiet, Scarmiglione;"

<sb/>
<lb/>Then said to us: "You can no farther go
<lb/>Forward upon this crag, because is lying
<lb/>All shattered, at the bottom, the sixth arch.

<sb/>
<lb/>And if it still doth please you to go onward,
<lb/>Pursue your way along upon this rock;
<lb/>Near is another crag that yields a path.

<sb/>
<lb/>Yesterday, five hours later than this hour,
<lb/>One thousand and two hundred sixty-six
<lb/>Years were complete, that here the way was broken.

<sb/>
<lb/>I send in that direction some of mine
<lb/>To see if any one doth air himself;
<lb/>Go ye with them; for they will not be vicious.

<sb/>
<lb/>Step forward, Alichino and Calcabrina,"
<lb/>Began he to cry out, "and thou, Cagnazzo;
<lb/>And Barbariccia, do thou guide the ten.

<sb/>
<lb/>Come forward, Libicocco and Draghignazzo,
<lb/>And tusked Ciriatto and Graffiacane,
<lb/>And Farfarello and mad Rubicante;

<sb/>
<lb/>Search ye all round about the boiling pitch;
<lb/>Let these be safe as far as the next crag,
<lb/>That all unbroken passes o'er the dens."

<sb/>
<lb/>"O me! what is it, Master, that I see?
<lb/>Pray let us go," I said, "without an escort,
<lb/>If thou knowest how, since for myself I ask none.

<sb/>
<lb/>If thou art as observant as thy wont is,
<lb/>Dost thou not see that they do gnash their teeth,
<lb/>And with their brows are threatening woe to us?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "I will not have thee fear;
<lb/>Let them gnash on, according to their fancy,
<lb/>Because they do it for those boiling wretches."

<sb/>
<lb/>Along the left-hand dike they wheeled about;
<lb/>But first had each one thrust his tongue between
<lb/>His teeth towards their leader for a signal;

<sb/>
<lb/>And he had made a trumpet of his rump.
        
<canto numeral="XXII"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>I have erewhile seen horsemen moving camp,
<lb/>Begin the storming, and their muster make,
<lb/>And sometimes starting off for their escape;

<sb/>
<lb/>Vaunt-couriers have I seen upon your land,
<lb/>O Aretines, and foragers go forth,
<lb/>Tournaments stricken, and the joustings run,

<sb/>
<lb/>Sometimes with trumpets and sometimes with bells,
<lb/>With kettle-drums, and signals of the castles,
<lb/>And with our own, and with outlandish things,

<sb/>
<lb/>But never yet with bagpipe so uncouth
<lb/>Did I see horsemen move, nor infantry,
<lb/>Nor ship by any sign of land or star.

<sb/>
<lb/>We went upon our way with the ten demons;
<lb/>Ah, savage company! but in the church
<lb/>With saints, and in the tavern with the gluttons!

<sb/>
<lb/>Ever upon the pitch was my intent,
<lb/>To see the whole condition of that Bolgia,
<lb/>And of the people who therein were burned.

<sb/>
<lb/>Even as the dolphins, when they make a sign
<lb/>To mariners by arching of the back,
<lb/>That they should counsel take to save their vessel,

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus sometimes, to alleviate his pain,
<lb/>One of the sinners would display his back,
<lb/>And in less time conceal it than it lightens.

<sb/>
<lb/>As on the brink of water in a ditch
<lb/>The frogs stand only with their muzzles out,
<lb/>So that they hide their feet and other bulk,

<sb/>
<lb/>So upon every side the sinners stood;
<lb/>But ever as Barbariccia near them came,
<lb/>Thus underneath the boiling they withdrew.

<sb/>
<lb/>I saw, and still my heart doth shudder at it,
<lb/>One waiting thus, even as it comes to pass
<lb/>One frog remains, and down another dives;

<sb/>
<lb/>And Graffiacan, who most confronted him,
<lb/>Grappled him by his tresses smeared with pitch,
<lb/>And drew him up, so that he seemed an otter.

<sb/>
<lb/>I knew, before, the names of all of them,
<lb/>So had I noted them when they were chosen,
<lb/>And when they called each other, listened how.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O Rubicante, see that thou do lay
<lb/>Thy claws upon him, so that thou mayst flay him,"
<lb/>Cried all together the accursed ones.

<sb/>
<lb/>And I: "My Master, see to it, if thou canst,
<lb/>That thou mayst know who is the luckless wight,
<lb/>Thus come into his adversaries' hands."

<sb/>
<lb/>Near to the side of him my Leader drew,
<lb/>Asked of him whence he was; and he replied:
<lb/>"I in the kingdom of Navarre was born;

<sb/>
<lb/>My mother placed me servant to a lord,
<lb/>For she had borne me to a ribald knave,
<lb/>Destroyer of himself and of his things.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then I domestic was of good King Thibault;
<lb/>I set me there to practise barratry,
<lb/>For which I pay the reckoning in this heat."

<sb/>
<lb/>And Ciriatto, from whose mouth projected,
<lb/>On either side, a tusk, as in a boar,
<lb/>Caused him to feel how one of them could rip.

<sb/>
<lb/>Among malicious cats the mouse had come;
<lb/>But Barbariccia clasped him in his arms,
<lb/>And said: "Stand ye aside, while I enfork him."

<sb/>
<lb/>And to my Master he turned round his head;
<lb/>"Ask him again," he said, "if more thou wish
<lb/>To know from him, before some one destroy him."

<sb/>
<lb/>The Guide: "Now tell then of the other culprits;
<lb/>Knowest thou any one who is a Latian,
<lb/>Under the pitch?"  And he: "I separated

<sb/>
<lb/>Lately from one who was a neighbour to it;
<lb/>Would that I still were covered up with him,
<lb/>For I should fear not either claw nor hook!"

<sb/>
<lb/>And Libicocco: "We have borne too much;"
<lb/>And with his grapnel seized him by the arm,
<lb/>So that, by rending, he tore off a tendon.

<sb/>
<lb/>Eke Draghignazzo wished to pounce upon him
<lb/>Down at the legs; whence their Decurion
<lb/>Turned round and round about with evil look.

<sb/>
<lb/>When they again somewhat were pacified,
<lb/>Of him, who still was looking at his wound,
<lb/>Demanded my Conductor without stay:

<sb/>
<lb/>"Who was that one, from whom a luckless parting
<lb/>Thou sayest thou hast made, to come ashore?"
<lb/>And he replied: "It was the Friar Gomita,

<sb/>
<lb/>He of Gallura, vessel of all fraud,
<lb/>Who had the enemies of his Lord in hand,
<lb/>And dealt so with them each exults thereat;

<sb/>
<lb/>Money he took, and let them smoothly off,
<lb/>As he says; and in other offices
<lb/>A barrator was he, not mean but sovereign.

<sb/>
<lb/>Foregathers with him one Don Michael Zanche
<lb/>Of Logodoro; and of Sardinia
<lb/>To gossip never do their tongues feel tired.

<sb/>
<lb/>O me! see that one, how he grinds his teeth;
<lb/>Still farther would I speak, but am afraid
<lb/>Lest he to scratch my itch be making ready."

<sb/>
<lb/>And the grand Provost, turned to Farfarello,
<lb/>Who rolled his eyes about as if to strike,
<lb/>Said: "Stand aside there, thou malicious bird."

<sb/>
<lb/>"If you desire either to see or hear,"
<lb/>The terror-stricken recommenced thereon,
<lb/>"Tuscans or Lombards, I will make them come.

<sb/>
<lb/>But let the Malebranche cease a little,
<lb/>So that these may not their revenges fear,
<lb/>And I, down sitting in this very place,

<sb/>
<lb/>For one that I am will make seven come,
<lb/>When I shall whistle, as our custom is
<lb/>To do whenever one of us comes out."

<sb/>
<lb/>Cagnazzo at these words his muzzle lifted,
<lb/>Shaking his head, and said: "Just hear the trick
<lb/>Which he has thought of, down to throw himself!"

<sb/>
<lb/>Whence he, who snares in great abundance had,
<lb/>Responded: "I by far too cunning am,
<lb/>When I procure for mine a greater sadness."

<sb/>
<lb/>Alichin held not in, but running counter
<lb/>Unto the rest, said to him: "If thou dive,
<lb/>I will not follow thee upon the gallop,

<sb/>
<lb/>But I will beat my wings above the pitch;
<lb/>The height be left, and be the bank a shield
<lb/>To see if thou alone dost countervail us."

<sb/>
<lb/>O thou who readest, thou shalt hear new sport!
<lb/>Each to the other side his eyes averted;
<lb/>He first, who most reluctant was to do it.

<sb/>
<lb/>The Navarrese selected well his time;
<lb/>Planted his feet on land, and in a moment
<lb/>Leaped, and released himself from their design.

<sb/>
<lb/>Whereat each one was suddenly stung with shame,
<lb/>But he most who was cause of the defeat;
<lb/>Therefore he moved, and cried: "Thou art o'ertakern."

<sb/>
<lb/>But little it availed, for wings could not
<lb/>Outstrip the fear; the other one went under,
<lb/>And, flying, upward he his breast directed;

<sb/>
<lb/>Not otherwise the duck upon a sudden
<lb/>Dives under, when the falcon is approaching,
<lb/>And upward he returneth cross and weary.

<sb/>
<lb/>Infuriate at the mockery, Calcabrina
<lb/>Flying behind him followed close, desirous
<lb/>The other should escape, to have a quarrel.

<sb/>
<lb/>And when the barrator had disappeared,
<lb/>He turned his talons upon his companion,
<lb/>And grappled with him right above the moat.

<sb/>
<lb/>But sooth the other was a doughty sparhawk
<lb/>To clapperclaw him well; and both of them
<lb/>Fell in the middle of the boiling pond.

<sb/>
<lb/>A sudden intercessor was the heat;
<lb/>But ne'ertheless of rising there was naught,
<lb/>To such degree they had their wings belimed.

<sb/>
<lb/>Lamenting with the others, Barbariccia
<lb/>Made four of them fly to the other side
<lb/>With all their gaffs, and very speedily

<sb/>
<lb/>This side and that they to their posts descended;
<lb/>They stretched their hooks towards the pitch-ensnared,
<lb/>Who were already baked within the crust,

<sb/>
<lb/>And in this manner busied did we leave them.

<canto numeral="XXIII"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>Silent, alone, and without company
<lb/>We went, the one in front, the other after,
<lb/>As go the Minor Friars along their way.

<sb/>
<lb/>Upon the fable of Aesop was directed
<lb/>My thought, by reason of the present quarrel,
<lb/>Where he has spoken of the frog and mouse;

<sb/>
<lb/>For 'mo' and 'issa' are not more alike
<lb/>Than this one is to that, if well we couple
<lb/>End and beginning with a steadfast mind.

<sb/>
<lb/>And even as one thought from another springs,
<lb/>So afterward from that was born another,
<lb/>Which the first fear within me double made.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus did I ponder: "These on our account
<lb/>Are laughed to scorn, with injury and scoff
<lb/>So great, that much I think it must annoy them.

<sb/>
<lb/>If anger be engrafted on ill-will,
<lb/>They will come after us more merciless
<lb/>Than dog upon the leveret which he seizes,"

<sb/>
<lb/>I felt my hair stand all on end already
<lb/>With terror, and stood backwardly intent,
<lb/>When said I: "Master, if thou hidest not

<sb/>
<lb/>Thyself and me forthwith, of Malebranche
<lb/>I am in dread; we have them now behind us;
<lb/>I so imagine them, I already feel them."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he: "If I were made of leaded glass,
<lb/>Thine outward image I should not attract
<lb/>Sooner to me than I imprint the inner.

<sb/>
<lb/>Just now thy thoughts came in among my own,
<lb/>With similar attitude and similar face,
<lb/>So that of both one counsel sole I made.

<sb/>
<lb/>If peradventure the right bank so slope
<lb/>That we to the next Bolgia can descend,
<lb/>We shall escape from the imagined chase."

<sb/>
<lb/>Not yet he finished rendering such opinion,
<lb/>When I beheld them come with outstretched wings,
<lb/>Not far remote, with will to seize upon us.

<sb/>
<lb/>My Leader on a sudden seized me up,
<lb/>Even as a mother who by noise is wakened,
<lb/>And close beside her sees the enkindled flames,

<sb/>
<lb/>Who takes her son, and flies, and does not stop,
<lb/>Having more care of him than of herself,
<lb/>So that she clothes her only with a shift;

<sb/>
<lb/>And downward from the top of the hard bank
<lb/>Supine he gave him to the pendent rock,
<lb/>That one side of the other Bolgia walls.

<sb/>
<lb/>Ne'er ran so swiftly water through a sluice
<lb/>To turn the wheel of any land-built mill,
<lb/>When nearest to the paddles it approaches,

<sb/>
<lb/>As did my Master down along that border,
<lb/>Bearing me with him on his breast away,
<lb/>As his own son, and not as a companion.

<sb/>
<lb/>Hardly the bed of the ravine below
<lb/>His feet had reached, ere they had reached the hill
<lb/>Right over us; but he was not afraid;

<sb/>
<lb/>For the high Providence, which had ordained
<lb/>To place them ministers of the fifth moat,
<lb/>The power of thence departing took from all.

</pouch_ring>

<pouch_ring number="6" sub_sin="hypocrite">

<sb/>
<lb/>A painted people there below we found,
<lb/>Who went about with footsteps very slow,
<lb/>Weeping and in their semblance tired and vanquished.

<sb/>
<lb/>They had on mantles with the hoods low down
<lb/>Before their eyes, and fashioned of the cut
<lb/>That in Cologne they for the monks are made.

<sb/>
<lb/>Without, they gilded are so that it dazzles;
<lb/>But inwardly all leaden and so heavy
<lb/>That Frederick used to put them on of straw.

<sb/>
<lb/>O everlastingly fatiguing mantle!
<lb/>Again we turned us, still to the left hand
<lb/>Along with them, intent on their sad plaint;

<sb/>
<lb/>But owing to the weight, that weary folk
<lb/>Came on so tardily, that we were new
<lb/>In company at each motion of the haunch.

<sb/>
<lb/>Whence I unto my Leader: "See thou find
<lb/>Some one who may by deed or name be known,
<lb/>And thus in going move thine eye about."

<sb/>
<lb/>And one, who understood the Tuscan speech,
<lb/>Cried to us from behind: "Stay ye your feet,
<lb/>Ye, who so run athwart the dusky air!

<sb/>
<lb/>Perhaps thou'lt have from me what thou demandest."
<lb/>Whereat the Leader turned him, and said: "Wait,
<lb/>And then according to his pace proceed."

<sb/>
<lb/>I stopped, and two beheld I show great haste
<lb/>Of spirit, in their faces, to be with me;
<lb/>But the burden and the narrow way delayed them.

<sb/>
<lb/>When they came up, long with an eye askance
<lb/>They scanned me without uttering a word.
<lb/>Then to each other turned, and said together:

<sb/>
<lb/>"He by the action of his throat seems living;
<lb/>And if they dead are, by what privilege
<lb/>Go they uncovered by the heavy stole?"

<sb/>
<lb/>Then said to me: "Tuscan, who to the college
<lb/>Of miserable hypocrites art come,
<lb/>Do not disdain to tell us who thou art."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I to them: "Born was I, and grew up
<lb/>In the great town on the fair river of Arno,
<lb/>And with the body am I've always had.

<sb/>
<lb/>But who are ye, in whom there trickles down
<lb/>Along your cheeks such grief as I behold?
<lb/>And what pain is upon you, that so sparkles?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And one replied to me: "These orange cloaks
<lb/>Are made of lead so heavy, that the weights
<lb/>Cause in this way their balances to creak.

<sb/>
<lb/>Frati Gaudenti were we, and Bolognese;
<lb/>I Catalano, and he Loderingo
<lb/>Named, and together taken by thy city,

<sb/>
<lb/>As the wont is to take one man alone,
<lb/>For maintenance of its peace; and we were such
<lb/>That still it is apparent round Gardingo."

<sb/>
<lb/>"O Friars," began I, "your iniquitous. . ."
<lb/>But said no more; for to mine eyes there rushed
<lb/>One crucified with three stakes on the ground.

<sb/>
<lb/>When me he saw, he writhed himself all over,
<lb/>Blowing into his beard with suspirations;
<lb/>And the Friar Catalan, who noticed this,

<sb/>
<lb/>Said to me: "This transfixed one, whom thou seest,
<lb/>Counselled the Pharisees that it was meet
<lb/>To put one man to torture for the people.

<sb/>
<lb/>Crosswise and naked is he on the path,
<lb/>As thou perceivest; and he needs must feel,
<lb/>Whoever passes, first how much he weighs;

<sb/>
<lb/>And in like mode his father-in-law is punished
<lb/>Within this moat, and the others of the council,
<lb/>Which for the Jews was a malignant seed."

<sb/>
<lb/>And thereupon I saw Virgilius marvel
<lb/>O'er him who was extended on the cross
<lb/>So vilely in eternal banishment.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then he directed to the Friar this voice:
<lb/>"Be not displeased, if granted thee, to tell us
<lb/>If to the right hand any pass slope down

<sb/>
<lb/>By which we two may issue forth from here,
<lb/>Without constraining some of the black angels
<lb/>To come and extricate us from this deep."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then he made answer: "Nearer than thou hopest
<lb/>There is a rock, that forth from the great circle
<lb/>Proceeds, and crosses all the cruel valleys,

<sb/>
<lb/>Save that at this 'tis broken, and does not bridge it;
<lb/>You will be able to mount up the ruin,
<lb/>That sidelong slopes and at the bottom rises."

<sb/>
<lb/>The Leader stood awhile with head bowed down;
<lb/>Then said: "The business badly he recounted
<lb/>Who grapples with his hook the sinners yonder."

<sb/>
<lb/>And the Friar: "Many of the Devil's vices
<lb/>Once heard I at Bologna, and among them,
<lb/>That he's a liar and the father of lies."

<sb/>
<lb/>Thereat my Leader with great strides went on,
<lb/>Somewhat disturbed with anger in his looks;
<lb/>Whence from the heavy-laden I departed

<sb/>
<lb/>After the prints of his beloved feet.
    
</pouch_ring>

<canto numeral="XXIV"/>
    
<pouch_ring number="7" sub_sin="thief">

<sb/>
<lb/>In that part of the youthful year wherein
<lb/>The Sun his locks beneath Aquarius tempers,
<lb/>And now the nights draw near to half the day,

<sb/>
<lb/>What time the hoar-frost copies on the ground
<lb/>The outward semblance of her sister white,
<lb/>But little lasts the temper of her pen,

<sb/>
<lb/>The husbandman, whose forage faileth him,
<lb/>Rises, and looks, and seeth the champaign
<lb/>All gleaming white, whereat he beats his flank,

<sb/>
<lb/>Returns in doors, and up and down laments,
<lb/>Like a poor wretch, who knows not what to do;
<lb/>Then he returns and hope revives again,

<sb/>
<lb/>Seeing the world has changed its countenance
<lb/>In little time, and takes his shepherd's crook,
<lb/>And forth the little lambs to pasture drives.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus did the Master fill me with alarm,
<lb/>When I beheld his forehead so disturbed,
<lb/>And to the ailment came as soon the plaster.

<sb/>
<lb/>For as we came unto the ruined bridge,
<lb/>The Leader turned to me with that sweet look
<lb/>Which at the mountain's foot I first beheld.

<sb/>
<lb/>His arms he opened, after some advisement
<lb/>Within himself elected, looking first
<lb/>Well at the ruin, and laid hold of me.

<sb/>
<lb/>And even as he who acts and meditates,
<lb/>For aye it seems that he provides beforehand,
<lb/>So upward lifting me towards the summit

<sb/>
<lb/>Of a huge rock, he scanned another crag,
<lb/>Saying: "To that one grapple afterwards,
<lb/>But try first if 'tis such that it will hold thee."

<sb/>
<lb/>This was no way for one clothed with a cloak;
<lb/>For hardly we, he light, and I pushed upward,
<lb/>Were able to ascend from jag to jag.

<sb/>
<lb/>And had it not been, that upon that precinct
<lb/>Shorter was the ascent than on the other,
<lb/>He I know not, but I had been dead beat.

<sb/>
<lb/>But because Malebolge tow'rds the mouth
<lb/>Of the profoundest well is all inclining,
<lb/>The structure of each valley doth import

<sb/>
<lb/>That one bank rises and the other sinks.
<lb/>Still we arrived at length upon the point
<lb/>Wherefrom the last stone breaks itself asunder.

<sb/>
<lb/>The breath was from my lungs so milked away,
<lb/>When I was up, that I could go no farther,
<lb/>Nay, I sat down upon my first arrival.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Now it behoves thee thus to put off sloth,"
<lb/>My Master said; "for sitting upon down,
<lb/>Or under quilt, one cometh not to fame,

<sb/>
<lb/>Withouten which whoso his life consumes
<lb/>Such vestige leaveth of himself on earth,
<lb/>As smoke in air or in the water foam.

<sb/>
<lb/>And therefore raise thee up, o'ercome the anguish
<lb/>With spirit that o'ercometh every battle,
<lb/>If with its heavy body it sink not.

<sb/>
<lb/>A longer stairway it behoves thee mount;
<lb/>'Tis not enough from these to have departed;
<lb/>Let it avail thee, if thou understand me."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then I uprose, showing myself provided
<lb/>Better with breath than I did feel myself,
<lb/>And said: "Go on, for I am strong and bold."

<sb/>
<lb/>Upward we took our way along the crag,
<lb/>Which jagged was, and narrow, and difficult,
<lb/>And more precipitous far than that before.

<sb/>
<lb/>Speaking I went, not to appear exhausted;
<lb/>Whereat a voice from the next moat came forth,
<lb/>Not well adapted to articulate words.

<sb/>
<lb/>I know not what it said, though o'er the back
<lb/>I now was of the arch that passes there;
<lb/>But he seemed moved to anger who was speaking.

<sb/>
<lb/>I was bent downward, but my living eyes
<lb/>Could not attain the bottom, for the dark;
<lb/>Wherefore I: "Master, see that thou arrive

<sb/>
<lb/>At the next round, and let us descend the wall;
<lb/>For as from hence I hear and understand not,
<lb/>So I look down and nothing I distinguish."

<sb/>
<lb/>"Other response," he said, "I make thee not,
<lb/>Except the doing; for the modest asking
<lb/>Ought to be followed by the deed in silence."

<sb/>
<lb/>We from the bridge descended at its head,
<lb/>Where it connects itself with the eighth bank,
<lb/>And then was manifest to me the Bolgia;

<sb/>
<lb/>And I beheld therein a terrible throng
<lb/>Of serpents, and of such a monstrous kind,
<lb/>That the remembrance still congeals my blood

<sb/>
<lb/>Let Libya boast no longer with her sand;
<lb/>For if Chelydri, Jaculi, and Phareae
<lb/>She breeds, with Cenchri and with Amphisbaena,

<sb/>
<lb/>Neither so many plagues nor so malignant
<lb/>E'er showed she with all Ethiopia,
<lb/>Nor with whatever on the Red Sea is!

<sb/>
<lb/>Among this cruel and most dismal throng
<lb/>People were running naked and affrighted.
<lb/>Without the hope of hole or heliotrope.

<sb/>
<lb/>They had their hands with serpents bound behind them;
<lb/>These riveted upon their reins the tail
<lb/>And head, and were in front of them entwined.

<sb/>
<lb/>And lo! at one who was upon our side
<lb/>There darted forth a serpent, which transfixed him
<lb/>There where the neck is knotted to the shoulders.

<sb/>
<lb/>Nor 'O' so quickly e'er, nor 'I' was written,
<lb/>As he took fire, and burned; and ashes wholly
<lb/>Behoved it that in falling he became.

<sb/>
<lb/>And when he on the ground was thus destroyed,
<lb/>The ashes drew together, and of themselves
<lb/>Into himself they instantly returned.

<sb/>
<lb/>Even thus by the great sages 'tis confessed
<lb/>The phoenix dies, and then is born again,
<lb/>When it approaches its five-hundredth year;

<sb/>
<lb/>On herb or grain it feeds not in its life,
<lb/>But only on tears of incense and amomum,
<lb/>And nard and myrrh are its last winding-sheet.

<sb/>
<lb/>And as he is who falls, and knows not how,
<lb/>By force of demons who to earth down drag him,
<lb/>Or other oppilation that binds man,

<sb/>
<lb/>When he arises and around him looks,
<lb/>Wholly bewildered by the mighty anguish
<lb/>Which he has suffered, and in looking sighs;

<sb/>
<lb/>Such was that sinner after he had risen.
<lb/>Justice of God! O how severe it is,
<lb/>That blows like these in vengeance poureth down!

<sb/>
<lb/>The Guide thereafter asked him who he was;
<lb/>Whence he replied: "I rained from Tuscany
<lb/>A short time since into this cruel gorge.

<sb/>
<lb/>A bestial life, and not a human, pleased me,
<lb/>Even as the mule I was; I'm Vanni Fucci,
<lb/>Beast, and Pistoia was my worthy den."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I unto the Guide: "Tell him to stir not,
<lb/>And ask what crime has thrust him here below,
<lb/>For once a man of blood and wrath I saw him."

<sb/>
<lb/>And the sinner, who had heard, dissembled not,
<lb/>But unto me directed mind and face,
<lb/>And with a melancholy shame was painted.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then said: "It pains me more that thou hast caught me
<lb/>Amid this misery where thou seest me,
<lb/>Than when I from the other life was taken.

<sb/>
<lb/>What thou demandest I cannot deny;
<lb/>So low am I put down because I robbed
<lb/>The sacristy of the fair ornaments,

<sb/>
<lb/>And falsely once 'twas laid upon another;
<lb/>But that thou mayst not such a sight enjoy,
<lb/>If thou shalt e'er be out of the dark places,

<sb/>
<lb/>Thine ears to my announcement ope and hear:
<lb/>Pistoia first of Neri groweth meagre;
<lb/>Then Florence doth renew her men and manners;

<sb/>
<lb/>Mars draws a vapour up from Val di Magra,
<lb/>Which is with turbid clouds enveloped round,
<lb/>And with impetuous and bitter tempest

<sb/>
<lb/>Over Campo Picen shall be the battle;
<lb/>When it shall suddenly rend the mist asunder,
<lb/>So that each Bianco shall thereby be smitten.

<sb/>
<lb/>And this I've said that it may give thee pain."

<canto numeral="XXV"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>At the conclusion of his words, the thief
<lb/>Lifted his hands aloft with both the figs,
<lb/>Crying: "Take that, God, for at thee I aim them."

<sb/>
<lb/>From that time forth the serpents were my friends;
<lb/>For one entwined itself about his neck
<lb/>As if it said: "I will not thou speak more;"

<sb/>
<lb/>And round his arms another, and rebound him,
<lb/>Clinching itself together so in front,
<lb/>That with them he could not a motion make.

<sb/>
<lb/>Pistoia, ah, Pistoia! why resolve not
<lb/>To burn thyself to ashes and so perish,
<lb/>Since in ill-doing thou thy seed excellest?

<sb/>
<lb/>Through all the sombre circles of this Hell,
<lb/>Spirit I saw not against God so proud,
<lb/>Not he who fell at Thebes down from the walls!

<sb/>
<lb/>He fled away, and spake no further word;
<lb/>And I beheld a Centaur full of rage
<lb/>Come crying out: "Where is, where is the scoffer?"

<sb/>
<lb/>I do not think Maremma has so many
<lb/>Serpents as he had all along his back,
<lb/>As far as where our countenance begins.

<sb/>
<lb/>Upon the shoulders, just behind the nape,
<lb/>With wings wide open was a dragon lying,
<lb/>And he sets fire to all that he encounters.

<sb/>
<lb/>My Master said: "That one is Cacus, who
<lb/>Beneath the rock upon Mount Aventine
<lb/>Created oftentimes a lake of blood.

<sb/>
<lb/>He goes not on the same road with his brothers,
<lb/>By reason of the fraudulent theft he made
<lb/>Of the great herd, which he had near to him;

<sb/>
<lb/>Whereat his tortuous actions ceased beneath
<lb/>The mace of Hercules, who peradventure
<lb/>Gave him a hundred, and he felt not ten."

<sb/>
<lb/>While he was speaking thus, he had passed by,
<lb/>And spirits three had underneath us come,
<lb/>Of which nor I aware was, nor my Leader,

<sb/>
<lb/>Until what time they shouted: "Who are you?"
<lb/>On which account our story made a halt,
<lb/>And then we were intent on them alone.

<sb/>
<lb/>I did not know them; but it came to pass,
<lb/>As it is wont to happen by some chance,
<lb/>That one to name the other was compelled,

<sb/>
<lb/>Exclaiming: "Where can Cianfa have remained?"
<lb/>Whence I, so that the Leader might attend,
<lb/>Upward from chin to nose my finger laid.

<sb/>
<lb/>If thou art, Reader, slow now to believe
<lb/>What I shall say, it will no marvel be,
<lb/>For I who saw it hardly can admit it.

<sb/>
<lb/>As I was holding raised on them my brows,
<lb/>Behold! a serpent with six feet darts forth
<lb/>In front of one, and fastens wholly on him.

<sb/>
<lb/>With middle feet it bound him round the paunch,
<lb/>And with the forward ones his arms it seized;
<lb/>Then thrust its teeth through one cheek and the other;

<sb/>
<lb/>The hindermost it stretched upon his thighs,
<lb/>And put its tail through in between the two,
<lb/>And up behind along the reins outspread it.

<sb/>
<lb/>Ivy was never fastened by its barbs
<lb/>Unto a tree so, as this horrible reptile
<lb/>Upon the other's limbs entwined its own.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then they stuck close, as if of heated wax
<lb/>They had been made, and intermixed their colour;
<lb/>Nor one nor other seemed now what he was;

<sb/>
<lb/>E'en as proceedeth on before the flame
<lb/>Upward along the paper a brown colour,
<lb/>Which is not black as yet, and the white dies.

<sb/>
<lb/>The other two looked on, and each of them
<lb/>Cried out: "O me, Agnello, how thou changest!
<lb/>Behold, thou now art neither two nor one."

<sb/>
<lb/>Already the two heads had one become,
<lb/>When there appeared to us two figures mingled
<lb/>Into one face, wherein the two were lost.

<sb/>
<lb/>Of the four lists were fashioned the two arms,
<lb/>The thighs and legs, the belly and the chest
<lb/>Members became that never yet were seen.

<sb/>
<lb/>Every original aspect there was cancelled;
<lb/>Two and yet none did the perverted image
<lb/>Appear, and such departed with slow pace.

<sb/>
<lb/>Even as a lizard, under the great scourge
<lb/>Of days canicular, exchanging hedge,
<lb/>Lightning appeareth if the road it cross;

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus did appear, coming towards the bellies
<lb/>Of the two others, a small fiery serpent,
<lb/>Livid and black as is a peppercorn.

<sb/>
<lb/>And in that part whereat is first received
<lb/>Our aliment, it one of them transfixed;
<lb/>Then downward fell in front of him extended.

<sb/>
<lb/>The one transfixed looked at it, but said naught;
<lb/>Nay, rather with feet motionless he yawned,
<lb/>Just as if sleep or fever had assailed him.

<sb/>
<lb/>He at the serpent gazed, and it at him;
<lb/>One through the wound, the other through the mouth
<lb/>Smoked violently, and the smoke commingled.

<sb/>
<lb/>Henceforth be silent Lucan, where he mentions
<lb/>Wretched Sabellus and Nassidius,
<lb/>And wait to hear what now shall be shot forth.

<sb/>
<lb/>Be silent Ovid, of Cadmus and Arethusa;
<lb/>For if him to a snake, her to fountain,
<lb/>Converts he fabling, that I grudge him not;

<sb/>
<lb/>Because two natures never front to front
<lb/>Has he transmuted, so that both the forms
<lb/>To interchange their matter ready were.

<sb/>
<lb/>Together they responded in such wise,
<lb/>That to a fork the serpent cleft his tail,
<lb/>And eke the wounded drew his feet together.

<sb/>
<lb/>The legs together with the thighs themselves
<lb/>Adhered so, that in little time the juncture
<lb/>No sign whatever made that was apparent.

<sb/>
<lb/>He with the cloven tail assumed the figure
<lb/>The other one was losing, and his skin
<lb/>Became elastic, and the other's hard.

<sb/>
<lb/>I saw the arms draw inward at the armpits,
<lb/>And both feet of the reptile, that were short,
<lb/>Lengthen as much as those contracted were.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thereafter the hind feet, together twisted,
<lb/>Became the member that a man conceals,
<lb/>And of his own the wretch had two created.

<sb/>
<lb/>While both of them the exhalation veils
<lb/>With a new colour, and engenders hair
<lb/>On one of them and depilates the other,

<sb/>
<lb/>The one uprose and down the other fell,
<lb/>Though turning not away their impious lamps,
<lb/>Underneath which each one his muzzle changed.

<sb/>
<lb/>He who was standing drew it tow'rds the temples,
<lb/>And from excess of matter, which came thither,
<lb/>Issued the ears from out the hollow cheeks;

<sb/>
<lb/>What did not backward run and was retained
<lb/>Of that excess made to the face a nose,
<lb/>And the lips thickened far as was befitting.

<sb/>
<lb/>He who lay prostrate thrusts his muzzle forward,
<lb/>And backward draws the ears into his head,
<lb/>In the same manner as the snail its horns;

<sb/>
<lb/>And so the tongue, which was entire and apt
<lb/>For speech before, is cleft, and the bi-forked
<lb/>In the other closes up, and the smoke ceases.

<sb/>
<lb/>The soul, which to a reptile had been changed,
<lb/>Along the valley hissing takes to flight,
<lb/>And after him the other speaking sputters.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then did he turn upon him his new shoulders,
<lb/>And said to the other: "I'll have Buoso run,
<lb/>Crawling as I have done, along this road."

<sb/>
<lb/>In this way I beheld the seventh ballast
<lb/>Shift and reshift, and here be my excuse
<lb/>The novelty, if aught my pen transgress.

<sb/>
<lb/>And notwithstanding that mine eyes might be
<lb/>Somewhat bewildered, and my mind dismayed,
<lb/>They could not flee away so secretly

<sb/>
<lb/>But that I plainly saw Puccio Sciancato;
<lb/>And he it was who sole of three companions,
<lb/>Which came in the beginning, was not changed;

<sb/>
<lb/>The other was he whom thou, Gaville, weepest.
    
</pouch_ring>

<canto numeral="XXVI"/>
    
<pouch_ring number="8" sub_sin="fraudulent_counselor">

<sb/>
<lb/>Rejoice, O Florence, since thou art so great,
<lb/>That over sea and land thou beatest thy wings,
<lb/>And throughout Hell thy name is spread abroad!

<sb/>
<lb/>Among the thieves five citizens of thine
<lb/>Like these I found, whence shame comes unto me,
<lb/>And thou thereby to no great honour risest.

<sb/>
<lb/>But if when morn is near our dreams are true,
<lb/>Feel shalt thou in a little time from now
<lb/>What Prato, if none other, craves for thee.

<sb/>
<lb/>And if it now were, it were not too soon;
<lb/>Would that it were, seeing it needs must be,
<lb/>For 'twill aggrieve me more the more I age.

<sb/>
<lb/>We went our way, and up along the stairs
<lb/>The bourns had made us to descend before,
<lb/>Remounted my Conductor and drew me.

<sb/>
<lb/>And following the solitary path
<lb/>Among the rocks and ridges of the crag,
<lb/>The foot without the hand sped not at all.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then sorrowed I, and sorrow now again,
<lb/>When I direct my mind to what I saw,
<lb/>And more my genius curb than I am wont,

<sb/>
<lb/>That it may run not unless virtue guide it;
<lb/>So that if some good star, or better thing,
<lb/>Have given me good, I may myself not grudge it.

<sb/>
<lb/>As many as the hind (who on the hill
<lb/>Rests at the time when he who lights the world
<lb/>His countenance keeps least concealed from us,

<sb/>
<lb/>While as the fly gives place unto the gnat)
<lb/>Seeth the glow-worms down along the valley,
<lb/>Perchance there where he ploughs and makes his vintage;

<sb/>
<lb/>With flames as manifold resplendent all
<lb/>Was the eighth Bolgia, as I grew aware
<lb/>As soon as I was where the depth appeared.

<sb/>
<lb/>And such as he who with the bears avenged him
<lb/>Beheld Elijah's chariot at departing,
<lb/>What time the steeds to heaven erect uprose,

<sb/>
<lb/>For with his eye he could not follow it
<lb/>So as to see aught else than flame alone,
<lb/>Even as a little cloud ascending upward,

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus each along the gorge of the intrenchment
<lb/>Was moving; for not one reveals the theft,
<lb/>And every flame a sinner steals away.

<sb/>
<lb/>I stood upon the bridge uprisen to see,
<lb/>So that, if I had seized not on a rock,
<lb/>Down had I fallen without being pushed.

<sb/>
<lb/>And the Leader, who beheld me so attent,
<lb/>Exclaimed: "Within the fires the spirits are;
<lb/>Each swathes himself with that wherewith he burns."

<sb/>
<lb/>"My Master," I replied, "by hearing thee
<lb/>I am more sure; but I surmised already
<lb/>It might be so, and already wished to ask thee

<sb/>
<lb/>Who is within that fire, which comes so cleft
<lb/>At top, it seems uprising from the pyre
<lb/>Where was Eteocles with his brother placed."

<sb/>
<lb/>He answered me: "Within there are tormented
<lb/>Ulysses and Diomed, and thus together
<lb/>They unto vengeance run as unto wrath.

<sb/>
<lb/>And there within their flame do they lament
<lb/>The ambush of the horse, which made the door
<lb/>Whence issued forth the Romans' gentle seed;

<sb/>
<lb/>Therein is wept the craft, for which being dead
<lb/>Deidamia still deplores Achilles,
<lb/>And pain for the Palladium there is borne."

<sb/>
<lb/>"If they within those sparks possess the power
<lb/>To speak," I said, "thee, Master, much I pray,
<lb/>And re-pray, that the prayer be worth a thousand,

<sb/>
<lb/>That thou make no denial of awaiting
<lb/>Until the horned flame shall hither come;
<lb/>Thou seest that with desire I lean towards it."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "Worthy is thy entreaty
<lb/>Of much applause, and therefore I accept it;
<lb/>But take heed that thy tongue restrain itself.

<sb/>
<lb/>Leave me to speak, because I have conceived
<lb/>That which thou wishest; for they might disdain
<lb/>Perchance, since they were Greeks, discourse of thine."

<sb/>
<lb/>When now the flame had come unto that point,
<lb/>Where to my Leader it seemed time and place,
<lb/>After this fashion did I hear him speak:

<sb/>
<lb/>"O ye, who are twofold within one fire,
<lb/>If I deserved of you, while I was living,
<lb/>If I deserved of you or much or little

<sb/>
<lb/>When in the world I wrote the lofty verses,
<lb/>Do not move on, but one of you declare
<lb/>Whither, being lost, he went away to die."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then of the antique flame the greater horn,
<lb/>Murmuring, began to wave itself about
<lb/>Even as a flame doth which the wind fatigues.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thereafterward, the summit to and fro
<lb/>Moving as if it were the tongue that spake,
<lb/>It uttered forth a voice, and said: "When I

<sb/>
<lb/>From Circe had departed, who concealed me
<lb/>More than a year there near unto Gaeta,
<lb/>Or ever yet Aeneas named it so,

<sb/>
<lb/>Nor fondness for my son, nor reverence
<lb/>For my old father, nor the due affection
<lb/>Which joyous should have made Penelope,

<sb/>
<lb/>Could overcome within me the desire
<lb/>I had to be experienced of the world,
<lb/>And of the vice and virtue of mankind;

<sb/>
<lb/>But I put forth on the high open sea
<lb/>With one sole ship, and that small company
<lb/>By which I never had deserted been.

<sb/>
<lb/>Both of the shores I saw as far as Spain,
<lb/>Far as Morocco, and the isle of Sardes,
<lb/>And the others which that sea bathes round about.

<sb/>
<lb/>I and my company were old and slow
<lb/>When at that narrow passage we arrived
<lb/>Where Hercules his landmarks set as signals,

<sb/>
<lb/>That man no farther onward should adventure.
<lb/>On the right hand behind me left I Seville,
<lb/>And on the other already had left Ceuta.

<sb/>
<lb/>'O brothers, who amid a hundred thousand
<lb/>Perils,' I said, 'have come unto the West,
<lb/>To this so inconsiderable vigil

<sb/>
<lb/>Which is remaining of your senses still
<lb/>Be ye unwilling to deny the knowledge,
<lb/>Following the sun, of the unpeopled world.

<sb/>
<lb/>Consider ye the seed from which ye sprang;
<lb/>Ye were not made to live like unto brutes,
<lb/>But for pursuit of virtue and of knowledge.'

<sb/>
<lb/>So eager did I render my companions,
<lb/>With this brief exhortation, for the voyage,
<lb/>That then I hardly could have held them back.

<sb/>
<lb/>And having turned our stern unto the morning,
<lb/>We of the oars made wings for our mad flight,
<lb/>Evermore gaining on the larboard side.

<sb/>
<lb/>Already all the stars of the other pole
<lb/>The night beheld, and ours so very low
<lb/>It did not rise above the ocean floor.

<sb/>
<lb/>Five times rekindled and as many quenched
<lb/>Had been the splendour underneath the moon,
<lb/>Since we had entered into the deep pass,

<sb/>
<lb/>When there appeared to us a mountain, dim
<lb/>From distance, and it seemed to me so high
<lb/>As I had never any one beheld.

<sb/>
<lb/>Joyful were we, and soon it turned to weeping;
<lb/>For out of the new land a whirlwind rose,
<lb/>And smote upon the fore part of the ship.

<sb/>
<lb/>Three times it made her whirl with all the waters,
<lb/>At the fourth time it made the stern uplift,
<lb/>And the prow downward go, as pleased Another,

<sb/>
<lb/>Until the sea above us closed again."

<canto numeral="XXVII"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>Already was the flame erect and quiet,
<lb/>To speak no more, and now departed from us
<lb/>With the permission of the gentle Poet;

<sb/>
<lb/>When yet another, which behind it came,
<lb/>Caused us to turn our eyes upon its top
<lb/>By a confused sound that issued from it.

<sb/>
<lb/>As the Sicilian bull (that bellowed first
<lb/>With the lament of him, and that was right,
<lb/>Who with his file had modulated it)

<sb/>
<lb/>Bellowed so with the voice of the afflicted,
<lb/>That, notwithstanding it was made of brass,
<lb/>Still it appeared with agony transfixed;

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus, by not having any way or issue
<lb/>At first from out the fire, to its own language
<lb/>Converted were the melancholy words.

<sb/>
<lb/>But afterwards, when they had gathered way
<lb/>Up through the point, giving it that vibration
<lb/>The tongue had given them in their passage out,

<sb/>
<lb/>We heard it said: "O thou, at whom I aim
<lb/>My voice, and who but now wast speaking Lombard,
<lb/>Saying, 'Now go thy way, no more I urge thee,'

<sb/>
<lb/>Because I come perchance a little late,
<lb/>To stay and speak with me let it not irk thee;
<lb/>Thou seest it irks not me, and I am burning.

<sb/>
<lb/>If thou but lately into this blind world
<lb/>Hast fallen down from that sweet Latian land,
<lb/>Wherefrom I bring the whole of my transgression,

<sb/>
<lb/>Say, if the Romagnuols have peace or war,
<lb/>For I was from the mountains there between
<lb/>Urbino and the yoke whence Tiber bursts."

<sb/>
<lb/>I still was downward bent and listening,
<lb/>When my Conductor touched me on the side,
<lb/>Saying: "Speak thou: this one a Latian is."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I, who had beforehand my reply
<lb/>In readiness, forthwith began to speak:
<lb/>"O soul, that down below there art concealed,

<sb/>
<lb/>Romagna thine is not and never has been
<lb/>Without war in the bosom of its tyrants;
<lb/>But open war I none have left there now.

<sb/>
<lb/>Ravenna stands as it long years has stood;
<lb/>The Eagle of Polenta there is brooding,
<lb/>So that she covers Cervia with her vans.

<sb/>
<lb/>The city which once made the long resistance,
<lb/>And of the French a sanguinary heap,
<lb/>Beneath the Green Paws finds itself again;

<sb/>
<lb/>Verrucchio's ancient Mastiff and the new,
<lb/>Who made such bad disposal of Montagna,
<lb/>Where they are wont make wimbles of their teeth.

<sb/>
<lb/>The cities of Lamone and Santerno
<lb/>Governs the Lioncel of the white lair,
<lb/>Who changes sides 'twixt summer-time and winter;

<sb/>
<lb/>And that of which the Savio bathes the flank,
<lb/>Even as it lies between the plain and mountain,
<lb/>Lives between tyranny and a free state.

<sb/>
<lb/>Now I entreat thee tell us who thou art;
<lb/>Be not more stubborn than the rest have been,
<lb/>So may thy name hold front there in the world."

<sb/>
<lb/>After the fire a little more had roared
<lb/>In its own fashion, the sharp point it moved
<lb/>This way and that, and then gave forth such breath:

<sb/>
<lb/>"If I believed that my reply were made
<lb/>To one who to the world would e'er return,
<lb/>This flame without more flickering would stand still;

<sb/>
<lb/>But inasmuch as never from this depth
<lb/>Did any one return, if I hear true,
<lb/>Without the fear of infamy I answer,

<sb/>
<lb/>I was a man of arms, then Cordelier,
<lb/>Believing thus begirt to make amends;
<lb/>And truly my belief had been fulfilled

<sb/>
<lb/>But for the High Priest, whom may ill betide,
<lb/>Who put me back into my former sins;
<lb/>And how and wherefore I will have thee hear.

<sb/>
<lb/>While I was still the form of bone and pulp
<lb/>My mother gave to me, the deeds I did
<lb/>Were not those of a lion, but a fox.

<sb/>
<lb/>The machinations and the covert ways
<lb/>I knew them all, and practised so their craft,
<lb/>That to the ends of earth the sound went forth.

<sb/>
<lb/>When now unto that portion of mine age
<lb/>I saw myself arrived, when each one ought
<lb/>To lower the sails, and coil away the ropes,

<sb/>
<lb/>That which before had pleased me then displeased me;
<lb/>And penitent and confessing I surrendered,
<lb/>Ah woe is me! and it would have bestead me;

<sb/>
<lb/>The Leader of the modern Pharisees
<lb/>Having a war near unto Lateran,
<lb/>And not with Saracens nor with the Jews,

<sb/>
<lb/>For each one of his enemies was Christian,
<lb/>And none of them had been to conquer Acre,
<lb/>Nor merchandising in the Sultan's land,

<sb/>
<lb/>Nor the high office, nor the sacred orders,
<lb/>In him regarded, nor in me that cord
<lb/>Which used to make those girt with it more meagre;

<sb/>
<lb/>But even as Constantine sought out Sylvester
<lb/>To cure his leprosy, within Soracte,
<lb/>So this one sought me out as an adept

<sb/>
<lb/>To cure him of the fever of his pride.
<lb/>Counsel he asked of me, and I was silent,
<lb/>Because his words appeared inebriate.

<sb/>
<lb/>And then he said: 'Be not thy heart afraid;
<lb/>Henceforth I thee absolve; and thou instruct me
<lb/>How to raze Palestrina to the ground.

<sb/>
<lb/>Heaven have I power to lock and to unlock,
<lb/>As thou dost know; therefore the keys are two,
<lb/>The which my predecessor held not dear.'

<sb/>
<lb/>Then urged me on his weighty arguments
<lb/>There, where my silence was the worst advice;
<lb/>And said I: 'Father, since thou washest me

<sb/>
<lb/>Of that sin into which I now must fall,
<lb/>The promise long with the fulfilment short
<lb/>Will make thee triumph in thy lofty seat.'

<sb/>
<lb/>Francis came afterward, when I was dead,
<lb/>For me; but one of the black Cherubim
<lb/>Said to him: 'Take him not; do me no wrong;

<sb/>
<lb/>He must come down among my servitors,
<lb/>Because he gave the fraudulent advice
<lb/>From which time forth I have been at his hair;

<sb/>
<lb/>For who repents not cannot be absolved,
<lb/>Nor can one both repent and will at once,
<lb/>Because of the contradiction which consents not.'

<sb/>
<lb/>O miserable me! how I did shudder
<lb/>When he seized on me, saying: 'Peradventure
<lb/>Thou didst not think that I was a logician!'

<sb/>
<lb/>He bore me unto Minos, who entwined
<lb/>Eight times his tail about his stubborn back,
<lb/>And after he had bitten it in great rage,

<sb/>
<lb/>Said: 'Of the thievish fire a culprit this;'
<lb/>Wherefore, here where thou seest, am I lost,
<lb/>And vested thus in going I bemoan me."

<sb/>
<lb/>When it had thus completed its recital,
<lb/>The flame departed uttering lamentations,
<lb/>Writhing and flapping its sharp-pointed horn.

<sb/>
<lb/>Onward we passed, both I and my Conductor,
<lb/>Up o'er the crag above another arch,
<lb/>Which the moat covers, where is paid the fee

<sb/>
<lb/>By those who, sowing discord, win their burden.
    
</pouch_ring>

<canto numeral="XXVIII"/>
    
<pouch_ring number="9" sub_sin="sower_of_discord">

<sb/>
<lb/>Who ever could, e'en with untrammelled words,
<lb/>Tell of the blood and of the wounds in full
<lb/>Which now I saw, by many times narrating?

<sb/>
<lb/>Each tongue would for a certainty fall short
<lb/>By reason of our speech and memory,
<lb/>That have small room to comprehend so much.

<sb/>
<lb/>If were again assembled all the people
<lb/>Which formerly upon the fateful land
<lb/>Of Puglia were lamenting for their blood

<sb/>
<lb/>Shed by the Romans and the lingering war
<lb/>That of the rings made such illustrious spoils,
<lb/>As Livy has recorded, who errs not,

<sb/>
<lb/>With those who felt the agony of blows
<lb/>By making counterstand to Robert Guiscard,
<lb/>And all the rest, whose bones are gathered still

<sb/>
<lb/>At Ceperano, where a renegade
<lb/>Was each Apulian, and at Tagliacozzo,
<lb/>Where without arms the old Alardo conquered,

<sb/>
<lb/>And one his limb transpierced, and one lopped off,
<lb/>Should show, it would be nothing to compare
<lb/>With the disgusting mode of the ninth Bolgia.

<sb/>
<lb/>A cask by losing centre-piece or cant
<lb/>Was never shattered so, as I saw one
<lb/>Rent from the chin to where one breaketh wind.

<sb/>
<lb/>Between his legs were hanging down his entrails;
<lb/>His heart was visible, and the dismal sack
<lb/>That maketh excrement of what is eaten.

<sb/>
<lb/>While I was all absorbed in seeing him,
<lb/>He looked at me, and opened with his hands
<lb/>His bosom, saying: "See now how I rend me;

<sb/>
<lb/>How mutilated, see, is Mahomet;
<lb/>In front of me doth Ali weeping go,
<lb/>Cleft in the face from forelock unto chin;

<sb/>
<lb/>And all the others whom thou here beholdest,
<lb/>Disseminators of scandal and of schism
<lb/>While living were, and therefore are cleft thus.

<sb/>
<lb/>A devil is behind here, who doth cleave us
<lb/>Thus cruelly, unto the falchion's edge
<lb/>Putting again each one of all this ream,

<sb/>
<lb/>When we have gone around the doleful road;
<lb/>By reason that our wounds are closed again
<lb/>Ere any one in front of him repass.

<sb/>
<lb/>But who art thou, that musest on the crag,
<lb/>Perchance to postpone going to the pain
<lb/>That is adjudged upon thine accusations?"

<sb/>
<lb/>"Nor death hath reached him yet, nor guilt doth bring him,"
<lb/>My Master made reply, "to be tormented;
<lb/>But to procure him full experience,

<sb/>
<lb/>Me, who am dead, behoves it to conduct him
<lb/>Down here through Hell, from circle unto circle;
<lb/>And this is true as that I speak to thee."

<sb/>
<lb/>More than a hundred were there when they heard him,
<lb/>Who in the moat stood still to look at me,
<lb/>Through wonderment oblivious of their torture.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Now say to Fra Dolcino, then, to arm him,
<lb/>Thou, who perhaps wilt shortly see the sun,
<lb/>If soon he wish not here to follow me,

<sb/>
<lb/>So with provisions, that no stress of snow
<lb/>May give the victory to the Novarese,
<lb/>Which otherwise to gain would not be easy."

<sb/>
<lb/>After one foot to go away he lifted,
<lb/>This word did Mahomet say unto me,
<lb/>Then to depart upon the ground he stretched it.

<sb/>
<lb/>Another one, who had his throat pierced through,
<lb/>And nose cut off close underneath the brows,
<lb/>And had no longer but a single ear,

<sb/>
<lb/>Staying to look in wonder with the others,
<lb/>Before the others did his gullet open,
<lb/>Which outwardly was red in every part,

<sb/>
<lb/>And said: "O thou, whom guilt doth not condemn,
<lb/>And whom I once saw up in Latian land,
<lb/>Unless too great similitude deceive me,

<sb/>
<lb/>Call to remembrance Pier da Medicina,
<lb/>If e'er thou see again the lovely plain
<lb/>That from Vercelli slopes to Marcabo,

<sb/>
<lb/>And make it known to the best two of Fano,
<lb/>To Messer Guido and Angiolello likewise,
<lb/>That if foreseeing here be not in vain,

<sb/>
<lb/>Cast over from their vessel shall they be,
<lb/>And drowned near unto the Cattolica,
<lb/>By the betrayal of a tyrant fell.

<sb/>
<lb/>Between the isles of Cyprus and Majorca
<lb/>Neptune ne'er yet beheld so great a crime,
<lb/>Neither of pirates nor Argolic people.

<sb/>
<lb/>That traitor, who sees only with one eye,
<lb/>And holds the land, which some one here with me
<lb/>Would fain be fasting from the vision of,

<sb/>
<lb/>Will make them come unto a parley with him;
<lb/>Then will do so, that to Focara's wind
<lb/>They will not stand in need of vow or prayer."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I to him: "Show to me and declare,
<lb/>If thou wouldst have me bear up news of thee,
<lb/>Who is this person of the bitter vision."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then did he lay his hand upon the jaw
<lb/>Of one of his companions, and his mouth
<lb/>Oped, crying: "This is he, and he speaks not.

<sb/>
<lb/>This one, being banished, every doubt submerged
<lb/>In Caesar by affirming the forearmed
<lb/>Always with detriment allowed delay."

<sb/>
<lb/>O how bewildered unto me appeared,
<lb/>With tongue asunder in his windpipe slit,
<lb/>Curio, who in speaking was so bold!

<sb/>
<lb/>And one, who both his hands dissevered had,
<lb/>The stumps uplifting through the murky air,
<lb/>So that the blood made horrible his face,

<sb/>
<lb/>Cried out: "Thou shalt remember Mosca also,
<lb/>Who said, alas! 'A thing done has an end!'
<lb/>Which was an ill seed for the Tuscan people."

<sb/>
<lb/>"And death unto thy race," thereto I added;
<lb/>Whence he, accumulating woe on woe,
<lb/>Departed, like a person sad and crazed.

<sb/>
<lb/>But I remained to look upon the crowd;
<lb/>And saw a thing which I should be afraid,
<lb/>Without some further proof, even to recount,

<sb/>
<lb/>If it were not that conscience reassures me,
<lb/>That good companion which emboldens man
<lb/>Beneath the hauberk of its feeling pure.

<sb/>
<lb/>I truly saw, and still I seem to see it,
<lb/>A trunk without a head walk in like manner
<lb/>As walked the others of the mournful herd.

<sb/>
<lb/>And by the hair it held the head dissevered,
<lb/>Hung from the hand in fashion of a lantern,
<lb/>And that upon us gazed and said: "O me!"

<sb/>
<lb/>It of itself made to itself a lamp,
<lb/>And they were two in one, and one in two;
<lb/>How that can be, He knows who so ordains it.

<sb/>
<lb/>When it was come close to the bridge's foot,
<lb/>It lifted high its arm with all the head,
<lb/>To bring more closely unto us its words,

<sb/>
<lb/>Which were: "Behold now the sore penalty,
<lb/>Thou, who dost breathing go the dead beholding;
<lb/>Behold if any be as great as this.

<sb/>
<lb/>And so that thou may carry news of me,
<lb/>Know that Bertram de Born am I, the same
<lb/>Who gave to the Young King the evil comfort.

<sb/>
<lb/>I made the father and the son rebellious;
<lb/>Achitophel not more with Absalom
<lb/>And David did with his accursed goadings.

<sb/>
<lb/>Because I parted persons so united,
<lb/>Parted do I now bear my brain, alas!
<lb/>From its beginning, which is in this trunk.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus is observed in me the counterpoise."
    
</pouch_ring>

<canto numeral="XXIX"/>
    
<pouch_ring number="10" sub_sin="falsifier">

<sb/>
<lb/>The many people and the divers wounds
<lb/>These eyes of mine had so inebriated,
<lb/>That they were wishful to stand still and weep;

<sb/>
<lb/>But said Virgilius: "What dost thou still gaze at?
<lb/>Why is thy sight still riveted down there
<lb/>Among the mournful, mutilated shades?

<sb/>
<lb/>Thou hast not done so at the other Bolge;
<lb/>Consider, if to count them thou believest,
<lb/>That two-and-twenty miles the valley winds,

<sb/>
<lb/>And now the moon is underneath our feet;
<lb/>Henceforth the time allotted us is brief,
<lb/>And more is to be seen than what thou seest."

<sb/>
<lb/>"If thou hadst," I made answer thereupon,
<lb/>"Attended to the cause for which I looked,
<lb/>Perhaps a longer stay thou wouldst have pardoned."

<sb/>
<lb/>Meanwhile my Guide departed, and behind him
<lb/>I went, already making my reply,
<lb/>And superadding: "In that cavern where

<sb/>
<lb/>I held mine eyes with such attention fixed,
<lb/>I think a spirit of my blood laments
<lb/>The sin which down below there costs so much."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then said the Master: "Be no longer broken
<lb/>Thy thought from this time forward upon him;
<lb/>Attend elsewhere, and there let him remain;

<sb/>
<lb/>For him I saw below the little bridge,
<lb/>Pointing at thee, and threatening with his finger
<lb/>Fiercely, and heard him called Geri del Bello.

<sb/>
<lb/>So wholly at that time wast thou impeded
<lb/>By him who formerly held Altaforte,
<lb/>Thou didst not look that way; so he departed."

<sb/>
<lb/>"O my Conductor, his own violent death,
<lb/>Which is not yet avenged for him," I said,
<lb/>"By any who is sharer in the shame,

<sb/>
<lb/>Made him disdainful; whence he went away,
<lb/>As I imagine, without speaking to me,
<lb/>And thereby made me pity him the more."

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus did we speak as far as the first place
<lb/>Upon the crag, which the next valley shows
<lb/>Down to the bottom, if there were more light.

<sb/>
<lb/>When we were now right over the last cloister
<lb/>Of Malebolge, so that its lay-brothers
<lb/>Could manifest themselves unto our sight,

<sb/>
<lb/>Divers lamentings pierced me through and through,
<lb/>Which with compassion had their arrows barbed,
<lb/>Whereat mine ears I covered with my hands.

<sb/>
<lb/>What pain would be, if from the hospitals
<lb/>Of Valdichiana, 'twixt July and September,
<lb/>And of Maremma and Sardinia

<sb/>
<lb/>All the diseases in one moat were gathered,
<lb/>Such was it here, and such a stench came from it
<lb/>As from putrescent limbs is wont to issue.

<sb/>
<lb/>We had descended on the furthest bank
<lb/>From the long crag, upon the left hand still,
<lb/>And then more vivid was my power of sight

<sb/>
<lb/>Down tow'rds the bottom, where the ministress
<lb/>Of the high Lord, Justice infallible,
<lb/>Punishes forgers, which she here records.

<sb/>
<lb/>I do not think a sadder sight to see
<lb/>Was in Aegina the whole people sick,
<lb/>(When was the air so full of pestilence,

<sb/>
<lb/>The animals, down to the little worm,
<lb/>All fell, and afterwards the ancient people,
<lb/>According as the poets have affirmed,

<sb/>
<lb/>Were from the seed of ants restored again,)
<lb/>Than was it to behold through that dark valley
<lb/>The spirits languishing in divers heaps.

<sb/>
<lb/>This on the belly, that upon the back
<lb/>One of the other lay, and others crawling
<lb/>Shifted themselves along the dismal road.

<sb/>
<lb/>We step by step went onward without speech,
<lb/>Gazing upon and listening to the sick
<lb/>Who had not strength enough to lift their bodies.

<sb/>
<lb/>I saw two sitting leaned against each other,
<lb/>As leans in heating platter against platter,
<lb/>From head to foot bespotted o'er with scabs;

<sb/>
<lb/>And never saw I plied a currycomb
<lb/>By stable-boy for whom his master waits,
<lb/>Or him who keeps awake unwillingly,

<sb/>
<lb/>As every one was plying fast the bite
<lb/>Of nails upon himself, for the great rage
<lb/>Of itching which no other succour had.

<sb/>
<lb/>And the nails downward with them dragged the scab,
<lb/>In fashion as a knife the scales of bream,
<lb/>Or any other fish that has them largest.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O thou, that with thy fingers dost dismail thee,"
<lb/>Began my Leader unto one of them,
<lb/>"And makest of them pincers now and then,

<sb/>
<lb/>Tell me if any Latian is with those
<lb/>Who are herein; so may thy nails suffice thee
<lb/>To all eternity unto this work."

<sb/>
<lb/>"Latians are we, whom thou so wasted seest,
<lb/>Both of us here," one weeping made reply;
<lb/>"But who art thou, that questionest about us?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And said the Guide: "One am I who descends
<lb/>Down with this living man from cliff to cliff,
<lb/>And I intend to show Hell unto him."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then broken was their mutual support,
<lb/>And trembling each one turned himself to me,
<lb/>With others who had heard him by rebound.

<sb/>
<lb/>Wholly to me did the good Master gather,
<lb/>Saying: "Say unto them whate'er thou wishest."
<lb/>And I began, since he would have it so:

<sb/>
<lb/>"So may your memory not steal away
<lb/>In the first world from out the minds of men,
<lb/>But so may it survive 'neath many suns,

<sb/>
<lb/>Say to me who ye are, and of what people;
<lb/>Let not your foul and loathsome punishment
<lb/>Make you afraid to show yourselves to me."

<sb/>
<lb/>"I of Arezzo was," one made reply,
<lb/>"And Albert of Siena had me burned;
<lb/>But what I died for does not bring me here.

<sb/>
<lb/>'Tis true I said to him, speaking in jest,
<lb/>That I could rise by flight into the air,
<lb/>And he who had conceit, but little wit,

<sb/>
<lb/>Would have me show to him the art; and only
<lb/>Because no Daedalus I made him, made me
<lb/>Be burned by one who held him as his son.

<sb/>
<lb/>But unto the last Bolgia of the ten,
<lb/>For alchemy, which in the world I practised,
<lb/>Minos, who cannot err, has me condemned."

<sb/>
<lb/>And to the Poet said I: "Now was ever
<lb/>So vain a people as the Sienese?
<lb/>Not for a certainty the French by far."

<sb/>
<lb/>Whereat the other leper, who had heard me,
<lb/>Replied unto my speech: "Taking out Stricca,
<lb/>Who knew the art of moderate expenses,

<sb/>
<lb/>And Niccolo, who the luxurious use
<lb/>Of cloves discovered earliest of all
<lb/>Within that garden where such seed takes root;

<sb/>
<lb/>And taking out the band, among whom squandered
<lb/>Caccia d'Ascian his vineyards and vast woods,
<lb/>And where his wit the Abbagliato proffered!

<sb/>
<lb/>But, that thou know who thus doth second thee
<lb/>Against the Sienese, make sharp thine eye
<lb/>Tow'rds me, so that my face well answer thee,

<sb/>
<lb/>And thou shalt see I am Capocchio's shade,
<lb/>Who metals falsified by alchemy;
<lb/>Thou must remember, if I well descry thee,

<sb/>
<lb/>How I a skilful ape of nature was."

<canto numeral="XXX"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>'Twas at the time when Juno was enraged,
<lb/>For Semele, against the Theban blood,
<lb/>As she already more than once had shown,

<sb/>
<lb/>So reft of reason Athamas became,
<lb/>That, seeing his own wife with children twain
<lb/>Walking encumbered upon either hand,

<sb/>
<lb/>He cried: "Spread out the nets, that I may take
<lb/>The lioness and her whelps upon the passage;"
<lb/>And then extended his unpitying claws,

<sb/>
<lb/>Seizing the first, who had the name Learchus,
<lb/>And whirled him round, and dashed him on a rock;
<lb/>And she, with the other burthen, drowned herself;--

<sb/>
<lb/>And at the time when fortune downward hurled
<lb/>The Trojan's arrogance, that all things dared,
<lb/>So that the king was with his kingdom crushed,

<sb/>
<lb/>Hecuba sad, disconsolate, and captive,
<lb/>When lifeless she beheld Polyxena,
<lb/>And of her Polydorus on the shore

<sb/>
<lb/>Of ocean was the dolorous one aware,
<lb/>Out of her senses like a dog she barked,
<lb/>So much the anguish had her mind distorted;

<sb/>
<lb/>But not of Thebes the furies nor the Trojan
<lb/>Were ever seen in any one so cruel
<lb/>In goading beasts, and much more human members,

<sb/>
<lb/>As I beheld two shadows pale and naked,
<lb/>Who, biting, in the manner ran along
<lb/>That a boar does, when from the sty turned loose.

<sb/>
<lb/>One to Capocchio came, and by the nape
<lb/>Seized with its teeth his neck, so that in dragging
<lb/>It made his belly grate the solid bottom.

<sb/>
<lb/>And the Aretine, who trembling had remained,
<lb/>Said to me: "That mad sprite is Gianni Schicchi,
<lb/>And raving goes thus harrying other people."

<sb/>
<lb/>"O," said I to him, "so may not the other
<lb/>Set teeth on thee, let it not weary thee
<lb/>To tell us who it is, ere it dart hence."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "That is the ancient ghost
<lb/>Of the nefarious Myrrha, who became
<lb/>Beyond all rightful love her father's lover.

<sb/>
<lb/>She came to sin with him after this manner,
<lb/>By counterfeiting of another's form;
<lb/>As he who goeth yonder undertook,

<sb/>
<lb/>That he might gain the lady of the herd,
<lb/>To counterfeit in himself Buoso Donati,
<lb/>Making a will and giving it due form."

<sb/>
<lb/>And after the two maniacs had passed
<lb/>On whom I held mine eye, I turned it back
<lb/>To look upon the other evil-born.

<sb/>
<lb/>I saw one made in fashion of a lute,
<lb/>If he had only had the groin cut off
<lb/>Just at the point at which a man is forked.

<sb/>
<lb/>The heavy dropsy, that so disproportions
<lb/>The limbs with humours, which it ill concocts,
<lb/>That the face corresponds not to the belly,

<sb/>
<lb/>Compelled him so to hold his lips apart
<lb/>As does the hectic, who because of thirst
<lb/>One tow'rds the chin, the other upward turns.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O ye, who without any torment are,
<lb/>And why I know not, in the world of woe,"
<lb/>He said to us, "behold, and be attentive

<sb/>
<lb/>Unto the misery of Master Adam;
<lb/>I had while living much of what I wished,
<lb/>And now, alas! a drop of water crave.

<sb/>
<lb/>The rivulets, that from the verdant hills
<lb/>Of Cassentin descend down into Arno,
<lb/>Making their channels to be cold and moist,

<sb/>
<lb/>Ever before me stand, and not in vain;
<lb/>For far more doth their image dry me up
<lb/>Than the disease which strips my face of flesh.

<sb/>
<lb/>The rigid justice that chastises me
<lb/>Draweth occasion from the place in which
<lb/>I sinned, to put the more my sighs in flight.

<sb/>
<lb/>There is Romena, where I counterfeited
<lb/>The currency imprinted with the Baptist,
<lb/>For which I left my body burned above.

<sb/>
<lb/>But if I here could see the tristful soul
<lb/>Of Guido, or Alessandro, or their brother,
<lb/>For Branda's fount I would not give the sight.

<sb/>
<lb/>One is within already, if the raving
<lb/>Shades that are going round about speak truth;
<lb/>But what avails it me, whose limbs are tied?

<sb/>
<lb/>If I were only still so light, that in
<lb/>A hundred years I could advance one inch,
<lb/>I had already started on the way,

<sb/>
<lb/>Seeking him out among this squalid folk,
<lb/>Although the circuit be eleven miles,
<lb/>And be not less than half a mile across.

<sb/>
<lb/>For them am I in such a family;
<lb/>They did induce me into coining florins,
<lb/>Which had three carats of impurity."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I to him: "Who are the two poor wretches
<lb/>That smoke like unto a wet hand in winter,
<lb/>Lying there close upon thy right-hand confines?"

<sb/>
<lb/>"I found them here," replied he, "when I rained
<lb/>Into this chasm, and since they have not turned,
<lb/>Nor do I think they will for evermore.

<sb/>
<lb/>One the false woman is who accused Joseph,
<lb/>The other the false Sinon, Greek of Troy;
<lb/>From acute fever they send forth such reek."

<sb/>
<lb/>And one of them, who felt himself annoyed
<lb/>At being, peradventure, named so darkly,
<lb/>Smote with the fist upon his hardened paunch.

<sb/>
<lb/>It gave a sound, as if it were a drum;
<lb/>And Master Adam smote him in the face,
<lb/>With arm that did not seem to be less hard,

<sb/>
<lb/>Saying to him: "Although be taken from me
<lb/>All motion, for my limbs that heavy are,
<lb/>I have an arm unfettered for such need."

<sb/>
<lb/>Whereat he answer made: "When thou didst go
<lb/>Unto the fire, thou hadst it not so ready:
<lb/>But hadst it so and more when thou wast coining."

<sb/>
<lb/>The dropsical: "Thou sayest true in that;
<lb/>But thou wast not so true a witness there,
<lb/>Where thou wast questioned of the truth at Troy."

<sb/>
<lb/>"If I spake false, thou falsifiedst the coin,"
<lb/>Said Sinon; "and for one fault I am here,
<lb/>And thou for more than any other demon."

<sb/>
<lb/>"Remember, perjurer, about the horse,"
<lb/>He made reply who had the swollen belly,
<lb/>"And rueful be it thee the whole world knows it."

<sb/>
<lb/>"Rueful to thee the thirst be wherewith cracks
<lb/>Thy tongue," the Greek said, "and the putrid water
<lb/>That hedges so thy paunch before thine eyes."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then the false-coiner: "So is gaping wide
<lb/>Thy mouth for speaking evil, as 'tis wont;
<lb/>Because if I have thirst, and humour stuff me

<sb/>
<lb/>Thou hast the burning and the head that aches,
<lb/>And to lick up the mirror of Narcissus
<lb/>Thou wouldst not want words many to invite thee."

<sb/>
<lb/>In listening to them was I wholly fixed,
<lb/>When said the Master to me: "Now just look,
<lb/>For little wants it that I quarrel with thee."

<sb/>
<lb/>When him I heard in anger speak to me,
<lb/>I turned me round towards him with such shame
<lb/>That still it eddies through my memory.

<sb/>
<lb/>And as he is who dreams of his own harm,
<lb/>Who dreaming wishes it may be a dream,
<lb/>So that he craves what is, as if it were not;

<sb/>
<lb/>Such I became, not having power to speak,
<lb/>For to excuse myself I wished, and still
<lb/>Excused myself, and did not think I did it.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Less shame doth wash away a greater fault,"
<lb/>The Master said, "than this of thine has been;
<lb/>Therefore thyself disburden of all sadness,

<sb/>
<lb/>And make account that I am aye beside thee,
<lb/>If e'er it come to pass that fortune bring thee
<lb/>Where there are people in a like dispute;

<sb/>
<lb/>For a base wish it is to wish to hear it."

<canto numeral="XXXI"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>One and the selfsame tongue first wounded me,
<lb/>So that it tinged the one cheek and the other,
<lb/>And then held out to me the medicine;

<sb/>
<lb/>Thus do I hear that once Achilles' spear,
<lb/>His and his father's, used to be the cause
<lb/>First of a sad and then a gracious boon.

<sb/>
<lb/>We turned our backs upon the wretched valley,
<lb/>Upon the bank that girds it round about,
<lb/>Going across it without any speech.

<sb/>
<lb/>There it was less than night, and less than day,
<lb/>So that my sight went little in advance;
<lb/>But I could hear the blare of a loud horn,

<sb/>
<lb/>So loud it would have made each thunder faint,
<lb/>Which, counter to it following its way,
<lb/>Mine eyes directed wholly to one place.

<sb/>
<lb/>After the dolorous discomfiture
<lb/>When Charlemagne the holy emprise lost,
<lb/>So terribly Orlando sounded not.

<sb/>
<lb/>Short while my head turned thitherward I held
<lb/>When many lofty towers I seemed to see,
<lb/>Whereat I: "Master, say, what town is this?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "Because thou peerest forth
<lb/>Athwart the darkness at too great a distance,
<lb/>It happens that thou errest in thy fancy.

<sb/>
<lb/>Well shalt thou see, if thou arrivest there,
<lb/>How much the sense deceives itself by distance;
<lb/>Therefore a little faster spur thee on."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then tenderly he took me by the hand,
<lb/>And said: "Before we farther have advanced,
<lb/>That the reality may seem to thee

<sb/>
<lb/>Less strange, know that these are not towers, but giants,
<lb/>And they are in the well, around the bank,
<lb/>From navel downward, one and all of them."

<sb/>
<lb/>As, when the fog is vanishing away,
<lb/>Little by little doth the sight refigure
<lb/>Whate'er the mist that crowds the air conceals,

<sb/>
<lb/>So, piercing through the dense and darksome air,
<lb/>More and more near approaching tow'rd the verge,
<lb/>My error fled, and fear came over me;

<sb/>
<lb/>Because as on its circular parapets
<lb/>Montereggione crowns itself with towers,
<lb/>E'en thus the margin which surrounds the well

<sb/>
<lb/>With one half of their bodies turreted
<lb/>The horrible giants, whom Jove menaces
<lb/>E'en now from out the heavens when he thunders.

<sb/>
<lb/>And I of one already saw the face,
<lb/>Shoulders, and breast, and great part of the belly,
<lb/>And down along his sides both of the arms.

<sb/>
<lb/>Certainly Nature, when she left the making
<lb/>Of animals like these, did well indeed,
<lb/>By taking such executors from Mars;

<sb/>
<lb/>And if of elephants and whales she doth not
<lb/>Repent her, whosoever looketh subtly
<lb/>More just and more discreet will hold her for it;

<sb/>
<lb/>For where the argument of intellect
<lb/>Is added unto evil will and power,
<lb/>No rampart can the people make against it.

<sb/>
<lb/>His face appeared to me as long and large
<lb/>As is at Rome the pine-cone of Saint Peter's,
<lb/>And in proportion were the other bones;

<sb/>
<lb/>So that the margin, which an apron was
<lb/>Down from the middle, showed so much of him
<lb/>Above it, that to reach up to his hair

<sb/>
<lb/>Three Frieslanders in vain had vaunted them;
<lb/>For I beheld thirty great palms of him
<lb/>Down from the place where man his mantle buckles.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Raphael mai amech izabi almi,"
<lb/>Began to clamour the ferocious mouth,
<lb/>To which were not befitting sweeter psalms.

<sb/>
<lb/>And unto him my Guide: "Soul idiotic,
<lb/>Keep to thy horn, and vent thyself with that,
<lb/>When wrath or other passion touches thee.

<sb/>
<lb/>Search round thy neck, and thou wilt find the belt
<lb/>Which keeps it fastened, O bewildered soul,
<lb/>And see it, where it bars thy mighty breast."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then said to me: "He doth himself accuse;
<lb/>This one is Nimrod, by whose evil thought
<lb/>One language in the world is not still used.

<sb/>
<lb/>Here let us leave him and not speak in vain;
<lb/>For even such to him is every language
<lb/>As his to others, which to none is known."

<sb/>
<lb/>Therefore a longer journey did we make,
<lb/>Turned to the left, and a crossbow-shot oft
<lb/>We found another far more fierce and large.

<sb/>
<lb/>In binding him, who might the master be
<lb/>I cannot say; but he had pinioned close
<lb/>Behind the right arm, and in front the other,

<sb/>
<lb/>With chains, that held him so begirt about
<lb/>From the neck down, that on the part uncovered
<lb/>It wound itself as far as the fifth gyre.

<sb/>
<lb/>"This proud one wished to make experiment
<lb/>Of his own power against the Supreme Jove,"
<lb/>My Leader said, "whence he has such a guerdon.

<sb/>
<lb/>Ephialtes is his name; he showed great prowess.
<lb/>What time the giants terrified the gods;
<lb/>The arms he wielded never more he moves."

<sb/>
<lb/>And I to him: "If possible, I should wish
<lb/>That of the measureless Briareus
<lb/>These eyes of mine might have experience."

<sb/>
<lb/>Whence he replied: "Thou shalt behold Antaeus
<lb/>Close by here, who can speak and is unbound,
<lb/>Who at the bottom of all crime shall place us.

<sb/>
<lb/>Much farther yon is he whom thou wouldst see,
<lb/>And he is bound, and fashioned like to this one,
<lb/>Save that he seems in aspect more ferocious."

<sb/>
<lb/>There never was an earthquake of such might
<lb/>That it could shake a tower so violently,
<lb/>As Ephialtes suddenly shook himself.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then was I more afraid of death than ever,
<lb/>For nothing more was needful than the fear,
<lb/>If I had not beheld the manacles.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then we proceeded farther in advance,
<lb/>And to Antaeus came, who, full five ells
<lb/>Without the head, forth issued from the cavern.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O thou, who in the valley fortunate,
<lb/>Which Scipio the heir of glory made,
<lb/>When Hannibal turned back with all his hosts,

<sb/>
<lb/>Once brought'st a thousand lions for thy prey,
<lb/>And who, hadst thou been at the mighty war
<lb/>Among thy brothers, some it seems still think

<sb/>
<lb/>The sons of Earth the victory would have gained:
<lb/>Place us below, nor be disdainful of it,
<lb/>There where the cold doth lock Cocytus up.

<sb/>
<lb/>Make us not go to Tityus nor Typhoeus;
<lb/>This one can give of that which here is longed for;
<lb/>Therefore stoop down, and do not curl thy lip.

<sb/>
<lb/>Still in the world can he restore thy fame;
<lb/>Because he lives, and still expects long life,
<lb/>If to itself Grace call him not untimely."

<sb/>
<lb/>So said the Master; and in haste the other
<lb/>His hands extended and took up my Guide,--
<lb/>Hands whose great pressure Hercules once felt.

<sb/>
<lb/>Virgilius, when he felt himself embraced,
<lb/>Said unto me: "Draw nigh, that I may take thee;"
<lb/>Then of himself and me one bundle made.

<sb/>
<lb/>As seems the Carisenda, to behold
<lb/>Beneath the leaning side, when goes a cloud
<lb/>Above it so that opposite it hangs;

<sb/>
<lb/>Such did Antaeus seem to me, who stood
<lb/>Watching to see him stoop, and then it was
<lb/>I could have wished to go some other way.

<sb/>
<lb/>But lightly in the abyss, which swallows up
<lb/>Judas with Lucifer, he put us down;
<lb/>Nor thus bowed downward made he there delay,

<sb/>
<lb/>But, as a mast does in a ship, uprose.

</pouch_ring>

</circle>
    
<circle number="9" main_sin="traitor">

<canto numeral="XXXII"/>
    
<pouch_ring number="1" sub_sin="traitor_to_kin">

<sb/>
<lb/>If I had rhymes both rough and stridulous,
<lb/>As were appropriate to the dismal hole
<lb/>Down upon which thrust all the other rocks,

<sb/>
<lb/>I would press out the juice of my conception
<lb/>More fully; but because I have them not,
<lb/>Not without fear I bring myself to speak;

<sb/>
<lb/>For 'tis no enterprise to take in jest,
<lb/>To sketch the bottom of all the universe,
<lb/>Nor for a tongue that cries Mamma and Babbo.

<sb/>
<lb/>But may those Ladies help this verse of mine,
<lb/>Who helped Amphion in enclosing Thebes,
<lb/>That from the fact the word be not diverse.

<sb/>
<lb/>O rabble ill-begotten above all,
<lb/>Who're in the place to speak of which is hard,
<lb/>'Twere better ye had here been sheep or goats!

<sb/>
<lb/>When we were down within the darksome well,
<lb/>Beneath the giant's feet, but lower far,
<lb/>And I was scanning still the lofty wall,

<sb/>
<lb/>I heard it said to me: "Look how thou steppest!
<lb/>Take heed thou do not trample with thy feet
<lb/>The heads of the tired, miserable brothers!"

<sb/>
<lb/>Whereat I turned me round, and saw before me
<lb/>And underfoot a lake, that from the frost
<lb/>The semblance had of glass, and not of water.

<sb/>
<lb/>So thick a veil ne'er made upon its current
<lb/>In winter-time Danube in Austria,
<lb/>Nor there beneath the frigid sky the Don,

<sb/>
<lb/>As there was here; so that if Tambernich
<lb/>Had fallen upon it, or Pietrapana,
<lb/>E'en at the edge 'twould not have given a creak.

<sb/>
<lb/>And as to croak the frog doth place himself
<lb/>With muzzle out of water,--when is dreaming
<lb/>Of gleaning oftentimes the peasant-girl,--

<sb/>
<lb/>Livid, as far down as where shame appears,
<lb/>Were the disconsolate shades within the ice,
<lb/>Setting their teeth unto the note of storks.

<sb/>
<lb/>Each one his countenance held downward bent;
<lb/>From mouth the cold, from eyes the doleful heart
<lb/>Among them witness of itself procures.

<sb/>
<lb/>When round about me somewhat I had looked,
<lb/>I downward turned me, and saw two so close,
<lb/>The hair upon their heads together mingled.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Ye who so strain your breasts together, tell me,"
<lb/>I said, "who are you;" and they bent their necks,
<lb/>And when to me their faces they had lifted,

<sb/>
<lb/>Their eyes, which first were only moist within,
<lb/>Gushed o'er the eyelids, and the frost congealed
<lb/>The tears between, and locked them up again.

<sb/>
<lb/>Clamp never bound together wood with wood
<lb/>So strongly; whereat they, like two he-goats,
<lb/>Butted together, so much wrath o'ercame them.

<sb/>
<lb/>And one, who had by reason of the cold
<lb/>Lost both his ears, still with his visage downward,
<lb/>Said: "Why dost thou so mirror thyself in us?

<sb/>
<lb/>If thou desire to know who these two are,
<lb/>The valley whence Bisenzio descends
<lb/>Belonged to them and to their father Albert.

<sb/>
<lb/>They from one body came, and all Caina
<lb/>Thou shalt search through, and shalt not find a shade
<lb/>More worthy to be fixed in gelatine;

<sb/>
<lb/>Not he in whom were broken breast and shadow
<lb/>At one and the same blow by Arthur's hand;
<lb/>Focaccia not; not he who me encumbers

<sb/>
<lb/>So with his head I see no farther forward,
<lb/>And bore the name of Sassol Mascheroni;
<lb/>Well knowest thou who he was, if thou art Tuscan.

<sb/>
<lb/>And that thou put me not to further speech,
<lb/>Know that I Camicion de' Pazzi was,
<lb/>And wait Carlino to exonerate me."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then I beheld a thousand faces, made
<lb/>Purple with cold; whence o'er me comes a shudder,
<lb/>And evermore will come, at frozen ponds.

<sb/>
<lb/>And while we were advancing tow'rds the middle,
<lb/>Where everything of weight unites together,
<lb/>And I was shivering in the eternal shade,

<sb/>
<lb/>Whether 'twere will, or destiny, or chance,
<lb/>I know not; but in walking 'mong the heads
<lb/>I struck my foot hard in the face of one.

<sb/>
<lb/>Weeping he growled: "Why dost thou trample me?
<lb/>Unless thou comest to increase the vengeance
<lb/>of Montaperti, why dost thou molest me?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And I: "My Master, now wait here for me,
<lb/>That I through him may issue from a doubt;
<lb/>Then thou mayst hurry me, as thou shalt wish."

<sb/>
<lb/>The Leader stopped; and to that one I said
<lb/>Who was blaspheming vehemently still:
<lb/>"Who art thou, that thus reprehendest others?"

</pouch_ring>

<pouch_ring number="2" sub_sin="traitor_to_country">

<sb/>
<lb/>"Now who art thou, that goest through Antenora
<lb/>Smiting," replied he, "other people's cheeks,
<lb/>So that, if thou wert living, 'twere too much?"

<sb/>
<lb/>"Living I am, and dear to thee it may be,"
<lb/>Was my response, "if thou demandest fame,
<lb/>That 'mid the other notes thy name I place."

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "For the reverse I long;
<lb/>Take thyself hence, and give me no more trouble;
<lb/>For ill thou knowest to flatter in this hollow."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then by the scalp behind I seized upon him,
<lb/>And said: "It must needs be thou name thyself,
<lb/>Or not a hair remain upon thee here."

<sb/>
<lb/>Whence he to me: "Though thou strip off my hair,
<lb/>I will not tell thee who I am, nor show thee,
<lb/>If on my head a thousand times thou fall."

<sb/>
<lb/>I had his hair in hand already twisted,
<lb/>And more than one shock of it had pulled out,
<lb/>He barking, with his eyes held firmly down,

<sb/>
<lb/>When cried another: "What doth ail thee, Bocca?
<lb/>Is't not enough to clatter with thy jaws,
<lb/>But thou must bark? what devil touches thee?"

<sb/>
<lb/>"Now," said I, "I care not to have thee speak,
<lb/>Accursed traitor; for unto thy shame
<lb/>I will report of thee veracious news."

<sb/>
<lb/>"Begone," replied he, "and tell what thou wilt,
<lb/>But be not silent, if thou issue hence,
<lb/>Of him who had just now his tongue so prompt;

<sb/>
<lb/>He weepeth here the silver of the French;
<lb/>'I saw,' thus canst thou phrase it, 'him of Duera
<lb/>There where the sinners stand out in the cold.'

<sb/>
<lb/>If thou shouldst questioned be who else was there,
<lb/>Thou hast beside thee him of Beccaria,
<lb/>Of whom the gorget Florence slit asunder;

<sb/>
<lb/>Gianni del Soldanier, I think, may be
<lb/>Yonder with Ganellon, and Tebaldello
<lb/>Who oped Faenza when the people slep."

<sb/>
<lb/>Already we had gone away from him,
<lb/>When I beheld two frozen in one hole,
<lb/>So that one head a hood was to the other;

<sb/>
<lb/>And even as bread through hunger is devoured,
<lb/>The uppermost on the other set his teeth,
<lb/>There where the brain is to the nape united.

<sb/>
<lb/>Not in another fashion Tydeus gnawed
<lb/>The temples of Menalippus in disdain,
<lb/>Than that one did the skull and the other things.

<sb/>
<lb/>"O thou, who showest by such bestial sign
<lb/>Thy hatred against him whom thou art eating,
<lb/>Tell me the wherefore," said I, "with this compact,

<sb/>
<lb/>That if thou rightfully of him complain,
<lb/>In knowing who ye are, and his transgression,
<lb/>I in the world above repay thee for it,

<sb/>
<lb/>If that wherewith I speak be not dried up."

<canto numeral="XXXIII"/>

<sb/>
<lb/>His mouth uplifted from his grim repast,
<lb/>That sinner, wiping it upon the hair
<lb/>Of the same head that he behind had wasted.

<sb/>
<lb/>Then he began: "Thou wilt that I renew
<lb/>The desperate grief, which wrings my heart already
<lb/>To think of only, ere I speak of it;

<sb/>
<lb/>But if my words be seed that may bear fruit
<lb/>Of infamy to the traitor whom I gnaw,
<lb/>Speaking and weeping shalt thou see together.

<sb/>
<lb/>I know not who thou art, nor by what mode
<lb/>Thou hast come down here; but a Florentine
<lb/>Thou seemest to me truly, when I hear thee.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thou hast to know I was Count Ugolino,
<lb/>And this one was Ruggieri the Archbishop;
<lb/>Now I will tell thee why I am such a neighbour.

<sb/>
<lb/>That, by effect of his malicious thoughts,
<lb/>Trusting in him I was made prisoner,
<lb/>And after put to death, I need not say;

<sb/>
<lb/> But ne'ertheless what thou canst not have heard,
<lb/>That is to say, how cruel was my death,
<lb/>Hear shalt thou, and shalt know if he has wronged me.

<sb/>
<lb/>A narrow perforation in the mew,
<lb/>Which bears because of me the title of Famine,
<lb/>And in which others still must be locked up,

<sb/>
<lb/>Had shown me through its opening many moons
<lb/>Already, when I dreamed the evil dream
<lb/>Which of the future rent for me the veil.

<sb/>
<lb/>This one appeared to me as lord and master,
<lb/>Hunting the wolf and whelps upon the mountain
<lb/>For which the Pisans cannot Lucca see.

<sb/>
<lb/>With sleuth-hounds gaunt, and eager, and well trained,
<lb/>Gualandi with Sismondi and Lanfianchi
<lb/>He had sent out before him to the front.

<sb/>
<lb/>After brief course seemed unto me forespent
<lb/>The father and the sons, and with sharp tushes
<lb/>It seemed to me I saw their flanks ripped open.

<sb/>
<lb/>When I before the morrow was awake,
<lb/>Moaning amid their sleep I heard my sons
<lb/>Who with me were, and asking after bread.

<sb/>
<lb/>Cruel indeed art thou, if yet thou grieve not,
<lb/>Thinking of what my heart foreboded me,
<lb/>And weep'st thou not, what art thou wont to weep at?

<sb/>
<lb/>They were awake now, and the hour drew nigh
<lb/>At which our food used to be brought to us,
<lb/>And through his dream was each one apprehensive;

<sb/>
<lb/>And I heard locking up the under door
<lb/>Of the horrible tower; whereat without a word
<lb/>I gazed into the faces of my sons.

<sb/>
<lb/>I wept not, I within so turned to stone;
<lb/>They wept; and darling little Anselm mine
<lb/>Said: 'Thou dost gaze so, father, what doth ail thee?'

<sb/>
<lb/>Still not a tear I shed, nor answer made
<lb/>All of that day, nor yet the night thereafter,
<lb/>Until another sun rose on the world.

<sb/>
<lb/>As now a little glimmer made its way
<lb/>Into the dolorous prison, and I saw
<lb/>Upon four faces my own very aspect,

<sb/>
<lb/>Both of my hands in agony I bit;
<lb/>And, thinking that I did it from desire
<lb/>Of eating, on a sudden they uprose,

<sb/>
<lb/>And said they: 'Father, much less pain 'twill give us
<lb/>If thou do eat of us; thyself didst clothe us
<lb/>With this poor flesh, and do thou strip it off.'

<sb/>
<lb/>I calmed me then, not to make them more sad.
<lb/>That day we all were silent, and the next.
<lb/>Ah! obdurate earth, wherefore didst thou not open?

<sb/>
<lb/>When we had come unto the fourth day, Gaddo
<lb/>Threw himself down outstretched before my feet,
<lb/>Saying, 'My father, why dost thou not help me?'

<sb/>
<lb/>And there he died; and, as thou seest me,
<lb/>I saw the three fall, one by one, between
<lb/>The fifth day and the sixth; whence I betook me,

<sb/>
<lb/>Already blind, to groping over each,
<lb/>And three days called them after they were dead;
<lb/>Then hunger did what sorrow could not do."

<sb/>
<lb/>When he had said this, with his eyes distorted,
<lb/>The wretched skull resumed he with his teeth,
<lb/>Which, as a dog's, upon the bone were strong.

<sb/>
<lb/>Ah! Pisa, thou opprobrium of the people
<lb/>Of the fair land there where the 'Si' doth sound,
<lb/>Since slow to punish thee thy neighbours are,

<sb/>
<lb/>Let the Capraia and Gorgona move,
<lb/>And make a hedge across the mouth of Arno
<lb/>That every person in thee it may drown!

<sb/>
<lb/>For if Count Ugolino had the fame
<lb/>Of having in thy castles thee betrayed,
<lb/>Thou shouldst not on such cross have put his sons.

<sb/>
<lb/>Guiltless of any crime, thou modern Thebes!
<lb/>Their youth made Uguccione and Brigata,
<lb/>And the other two my song doth name above!

<sb/>
<lb/>We passed still farther onward, where the ice
<lb/>Another people ruggedly enswathes,
<lb/>Not downward turned, but all of them reversed.

<sb/>
<lb/>Weeping itself there does not let them weep,
<lb/>And grief that finds a barrier in the eyes
<lb/>Turns itself inward to increase the anguish;

<sb/>
<lb/>Because the earliest tears a cluster form,
<lb/>And, in the manner of a crystal visor,
<lb/>Fill all the cup beneath the eyebrow full.

<sb/>
<lb/>And notwithstanding that, as in a callus,
<lb/>Because of cold all sensibility
<lb/>Its station had abandoned in my face,

<sb/>
<lb/>Still it appeared to me I felt some wind;
<lb/>Whence I: "My Master, who sets this in motion?
<lb/>Is not below here every vapour quenched?"

<sb/>
<lb/>Whence he to me: "Full soon shalt thou be where
<lb/>Thine eye shall answer make to thee of this,
<lb/>Seeing the cause which raineth down the blast."

<sb/>
<lb/>And one of the wretches of the frozen crust
<lb/>Cried out to us: "O souls so merciless
<lb/>That the last post is given unto you,

<sb/>
<lb/>Lift from mine eyes the rigid veils, that I
<lb/>May vent the sorrow which impregns my heart
<lb/>A little, e'er the weeping recongeal."

<sb/>
<lb/>Whence I to him: "If thou wouldst have me help thee
<lb/>Say who thou wast; and if I free thee not,
<lb/>May I go to the bottom of the ice."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then he replied: "I am Friar Alberigo;
<lb/>He am I of the fruit of the bad garden,
<lb/>Who here a date am getting for my fig."

<sb/>
<lb/>"O," said I to him, "now art thou, too, dead?"
<lb/>And he to me: "How may my body fare
<lb/>Up in the world, no knowledge I possess.

</pouch_ring>

<pouch_ring number="3" sub_sin="traitor_to_guest">

<sb/>
<lb/>Such an advantage has this Ptolomaea,
<lb/>That oftentimes the soul descendeth here
<lb/>Sooner than Atropos in motion sets it.

<sb/>
<lb/>And, that thou mayest more willingly remove
<lb/>From off my countenance these glassy tears,
<lb/>Know that as soon as any soul betrays

<sb/>
<lb/>As I have done, his body by a demon
<lb/>Is taken from him, who thereafter rules it,
<lb/>Until his time has wholly been revolved.

<sb/>
<lb/>Itself down rushes into such a cistern;
<lb/>And still perchance above appears the body
<lb/>Of yonder shade, that winters here behind me.

<sb/>
<lb/>This thou shouldst know, if thou hast just come down;
<lb/>It is Ser Branca d' Oria, and many years
<lb/>Have passed away since he was thus locked up."

<sb/>
<lb/>"I think," said I to him, "thou dost deceive me;
<lb/>For Branca d' Oria is not dead as yet,
<lb/>And eats, and drinks, and sleeps, and puts on clothes."

<sb/>
<lb/>"In moat above," said he, "of Malebranche,
<lb/>There where is boiling the tenacious pitch,
<lb/>As yet had Michel Zanche not arrived,

<sb/>
<lb/>When this one left a devil in his stead
<lb/>In his own body and one near of kin,
<lb/>Who made together with him the betrayal.

<sb/>
<lb/>But hitherward stretch out thy hand forthwith,
<lb/>Open mine eyes;"--and open them I did not,
<lb/>And to be rude to him was courtesy.

<sb/>
<lb/>Ah, Genoese! ye men at variance
<lb/>With every virtue, full of every vice
<lb/>Wherefore are ye not scattered from the world?

<sb/>
<lb/>For with the vilest spirit of Romagna
<lb/>I found of you one such, who for his deeds
<lb/>In soul already in Cocytus bathes,

<sb/>
<lb/>And still above in body seems alive!

</pouch_ring>

<canto numeral="XXXIV"/>
    
<pouch_ring number="4" sub_sin="traitor_to_benefactor">

<sb/>
<lb/>"'Vexilla Regis prodeunt Inferni'
<lb/>Towards us; therefore look in front of thee,"
<lb/>My Master said, "if thou discernest him."

<sb/>
<lb/>As, when there breathes a heavy fog, or when
<lb/>Our hemisphere is darkening into night,
<lb/>Appears far off a mill the wind is turning,

<sb/>
<lb/>Methought that such a building then I saw;
<lb/>And, for the wind, I drew myself behind
<lb/>My Guide, because there was no other shelter.

<sb/>
<lb/>Now was I, and with fear in verse I put it,
<lb/>There where the shades were wholly covered up,
<lb/>And glimmered through like unto straws in glass.

<sb/>
<lb/>Some prone are lying, others stand erect,
<lb/>This with the head, and that one with the soles;
<lb/>Another, bow-like, face to feet inverts.

<sb/>
<lb/>When in advance so far we had proceeded,
<lb/>That it my Master pleased to show to me
<lb/>The creature who once had the beauteous semblance,

<sb/>
<lb/>He from before me moved and made me stop,
<lb/>Saying: "Behold Dis, and behold the place
<lb/>Where thou with fortitude must arm thyself."

<sb/>
<lb/>How frozen I became and powerless then,
<lb/>Ask it not, Reader, for I write it not,
<lb/>Because all language would be insufficient.

<sb/>
<lb/>I did not die, and I alive remained not;
<lb/>Think for thyself now, hast thou aught of wit,
<lb/>What I became, being of both deprived.

<sb/>
<lb/>The Emperor of the kingdom dolorous
<lb/>From his mid-breast forth issued from the ice;
<lb/>And better with a giant I compare

<sb/>
<lb/>Than do the giants with those arms of his;
<lb/>Consider now how great must be that whole,
<lb/>Which unto such a part conforms itself.

<sb/>
<lb/>Were he as fair once, as he now is foul,
<lb/>And lifted up his brow against his Maker,
<lb/>Well may proceed from him all tribulation.

<sb/>
<lb/>O, what a marvel it appeared to me,
<lb/>When I beheld three faces on his head!
<lb/>The one in front, and that vermilion was;

<sb/>
<lb/>Two were the others, that were joined with this
<lb/>Above the middle part of either shoulder,
<lb/>And they were joined together at the crest;

<sb/>
<lb/>And the right-hand one seemed 'twixt white and yellow;
<lb/>The left was such to look upon as those
<lb/>Who come from where the Nile falls valley-ward.

<sb/>
<lb/>Underneath each came forth two mighty wings,
<lb/>Such as befitting were so great a bird;
<lb/>Sails of the sea I never saw so large.

<sb/>
<lb/> No feathers had they, but as of a bat
<lb/>Their fashion was; and he was waving them,
<lb/>So that three winds proceeded forth therefrom.

<sb/>
<lb/>Thereby Cocytus wholly was congealed.
<lb/>With six eyes did he weep, and down three chins
<lb/>Trickled the tear-drops and the bloody drivel.

<sb/>
<lb/>At every mouth he with his teeth was crunching
<lb/>A sinner, in the manner of a brake,
<lb/>So that he three of them tormented thus.

<sb/>
<lb/>To him in front the biting was as naught
<lb/>Unto the clawing, for sometimes the spine
<lb/>Utterly stripped of all the skin remained.

<sb/>
<lb/>"That soul up there which has the greatest pain,"
<lb/>The Master said, "is Judas Iscariot;
<lb/>With head inside, he plies his legs without.

<sb/>
<lb/>Of the two others, who head downward are,
<lb/>The one who hangs from the black jowl is Brutus;
<lb/>See how he writhes himself, and speaks no word.

<sb/>
<lb/>And the other, who so stalwart seems, is Cassius.
<lb/>But night is reascending, and 'tis time
<lb/>That we depart, for we have seen the whole."

<sb/>
<lb/>As seemed him good, I clasped him round the neck,
<lb/>And he the vantage seized of time and place,
<lb/>And when the wings were opened wide apart,

<sb/>
<lb/>He laid fast hold upon the shaggy sides;
<lb/>From fell to fell descended downward then
<lb/>Between the thick hair and the frozen crust.

<sb/>
<lb/>When we were come to where the thigh revolves
<lb/>Exactly on the thickness of the haunch,
<lb/>The Guide, with labour and with hard-drawn breath,

<sb/>
<lb/>Turned round his head where he had had his legs,
<lb/>And grappled to the hair, as one who mounts,
<lb/>So that to Hell I thought we were returning.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Keep fast thy hold, for by such stairs as these,"
<lb/>The Master said, panting as one fatigued,
<lb/>"Must we perforce depart from so much evil."

<sb/>
<lb/>Then through the opening of a rock he issued,
<lb/>And down upon the margin seated me;
<lb/>Then tow'rds me he outstretched his wary step.

<sb/>
<lb/>I lifted up mine eyes and thought to see
<lb/>Lucifer in the same way I had left him;
<lb/>And I beheld him upward hold his legs.

<sb/>
<lb/>And if I then became disquieted,
<lb/>Let stolid people think who do not see
<lb/>What the point is beyond which I had passed.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Rise up," the Master said, "upon thy feet;
<lb/>The way is long, and difficult the road,
<lb/>And now the sun to middle-tierce returns."

<sb/>
<lb/>It was not any palace corridor
<lb/>There where we were, but dungeon natural,
<lb/>With floor uneven and unease of light.

<sb/>
<lb/>"Ere from the abyss I tear myself away,
<lb/>My Master," said I when I had arisen,
<lb/>"To draw me from an error speak a little;

<sb/>
<lb/>Where is the ice? and how is this one fixed
<lb/>Thus upside down? and how in such short time
<lb/>From eve to morn has the sun made his transit?"

<sb/>
<lb/>And he to me: "Thou still imaginest
<lb/>Thou art beyond the centre, where I grasped
<lb/>The hair of the fell worm, who mines the world.

<sb/>
<lb/>That side thou wast, so long as I descended;
<lb/>When round I turned me, thou didst pass the point
<lb/>To which things heavy draw from every side,

<sb/>
<lb/>And now beneath the hemisphere art come
<lb/>Opposite that which overhangs the vast
<lb/>Dry-land, and 'neath whose cope was put to death

<sb/>
<lb/>The Man who without sin was born and lived.
<lb/>Thou hast thy feet upon the little sphere
<lb/>Which makes the other face of the Judecca.

<sb/>
<lb/>Here it is morn when it is evening there;
<lb/>And he who with his hair a stairway made us
<lb/>Still fixed remaineth as he was before.

<sb/>
<lb/>Upon this side he fell down out of heaven;
<lb/>And all the land, that whilom here emerged,
<lb/>For fear of him made of the sea a veil,

<sb/>
<lb/>And came to our hemisphere; and peradventure
<lb/>To flee from him, what on this side appears
<lb/>Left the place vacant here, and back recoiled."

<sb/>
<lb/>A place there is below, from Beelzebub
<lb/>As far receding as the tomb extends,
<lb/>Which not by sight is known, but by the sound

<sb/>
<lb/>Of a small rivulet, that there descendeth
<lb/>Through chasm within the stone, which it has gnawed
<lb/>With course that winds about and slightly falls.

<sb/>
<lb/>The Guide and I into that hidden road
<lb/>Now entered, to return to the bright world;
<lb/>And without care of having any rest

<sb/>
<lb/>We mounted up, he first and I the second,
<lb/>Till I beheld through a round aperture
<lb/>Some of the beauteous things that Heaven doth bear;

<sb/>
<lb/>Thence we came forth to rebehold the stars.

</pouch_ring>
</circle>
</body>
</inferno>